<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book"><chapter index="4" title="The Third Truth: the Cessation of Suffering The Fourth Truth: the Path of Peace - Part One" pagetitle="Module 4" tocentry="The Third Truth: the Cessation of Suffering The Fourth Truth: the Path of Peace - Part One"><section index="1" title="The Third Truth of the Realised: Cessation (of Suffering)" pagetitle="The Third Truth of the Realised: Cessation (of Suffering)" tocentry="The Third Truth of the Realised: Cessation (of Suffering)"><paragraph> </paragraph><image width="470" src="module4_files.image002.png" align=""/><paragraph>We shall examine this in the following eight ways:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Definition of Nirvana</item><item>Difference between liberation and enlightenment</item><item>A classical analysis of this truth</item><item>4 levels of Hinayana result</item><item>4 types of arhat</item><item>Enlightenment's twofold benefit</item><item>Qualities</item><item>Activity</item></list><image width="452" src="module4_files.image003.png" align=""/><subsection title="Nirvana" pagetitle="Nirvana" tocentry="Nirvana"><subsubsection title="Defining what is not" pagetitle="Defining what is not" tocentry="Defining what is not">Defining what is not<paragraph>You may remember from Module One that <italic>nirvana</italic> is not a term defining "something". It is only telling us what is <italic>no longer present</italic> . It means "beyond suffering", meaning that all the suffering of samsara (First Truth) and all of its causes (Second Truth) have been removed.</paragraph><paragraph>What is there when samsara has finished? What is it like? There is no single answer to this question, as different Buddhist schools and traditions have their own understandings of "nirvana". Their differences can be significant yet fairly easy to describe. They can also be, to translate Naropa's own words to Marpa, "exceedingly, immensely profound". In this module, we will mainly study two things:</paragraph><paragraph><essential>· <bold>Liberation</bold> or <italic>just nirvana</italic> , the Hinayana goal.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>· <bold>Enlightenment</bold> or <italic>non-abiding nirvana</italic> , the Mahayana goal.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>The main point of this Third Truth is that suffering <italic>can</italic> be ended forever .</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Results by removal" pagetitle="Results by removal" tocentry="Results by removal">Results by removal<paragraph>The goal, <italic>nirvana</italic> , can only be attained as the consequence of a long, intelligent, industrious process. It is a type of result is known as <italic>result through removal</italic> . This is usually compared by our lamas to emptying a room. The empty room results from removal (of the furniture etc.) but all the effort of shifting the armchairs and tables does not actually "create" the emptiness (voidness) itself. The space of the room was always there and remains unchanged. No one can "create" space: one can only remove whatever was obstructing it. Perhaps another, more vivid, example is that of drawing back thick curtains on a bright morning. The sun was already shining outside and the room was already full of receptive space and reflective surfaces yet the presence of the curtains made it a dark room. By pulling back the curtains, the room becomes filled with bright sunlight. However, the effort of moving the curtains does not create the light itself. The sun does that.</paragraph><paragraph>This point is important. When you construct a house the end result is composed of the materials that you have been handling for months—bricks, timber, paint and the like? However, when we do all the dharma work of the "path", the end result does not need at all to resemble the study, meditation, prostrations and so forth we have been doing for years, because those things served primarily to remove, not to construct.</paragraph><paragraph>Dharma is a destructive or deconstructive process. Some examples:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item>By removing busyness and agitation, there is natural peace.</item><item>By removing endless desires, there is natural satisfaction.</item><item>By removing self-centredness, there emerges a natural awareness of others and care for them.</item><item>By removing illusions, there is natural lucidity about things.</item><item>By removing fear of loss and stinginess, there is natural generosity.</item></list><paragraph>There are endless such examples. Nirvana is the 100% destruction of all the <italic>personal</italic> samsara forever and that includes the thorough elimination of samsara's causes. The destruction of <italic>everyone's</italic> samsara is another question.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Freedom - Cessation and Vimuktikaya" pagetitle="Freedom - Cessation and Vimuktikaya" tocentry="Freedom - Cessation and Vimuktikaya">Freedom - Cessation and Vimuktikaya<paragraph>The focus of this Third Truth is on freedom. The entire notion of "freedom" only makes sense in terms of the bondage from which someone has been freed or remains free. To no longer carry the karma of suffering is a freedom. To no longer have a mind pained by unfulfilled desires is a freedom. To be beyond anger is a freedom. To no longer be reborn into suffering is the greatest freedom. Those whose minds long for freedom should know that there is no greater freedom than this.</paragraph><paragraph>The Hinayana view of nirvana is simply the ending of samsara: "like a candle completely burned out". The term <italic>cessation</italic> fits perfectly. The non-abiding nirvana achieved in Mahayana Buddhism (see below) is not just the end of the suffering but also the total awakening of the buddha mind. The buddha mind has many facets or <italic>kaya</italic> and this particular facet—of <underline>absence of</underline> samsara and of samsara's causes—is called the <italic>vimuktikaya</italic> . <italic>Vimukti</italic> means total liberation. The <underline>presence of</underline> enlightened qualities is, in this context, known as <italic>dharmakaya</italic> . Dharmakaya and vimuktikaya occur as a pair, in the scriptures, to make clear what <italic>is</italic> and what <italic>is not</italic> part of enlightenment.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Why teach this Truth?" pagetitle="Why teach this Truth?" tocentry="Why teach this Truth?">Why teach this Truth?<paragraph>Cessation is an extremely profound topic. One of the main points about it is its indescribability. The Buddha taught whatever can be said about it—and we learn about it—because, by appreciating the point of this Third Truth (freedom from samsara), we will be inspired to dedicate our lives to the path of practice, which is the Fourth Truth. From reflection upon this Third Truth comes heartfelt conviction that total freedom from samsara is possible and that the bonds imprisoning the mind can be broken forever. It is harder to follow a path when one has no idea where it is going.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="A classical approach to the Third Truth" pagetitle="A classical approach to the Third Truth" tocentry="A classical approach to the Third Truth">A classical approach to the Third Truth<paragraph>As with the previous two truths, it is presented through four aspects denoted by four key terms: <bold>cessation, peace, excellence</bold> and <bold>definite transcendence</bold> .</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Cessation</italic> </bold> is defined as the end of suffering and its causes (karma and afflictions). This is not a temporary end but a definite end, as not only are those things removed but also any habitual tendency related to them has been removed. Thus, there is no remaining cause for them to reoccur. This point is the continued <italic>absence</italic> of any of those elements of samsara.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Peace</italic> </bold> is a term that is often substituted for <italic>nirvana</italic> . Whereas the previous term points to what was abandoned, this term points to the lasting happiness that is thereby achieved. <italic>Peace</italic> does not mean a great sleep—the ultimate cosmic tranquilizer—but denotes a clarity that cannot be troubled. In that sense, it is like the terms unruffled, unperturbed or untroubled. This is in stark contrast to samsara, which is naturally <italic>disturbed</italic> and chaotic. Samsaric life demands constant effort and attention. Things can go wrong at any moment, through the eruption of emotions inside or karmic surprises outside.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Excellence</italic> </bold> refers to the qualities present in nirvana. This is the translation of the Sanskrit <italic>pra</italic>  <italic>ṉī</italic>  <italic>ta</italic> which means <italic>the very best</italic> . There is no better than this, the purest, most liberated state possible for any mind.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Definite transcendence</italic> </bold> is a term highlighting the transcendent nature of nirvana. Unlike the ups-and-downs of samsara, where there can be ecstasy and seemingly wonderful times but which then change into something else, this is transcendent forever.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="Nirvana and Enlightenment" pagetitle="Nirvana and Enlightenment" tocentry="Nirvana and Enlightenment"><image width="461" src="module4_files.image005.png" align=""/><paragraph>As mentioned above, the Hinayana and Mahayana differ in their understanding of what is to be accomplished in the Third Truth. Both agree that the main point is that three things—samsaric suffering, karma and the afflictions—are eliminated definitively. Thereby, suffering and its causes are destroyed and "nirvana" is attained. However, the Mahayanists consider that the incredibly long-lasting peace attained through the Hinayana path of meditation and wisdom <italic>is not the ultimate peace</italic>  <italic>and nirvana</italic> that the Buddha himself attained and that, ultimately, all his followers will attain. In order to achieve the Mahayana nirvana—"non-abiding nirvana"—the dualistic split and dualistic thought (see Module 3) need also to be totally eliminated. Only then can all the glorious, natural qualities of enlightenment shine forth.</paragraph><paragraph>For Mahayanists, the Hinayana journey is seen as primarily one of renouncing samsara and withdrawing into the profound peace of concentration meditation —as outlined through the Four Dhyana and the Four Formless Meditations in the section on immobility karma in Module 3. This ever-deepening absorption in meditation has its own strong magnetic power. What happens is that the meditator finds more and more satisfaction as the mind furthers its refinement and stability. There is a natural wish to take the process further and a feeling of renunciation develops more and more pronouncedly, because samsara's chaotic meaninglessness is witnessed from a place of deep, inner peace. Although, with respect to other people, the meditator will naturally become a kinder, more tranquil person through this process, the preoccupation with withdrawal and renunciation does not encourage putting compassionate action to the forefront.</paragraph><paragraph><essential>Concentration meditation is also employed in the Mahayana path—mainly as a <underline>support</underline> for the development of wisdom, as insight into the mind. But the Mahayana is extremely wary of meditation's inherent magnetic pull. Recognising that compassion is the main quality needed for attaining a Buddha's enlightenment, Mahayanists precede, underpin and finish all meditation with the good compassionate heart, keeping the motivation fixed on all sentient beings' welfare rather than one's own preoccupation with meditative prowess; with meditation's beauty, with peace for ineself. The end result is to achieve a <italic>non-abiding nirvana,</italic> so-called because:</essential></paragraph><list kind="ul"><item><essential>Great compassion prevents it from dwelling in the Hinayana peace.</essential></item><item><essential>Non-dual wisdom, rooted in meditation, prevents it dwelling in samsara.</essential></item></list><subsubsection title="Why did the Buddha not teach everyone Mahayana?" pagetitle="Why did the Buddha not teach everyone Mahayana?" tocentry="Why did the Buddha not teach everyone Mahayana?">Why did the Buddha not teach everyone Mahayana?<paragraph><essential>Why did the Buddha teach the Hinayana way? Why did he not teach everyone the path based on love and compassion and non-dual wisdom? He simply could not, because such a path is not suited for everyone and the very characteristic of the Buddha's teaching is to teach what is best suited to a person's capacities and aspirations. The ambitious perspective of Mahayana—that of helping all sentient beings—would be far too daunting for many people. Many people need first to find solutions to their own confusion and to taste the peaceful stability of meditation before they can even consider thinking of helping others.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Gampopa explains the Buddha's teaching of the Hinayana path through an analogy and then goes on to describe what happens at the end of the Hinayana path, when the arhats "migrate" to Mahayana:</paragraph><paragraph>"What they achieve is not actually nirvana. At the time of their achievement they will, on account of a condition of subtle, latent ignorance, acquire and exist in a subtle mental body, brought about by their [former] untainted karma. However, they themselves are convinced that the state of untainted profound absorption they enjoy <italic>is</italic> the nirvana and that they <italic>have attained</italic> nirvana: it is not real nirvana though and this may lead some to question the propriety of the Buddha teaching those two paths (Hinayana and Mahayana).</paragraph><paragraph>It was, in fact, extremely appropriate for the Buddha to teach them as he did. Let us consider the following example. Some merchants from Rose Apple Land <a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>set out to the far-off oceans to obtain its precious gems. At one point in their journey, while crossing a great wilderness, they felt so tired and downhearted that they started thinking that they would never manage to get the jewels and they contemplated turning back. However their leader created, through his magical powers, a great illusory citadel where they were able to rest and recuperate their strength. Once fortified, they set off in good spirits and succeeded in their quest.</paragraph><paragraph>Like the merchants in the example, beings with little strength of resolution will be quite afraid when they learn about the tremendous wisdom of the buddhas and may feel that the task of achieving it is too daunting; far beyond the capacity of the likes of them. On account of the awe they feel, they will either never undertake the task of enlightenment or else they will [start out but] give up. By teaching the two paths of the Shravaka and Pratyekabuddha, the Buddha enables them to attain the refreshing, healing state of Shravaka or Pratyekabuddha. In the <italic>Sublime Dharma White Lotus Sutra</italic> it says:</paragraph><paragraph>Likewise all the Shravaka are under the impression that they have attained nirvana. The Buddha tells them this is not nirvana but a respite.</paragraph><paragraph>When they have rested and refreshed themselves in the state of Shravaka or Pratyekabuddha, the Buddha knows it is time to encourage them to achieve full enlightenment. How is this done? The Buddha inspires them through perfect body, pure speech and wisdom mind. Light rays stream from his mind. By these beams merely touching their mental bodies, the Shravaka and Pratyekabuddha are awakened from their untainted profound absorption. Then the Buddha manifests his own perfect presence and says the following with his pure speech:</paragraph><paragraph>O monks. By merely doing what you have done, the task is not being accomplished and the work is not yet done. Your nirvana is not <italic>the</italic> nirvana. Monks! Now approach the Tathagata and pay heed to what he says; understand his instruction.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus he motivates them. This is also taught in the verses of the <italic>Sublime Dharma White Lotus Sutra</italic>:</paragraph><paragraph>O monks! I therefore tell you today that by merely this you will not attain nirvana and that for you to gain the pristine cognition of the omniscient ones you must give rise to a noble and mighty wave of effort. By so doing, you will achieve all-knowing pristine cognition.</paragraph><paragraph>Through being exhorted in this way, the Shravaka and Pratyekabuddha will cultivate the great bodhicitta. Having conducted themselves as bodhisattvas for countless ages, they will become buddhas. We find this stated in the <italic>Sublime Dharma White Lotus Sutra</italic> in the same way as it is stated in the <italic>Going to Lanka Sutra</italic>:</paragraph><paragraph>Those Shravaka who have not attained nirvana will all, through having practiced the bodhisattva way of life, become buddhas."</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>end of quotation from Gampopa (Gems of Dharma, Jewels of Freedom)</italic> </paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="A Hinayana Understanding of Nirvana" pagetitle="A Hinayana Understanding of Nirvana" tocentry="A Hinayana Understanding of Nirvana"><image width="461" src="module4_files.image006.png" align=""/><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Four Stages of Attainment</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph><essential>There are four major stages of attainment in the Hinayana journey to total freedom from samsara:</essential></paragraph><list kind="ol"><item><essential>Stream-entrant.</essential></item><item><essential>One-time returner.</essential></item><item><essential>Non-returner.</essential></item><item><essential>Arhat. <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></essential></item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Stream Entrant</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>The stream entered is that of the Noble Eightfold Path. The stream-entrant is one who:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Has overcome the power of illusions of self.</item><item>Has overcome sceptical doubt, in particular about karma and reincarnation.</item><item>Has given up attachment to rituals, especially those based in an idea that spirituality is accomplished by austerities and asceticism.</item><item>Has opened the eye of dharma, meaning that there is much intuitive understanding of dharma through mastery of study and meditation.</item><item>Has virtuous conduct.</item><item>Has confidence in the Three Precious Refuges.</item></list><paragraph>In brief, like someone who has fallen into the current of a strong river, this person will be swept forward by dharma, which has become so strongly implanted that nothing can reverse it. Such a person is seen as attaining liberation in, at most, seven lifetimes. The stream-entrant can no longer be reborn in the lower realms.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>One-time Returner</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Following on from the above, the disciple will reach a point where the next incarnation in samsara will be the last one: the one in which liberation (arhat state) is attained. At this stage there is freedom from:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Belief in self.</item><item>Sceptical doubt.</item><item>Attachment to austerities and ritual.</item><item>(The gross aspects of) sensual craving.</item><item>(The gross aspects of) ill-will.</item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Non-Returner</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This is someone actually in the last reincarnation in the sensorial dimension of samsara. After death, it is possible for such a person to be reborn in the pure deva realms (see Module 2), where meditation practice will be brought to completion. At this stage there are five freedoms:</paragraph><paragraph>1. From belief in self.</paragraph><paragraph>2. From sceptical doubt.</paragraph><paragraph>3. From attachment to austerities and rituals.</paragraph><paragraph>4. From sensual craving.</paragraph><paragraph>5. From ill-will.</paragraph><paragraph>Yet there are still traces of the following five blockages:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Fine craving for material existence (meaning the meditative absorptions of the Four Dhyana {see Module 2}).</item><item>Fine craving for immaterial existence (the Four Formless Absorptions).</item><item>Pride.</item><item>Restlessness.</item><item>Ignorance.</item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Arhat - one who has achieved nirvana</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Also found as <italic>arhant</italic> or <italic>arahant</italic> . The word means <italic>noble one</italic> implying <italic>one who has laid down the burden</italic> . The Tibetan translation means <italic>one who has defeated the enemy</italic> , the enemy being suffering and its causes. This is someone who has attained total liberation, being forever free from all the ten blockages mentioned above.</paragraph><paragraph>Mipham Rinpoche, in his teachings on abhidharma, defines four types of arhat:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item> Arhat with remainders applies during the period of time between attaining the arhat state and death. If we take the Hinayana understanding of the Buddha's own life, as an example, it applies to the forty-five years between his "enlightenment" (which for them means becoming an arhat) and his passing into total nirvana. An arhat with remainders is therefore someone who has extinguished all causes of suffering yet still has some suffering-as-results to live through and it is these karmic results that keep them alive. Once the karma has run out, they die: samsara is over.</item><item> Arhat without remainders is one in whom all suffering and causes of suffering have been extinguished. This is attained when the arhat with remainders dies.</item><item> Unadorned arhats are those who have solely achieved freedom.</item><item> Adorned arhats have achieved freedom but also have many special qualities and accomplishments, due to long practice of many different forms of meditation.</item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>The Sixteen Great Arhats</italic> </bold> </paragraph><image width="455" src="module4_files.image007.png" align=""/><image width="455" src="module4_files.image008.png" align=""/><paragraph>For a remarkable drawing of the 16 Arhats, by His Holiness the Seventeenth Gyalwa Karmapa, please visit <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/17k16arhat.jpg">here</a>(many thanks to Karma Triyana for permission to use).</paragraph><paragraph>Many people achieved the state of arhat in the early days of Buddhism. In the first council we hear of a gathering of five hundred <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>arhats and there are many mentions of them in large number. As the centuries passed, the numbers dwindled and none are spoken of in recent times.</paragraph><paragraph>In Chinese Buddhism, sixteen famous arhats are particularly venerated. In a spirit similar to that of the bodhisattvas, these sixteen decided not to pass into nirvana but to remain to help beings, taking up residence in the various continents of our world as it appeared to be to people in India and China two millennia ago. Their names and abodes are given in <a href="#Arhat16">Annexe 1</a>.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Non-Abiding Nirvana of the Mahayana" pagetitle="The Non-Abiding Nirvana of the Mahayana" tocentry="The Non-Abiding Nirvana of the Mahayana"><image width="461" src="module4_files.image009.png" align=""/><paragraph>We will consider this from two angles:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>What is removed or avoided to attain it.</item><item>Its attainment, "enlightenment", as explained by Maitreya.</item><item>Its qualities and activity (very briefly, as these will be developed in later modules).</item></list><paragraph> <bold>1. What is removed or avoided to attain it</bold> </paragraph><image width="261" src="module4_files.image010.png" align=""/><paragraph>Progress on the path equates to obstacles being removed. Those obstacles are karma, the afflictions and duality. Their removal, in whole or in part, allows the natural qualities that they have been blocking to appear. In Year Two, we will enter into the detail of the five major stages of the Buddhist path. Each stage, and indeed many a sub-stage, has its own particular area of things to be worked on and eliminated.</paragraph><paragraph>Throughout this dharma journey, two major motor forces are employed to bring this about: wisdom and compassion. These can also be called <italic>wisdom and skilful means</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Wisdom</bold> means a deep realisation of voidness. It develops through first study, then intelligent reflection and finally meditation on such things as:</paragraph><paragraph>· The impermanent nature of everything (absence of lasting entity).</paragraph><paragraph>· The absence of own entity, because of interdependence.</paragraph><paragraph>· The dream-like nature of all things (absence of objective reality).</paragraph><paragraph>· The fact that involvement with illusions of <italic>permanence</italic> and <italic>self</italic> cause suffering.</paragraph><paragraph>Throughout the path, it is such understanding which keeps one away from <bold>samsara</bold> . The wisdom, established by thorough investigation, becomes more complete and more profound as the path progresses and becomes 100% perfect with buddhahood. In particular, this wisdom comes to focus on the non-dual, void nature of each moment of relative perception and on the ultimate buddha nature which permeates all.</paragraph><paragraph><essential>As mentioned just now, there are three steps to wisdom: study, reflection and meditation:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1. <italic>Study</italic> means the proper acquisition of information. This usually happens through formal oral teachings, the study of texts and discussion with the sangha. This involves mastering the specialised and precise terminology of dharma, which in turn makes it possible to reason clearly and intelligently.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. <italic>Reflection</italic> means a deep consideration of the meaning of what has been studied. In particular, it involves comparing one's own habitual feelings and ideas with what has been learnt. Any conflict or area of doubt needs to be resolved. The personal counsel of dharma masters is often the means for doing this.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3. <italic>Meditation</italic> does not mean simply sitting meditation, although that is part of the process. The actual term actually means <italic>familiarisation</italic> . This is well-expressed by the English expression <italic>becoming second nature</italic> (the words of which make little sense when translated back into Tibetan!). When the truths of dharma no longer need to be thought about but are vivid realities, shining second after second, this third stage has been achieved.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Compassion</bold> or <bold>Skilful Means</bold> is an immense topic. It could be described as <italic>accumulation and purification</italic> . It is best explained in detail through the first five of the six <italic>paramita</italic> , which will be developed at length in Year Two of this course. Compassion, which starts out as an attitude, becomes an entire way of life—a way of being—as a certain softness, warmth, generosity, selflessness, tolerance and broad-mindedness mature in the person. It becomes an inimitable strength of goodness and virtue. This goes hand-in-hand with the dwindling of painful karma and the increase of positive karma. The whole shines like light and serves also as an important basis for wisdom. Mahayana wisdom is not cold, dry, intellectual wisdom but, because it is "moistened" by compassion, the warm wisdom of the famous "good heart". The spontaneous and <underline>selfless</underline> care for all beings that emerges from all this will automatically counter the <underline>self-centred</underline> magnetic pull of concentration meditation, and this prevents one from undertaking the journey to the " <bold>mere nirvana</bold> " of the Hinayana.</essential></paragraph></subsection><subsection title="2. Enlightenment" pagetitle="2. Enlightenment" tocentry="2. Enlightenment"><image width="162" src="module4_files.image011.png" align=""/><paragraph>The main point of enlightenment is without doubt its freedom from samsara, on one hand, and the "acquisition <a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a>" of the three kayas, on the other. Everything mentioned in Module 1 concerning the three kayas is very relevant here, so please refer back to it and make a big mental note that <italic>enlightenment means becoming the three kayas</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>In Module 18, we will explore enlightenment in detail, according to Maitreya's teachings. What follows is a summary of its eight main points presented through eight key notions.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>enlightenment</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>main point</bold> </td><td> <bold>key notion</bold> </td></tr><tr><td>its nature</td><td>purity</td></tr><tr><td>its cause</td><td>it is an achievement</td></tr><tr><td>as a fruition</td><td>it is freedom</td></tr><tr><td>its function</td><td>twofold benefit</td></tr><tr><td>as a basis</td><td>important qualities</td></tr><tr><td>its manifestation</td><td>the three kayas</td></tr><tr><td>its permanence</td><td>it endures</td></tr><tr><td>its inconceivability</td><td>non-conceptual suchness</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Nature</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>The nature of enlightenment is " <bold>purity</bold> " and this is explained, in the commentaries, as meaning <bold>lucid clarity <a href="#_ftn5"> <bold>[5]</bold> </a></bold> —a term which signifies both wisdom and purity. The wisdom (lucidity) of the buddha mind is compared to the brilliant shining of the Sun and its purity (clarity) to the vastness of the unobstructed space in which the Sun shines.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Cause</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Enlightenment, a result by removal, is something <bold>achieved</bold> principally by bring wisdom to its fullness. Above, we saw that the three major steps of wisdom are <italic>study, reflection</italic> and <italic>meditation</italic> . A Buddha's wisdom is hard for us to imagine and it is helpful to understand it as being the final end of a long journey of cultivating the third of these steps—meditation. From the outset, it has two key aspects:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>The first is cultivated during the most profound moments of meditation and is an unveiling of the formless, non-conceptual, void nature of mind itself. This is called  non-conceptual wisdom.  </item><item>The second aspect, cultivated in the post-meditation phase, is an intelligent understanding of the millions of things ( dharma ) of life. It is called  analytical wisdom.  </item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Fruition</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>As a result, enlightenment is a freedom:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Simply by dwelling in the sheer transcendence of non-conceptual wisdom , desire and the other afflictions will fade away.</item><item> Analytical wisdom knows each thing through each its specific details but, most importantly, also knows it to be not other than that very mind which recognises its own voidness in deep meditation. Mind, in post-meditation, is experiencing its karmic "movie", which seems "other" but is not other, just as a foreign land in a dream seems like a place being visited but is none other than the mind of the dreamer. Analytical wisdom helps overcome duality.</item></list><paragraph>When these two wisdoms are totally perfected, the fruition achieved is enlightenment.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Function</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>The function of enlightenment is to accomplish what is known as the <bold>twofold benefit</bold>:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item> Benefit for oneself as the highest freedom and realisation.</item><item> Benefit for others through enlightened activity.</item></list><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Endowments</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Enlightenment is endowed with endless qualities, of which fifteen are particularly highlighted. The first of these, and the most important, is it <bold>inconceivability</bold> . Enlightenment cannot be imagined and cannot be made real by thought. When it happens, it knows itself. Nothing else can <italic>know</italic> it.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Actualisation</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Technically, it is under this heading that we find enlightenment as the <bold>three kayas</bold> . These have already been presented in general in Module One and will be developed through eight qualities each in Module Eighteen. We can relate this back to the twofold benefit, mentioned above. The dharmakaya is ultimate benefit for oneself and the two form kayas (sambhogakaya and nirmanakaya) are supreme benefit for others.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Permanence</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Enlightenment, as the three kayas, is permanent in three different ways:</paragraph><paragraph>1. The dharmakaya is naturally permanent, without beginning or end.</paragraph><paragraph>2. The sambhogakaya is permanent by its unceasing manifestation of pure lands to deeply-realised bodhisattvas.</paragraph><paragraph>3. The nirmanakaya is permanent by always having some manifestation somewhere, even though each of these manifestations is relatively short-lasting (for instance the eighty years of Sakyamuni Buddha's life on earth.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Inconceivability</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This topic comes back again and again as we explore the various facets of enlightenment. It was mentioned above, as one of the fifteen endowments of enlightenment. Here it is highlighted as being the eighth and final main quality of enlightenment.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Enlightened Qualities &amp; Activity" pagetitle="Enlightened Qualities &amp; Activity" tocentry="Enlightened Qualities &amp; Activity"><image width="218" src="module4_files.image012.png" align=""/><paragraph>These two important points will be developed more fully in Module Eighteen. Here they, will be mentioned in brief.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Enlightened qualities</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph><essential>They are often summed up as the <bold>sixty-four qualities of enlightenment:</bold> </essential></paragraph><list kind="ul"><item><essential>The <bold>4 Fearlessnesses</bold> .</essential></item><item><essential>The <bold>10 Powers of Perfect Knowledge</bold> .</essential></item><item><essential>The <bold>18 Distinctive Qualities</bold> of a Buddha.</essential></item><item><essential>The <bold>32 extraordinary marks</bold> of a Buddha.</essential></item></list><paragraph>To these we can add the 80 minor signs, 60 qualities of speech and so forth, some of which are in the annexes to Module One.</paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Enlightened activity</italic> </bold> </paragraph><paragraph>The actual forms that this activity takes are infinite, breath-taking in their variety and filled with grace, power and splendour. Enlightened activity is the response of the omniscient wisdom, total compassion and skill of ultimate reality to the confusion and suffering of beings in the world.</paragraph><paragraph>The texts concentrate, therefore, not so much on the myriad forms of compassionate emanation but on the nature of enlightened activity itself.</paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Enlightened activity</bold> is distinguished by two qualities:</essential></paragraph><list kind="ol"><item><essential>Its <bold>spontaneity</bold> .</essential></item><item><essential>The fact that <bold>it does not conceptualise</bold> .</essential></item></list><paragraph> <bold>The spontaneity</bold> of enlightened activity is an innate quality, like that of a mirror to reflect. Just as a mirror does not need to make any effort to reflect a person in front of it yet nevertheless sends back a perfect image, so does the buddha mind not have to make any effort to send the perfect response to a person's needs. Other examples are those of the rain falling from monsoon clouds or the Sun shining or the earth supporting plants, animals and humans. In all these cases, the beneficial object just simply is what it is, and does what it does, without any effort at all.</paragraph><paragraph>The <bold>non-thinking</bold> quality of the buddha mind is an extension of the above. The Sun does not need to think about each plant it will ripen, nor does a mirror need to plan how to reflect this or that object. This point of non-conceptualising is highlighted because, in the normal way of things, successful actions require planning and clever thought. Often our activity goes wrong because we did not think well enough about what we were doing. The activity of a buddha mind bares no similarity to the activity of an ordinary mind.</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="2" title="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace" pagetitle="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace" tocentry="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace"><subsection title="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace" pagetitle="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace" tocentry="The Fourth Truth of the Realised: The Path of Peace"><image width="389" src="module4_files.image013.png" align=""/><paragraph>The nirvana described in the pages above will never just happen, one day, all by itself. A path of diligent self-transformation needs to be followed: the famous Path of Peace. We will investigate this through several points:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>A classical definition through four terms.</item><item>The "Five Phases of the Path" description of the dharma journey. This works for both Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhism.</item><item>A brief review of the 37 Factors of Enlightenment associated with the Five Phases.</item><item>The Mahayana 'Five Phases'.</item><item>A closer look at mindfulness, the starting-point of the actual practice of the path.</item></list></subsection><subsection title="Classical analysis through Four Key Points" pagetitle="Classical analysis through Four Key Points" tocentry="Classical analysis through Four Key Points"><paragraph>As with the previous three Truths, this is presented through four key points: <bold>path, intelligent awareness, accomplishment</bold> and <bold>definite emergence</bold> .</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Path</bold> is a word defining this Fourth Truth as a journey. It is a long and progressive journey leading eventually to the cessation of suffering, explained in the Third Truth. The path consists of blending ethical conduct, meditation and wisdom development into a personal transformation known famously as <italic>following the path of peace</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Intelligent awareness</bold> (Sanskrit <italic>vidya,</italic> Tibetan <italic>rig pa</italic> ). In this context <a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a>, this is wise awareness focused on the true nature of reality. Its opposite, <italic>avidya</italic> , is the ignorance which lies at the very root of samsara (as we saw in the Second Truth, Interdepen-dence). The Buddhist path opens up clear awareness—"clarity"—concerning ultimate reality. It is centred on developing this clarity, as this automatically dispels ego delusions and, by consequence, the whole samsaric process.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Accomplishment</bold> refers to the diligent work of actually treading the path; making it a reality. This achievement is based on modelling oneself devotedly on the example set by the Buddha.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Definite emergence</bold> or renunciation is the real turning away, step by step, from samsara. This is directly related to the fourth point of the Third Truth—definite transcendence—and is, in fact, its cause. Definite transcendence is the end result of this progressive turning away from the afflictions and harmful karma.</paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Five Phases of the Path" pagetitle="The Five Phases of the Path" tocentry="The Five Phases of the Path"><paragraph>One of the earliest ways of analysing the journey to liberation was through the "five phases of the path". These portray the necessary and inevitable transformations that the mind must go through in order to get rid of its karma and harmful habits, as well as to acquire deep meditative experience and penetrative wisdom. With the advent of Mahayana Buddhism, this same, essential, fivefold model was maintained, with its detailed explanation being adapted to suit the actual Mahayana journey.</paragraph>thirty-seven factors of awakeningsamadhi,bsam gtan<image width="44" src="module4_files.image014.png" align=""/><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>The Universal Five Phases of the Path</bold>  <bold>&amp; the Thirty-Seven Factors of Awakening</bold> </td></tr><tr><td><essential> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold>Phase 5: No More Training</bold> </essential></td><td> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Phase 4: Cultivation</bold> </td><td> <bold>The Eightfold Path</bold> </td></tr><tr><td/><td><essential> <bold>Phase 3: Insight</bold> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold>Seven Aspects of Awakening</bold> </essential></td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Phase 2: Integration</bold> </td><td>"Highest Wordly"</td><td> <bold>5 Powers</bold> </td></tr><tr><td>"Forbearance"</td></tr><tr><td>"Summit"</td><td> <bold>5 Faculties</bold> </td></tr><tr><td>"Warming"</td></tr><tr><td><essential> <bold> </bold> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold>Phase 1: Accumulation</bold> </essential></td><td><essential>Greater</essential></td><td><essential> <bold>4 feet of miracles</bold> </essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>Middling</essential></td><td><essential> <bold>4 Eliminations</bold> </essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>Lesser</essential></td><td><essential> <bold>4 foundations of mindfulness</bold> </essential></td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph> <bold>The Phase of Accumulation</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This covers an immense area, from a beginner's first steps in dharma through to profound stability in meditation and considerable purity of being. Many a famous saint or reincarnate lama would still have been technically in this stage. It can be summed up as three major steps:</paragraph><paragraph>· Getting to understand oneself and the world.</paragraph><paragraph>· Changing one's life radically in the light of that knowledge.</paragraph><paragraph>· Thoroughly refining the mind.</paragraph><paragraph>This makes a lot of sense. Just as someone cannot repair a car engine without first understanding how it works and then what has gone wrong, so likewise a life cannot seriously be transformed without first having clear knowledge of its mechanisms, its positive points and its errors. Then, once it is working well, one can fine-tune its qualities. These three steps, which correspond to the three stages of the phase of accumulation, are classically presented as:</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Four Foundations of Mindfulness</bold> , which bring vivid and direct awareness of:</paragraph><paragraph>1. Physical reality.</paragraph><paragraph>2. Feelings.</paragraph><paragraph>3. Mind.</paragraph><paragraph>4. Phenomena.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Four Eliminations</bold> or four transformations:</paragraph><paragraph>5. Eliminating what is harmful in one's life.</paragraph><paragraph>6. Making sure not to introduce any new harmful thing.</paragraph><paragraph>7. Increasing what is helpful in one's life.</paragraph><paragraph>8. Introducing new helpful skills.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Four Feet of Miracles <a href="#_ftn7"> <bold>[7]</bold> </a></bold>:</paragraph><paragraph>9. Profound absorption through unbroken longing.</paragraph><paragraph>10. Profound absorption through unbroken diligence.</paragraph><paragraph>11. Profound absorption through unbroken intention.</paragraph><paragraph>12. Profound absorption through unbroken analysis.</paragraph><paragraph>The above form the first twelve of the thirty-seven factors of enlightenment.</paragraph><paragraph>In actual reality, someone first turning up at a dharma centre will not automatically be given the <bold>Four Foundations of Mindfulnes</bold> s as a first practice. Some people learn simple concentration meditations, others learn vajrayana practices such as Chenrezik and so on and so forth. "Be mindful" is a common counsel and any of those practices can become the basis for developing mindfulness and self-knowledge. What we are considering, in these five phases of the path and thirty-seven factors, is a simplified, idealised journey. In it, the importance of mindfulness can never be underestimated.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Four Eliminations</bold> , as you probably noticed, are in fact two areas of eliminating and two areas of nurturing. Together, they eliminate suffering. This phase is an enormous work, only completed when the person is truly, totally transformed. We could sum up these four eliminations by the two well-known ideas of <bold>purification</bold> and <bold>accumulation.</bold> </paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Four Feet of Miracles</bold> are a long work of meditation. This stage has to be long since layer after layer of affliction has to be removed. For instance, once strong passionate thoughts or angry thoughts have been overcome by persistent meditation practice, one discovers more subtle thoughts of passion and anger that were previously invisible. As these in turn are evaporated by meditation, yet another, even more subtle layer is revealed. Nine layers are mentioned <a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a>altogether.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>The Phase of Junction</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Most of the above work deals with a transformation of one's habitual existence, i.e. <bold>relative reality</bold> . The idea is to transform everything in one's life into something positive and helpful. The phase of junction complements this with an awakening to <bold>ultimate reality</bold> . It is called <italic>junction</italic> , or <italic>yoga</italic> or <italic>integration</italic> , because one is learning how to join the mind with what is ultimately true—voidness. This awakening is an intellectual one throughout this phase—not a direct awareness, which comes in the next phase—yet it is nevertheless very far-reaching. It happens in four steps:</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Warming</bold> , as one warms to voidness. The analogy here is one of approaching a large fire (fire of voidness which burns up illusions). Just as at one point, when approaching the fire, its heat will be first sensed, so this stage is the one in which the significance of voidness becomes appreciated.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Summit</bold> , or peak. The analogy here is one of a classical, conical mountain. The higher one goes, the less earth there is and the more space. At the top, there is a minimum of rock, a maximum of space and a panoramic view. At this stage the mind is going from one understanding of voidness to the next, moment after moment, with little hindrance.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Forbearance</bold> refers to an ability to forbear the reality-shattering implications of voidness, in the light of which age-old delusions crumble away.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Highest Worldly Thing</bold> is, as its name implies, the pinnacle of worldly existence: the last step in the journey to liberation from samsara. After this, there will be no more rebirth because of past karma. Samsara, although beginningless, has an end: this is it.</paragraph><paragraph>These four stages of the Phase of Junction are accomplished through ten more factors of enlightenment. These are in fact two sets of the same five things. During the stages of <bold>warming</bold> and <bold>summit</bold> they are called <bold>"five faculties"</bold> and during the stages of <bold>forbearance</bold> and <bold>highest worldly thing</bold> they are called <bold>"five powers"</bold> , because they have now become great strengths, due to skill in understanding voidness, applying it to one's life and facing its implications.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>The Five Faculties</bold> </td><td> <bold>The Five Powers</bold> </td></tr><tr><td>Faith Diligence Mindfulness Concentration Wisdom</td><td>Faith Diligence Mindfulness Concentration Wisdom</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph> <bold>The Phase of Insight</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This is the great breakthrough—an irreversible direct insight into the nature of truth. In the Hinayana, this means insight into the Four Noble Truths, with four stages to be accomplished for each truth <a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a>, making sixteen sub-stages in all. In the Mahayana, the breakthrough into the heart-meaning of the Four Truths is accomplished in a single stroke by direct realisation of voidness.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Seven Aspects of Awakening</bold>  <bold>(bodhi)</bold> are the seven factors of enlightenment operative during this phase:</paragraph><paragraph>Right mindfulness.</paragraph><paragraph>Right discerning appreciation.</paragraph><paragraph>Right diligence.</paragraph><paragraph>Right joy.</paragraph><paragraph>Right proficiency.</paragraph><paragraph>Right profound absorption.</paragraph><paragraph>Right equanimity.</paragraph><paragraph>You may notice that many of these factors have already been mentioned in previous phases. It is not that they are totally different here, but they are the qualities that have special relevance at this point and that combined form the tools needed to progress through this phase. Their nature is more subtle than before.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Phase of Cultivation</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This is also called the Phase of Meditation. Although insight has now been acquired, forever, the life-stream of the person is still not yet fully-liberated. In the light of the insight now gained, a long-term and increasingly-fine work of meditation has to be accomplished, until the finest of finest impurities/blockages have been radically removed. The factors of enlightenment required during this time are those of the famous <bold>eightfold path of the noble ones:</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>Right view.</paragraph><paragraph>Right concept.</paragraph><paragraph>Right expression.</paragraph><paragraph>Right limits of action.</paragraph><paragraph>Right livelihood.</paragraph><paragraph>Right effort.</paragraph><paragraph>Right mindfulness.</paragraph><paragraph>Right profound absorption.</paragraph><paragraph>At this level <bold>right view</bold> is of primordial importance. The other seven facets of the eightfold path all depend upon the view, which arises spontaneously from a direct awareness of voidness.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Phase Beyond Training</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>This is the end of the journey. For the Hinayanist, it is to become an arhat, and they consider that such a state is eternal. For the Mahayanist, it means becoming a Buddha. Since there is nothing left to be purified and nothing still to be attained, there is no training, no "practice" and hence no related factor of enlightenment.</paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Three Main Components of the Path" pagetitle="Three Main Components of the Path" tocentry="Three Main Components of the Path"><paragraph><essential>The Buddhist "path", described above, involves work in three areas:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Right conduct</bold> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Meditation</bold> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Wisdom</bold> development.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>Of these, the first concerns interaction with other sentient beings and the world at large. It principally involves actions (karma) of body and speech. The last two concern one's own 'mind karma' and inner experience. There is no aspect of Buddhism that is not included in the transformation of body, speech and mind and there is no Buddhist practice that falls outside these three key areas of development.</essential></paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Right conduct</bold> is traditionally based on vows or precepts, as these greatly reinforce the power of physical and verbal actions. In general it is based on avoiding the ten non-virtues and on cultivating the ten virtues. We will explore it in full in our studies of the <italic>paramita of right conduct</italic> next year. For the present, we should be aware of its two main areas:</paragraph><paragraph>1) Reducing and eliminating any harm done to others.</paragraph><paragraph>2) Increasing virtuous, positive qualities in oneself. To which the Mahayana adds</paragraph><paragraph>3) Acquiring skill in helping others.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Meditation</bold> is a direct working with the mind in order to overcome its harmful habits. This is primarily accomplished through concentration. As the meditator learns to maintain the mind focused on its object of meditation:</paragraph><paragraph>· The habitual power of thoughts and feelings to distract and occupy the mind is reduced.</paragraph><paragraph>· Peace and absorption are attained.</paragraph><paragraph>· Much self-knowledge is acquired in the process.</paragraph><paragraph>Meditation has the power to overcome the afflictions. Desires, anger, confusion, pride and jealousy will be naturally reduced by its regular practice. Ego thoughts will, to a certain extent, be laid bare and seen for the shallow illusions they are. <italic>However</italic> , the finest wisdom—especially pure insight into the Four Truths—will not necessarily emerge automatically. It may never emerge or take a long time, if unaided by the wisdom development mentioned next.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Wisdom development</bold> involves cultivating the three steps of wisdom: study, reflection and meditation. It is primarily focused on the Four Truths.</paragraph><paragraph>Just as concentration meditation will lead to peace but will not automatically give rise to wisdom, similarly wisdom development does not necessarily bring inner peace and stability nor does it reduce the afflictions. Wisdom and meditation complement each other and they are both made strong, healthy and meaningful by the strength of good karma obtained through a wholesome life of right conduct.</paragraph><paragraph>The abhidharma texts point out how dharma people are different. According to their past karma, some take easily to meditation and can develop great calm yet take a long time to awaken to wisdom's clarity. Others have natural access to much wisdom and insight yet are nervy and agitated, finding it hard to cultivate their meditation practice. The texts explain to Buddhist teachers how to help each one along the way, so that they acquire the skills they lack and use the ones they already possess to good advantage.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Refuge &amp; Precepts" pagetitle="Refuge &amp; Precepts" tocentry="Refuge &amp; Precepts"><image width="162" src="module4_files.image018.png" align=""/><paragraph>The way in which a person technically becomes a Buddhist is by formally "taking refuge" in the Buddha, Dharma and Sangha. This outer, ceremonial gesture is a reflection of the real refuge that forms the basis for all Buddhist practice, namely placing one's trust in the that which is worthy of trust and that can truly deliver the results. This extremely important topic will be treated in Module Five, once we have studied a little about the sangha and thereby completed this brief introduction to the Three Most Precious Refuges (Buddha, dharma and sangha - the <italic>triratna</italic> widely known as the Three Jewels).</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, the whole basis for right conduct is to take some degree of moral commitment not to harm other beings (and oneself). There are many levels of such commitment, suited to different lifestyles. They are known as "self-liberation vows" (Skt: <italic>pratimoksha</italic> ), since the free the mind from the shackles of what is harmful. These too will be treated in Module Five.</paragraph><paragraph>Refuge and precepts are universal in Buddhism, forming the working basis for Hinayana and Mahayana and Vajrayana forms of practice.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Mahayana Path" pagetitle="The Mahayana Path" tocentry="The Mahayana Path"><image width="461" src="module4_files.image019.png" align=""/><paragraph>Two thing absolutely dominate the Mahayana path: <bold>compassion</bold> and <bold>deepest wisdom</bold> (voidness). The path starts with compassion, is in itself the development of compassion and it ends as the total fullness of compassion. The basic mechanisms described in the five phases of the path above still apply in Mahayana. However, in Mahayana, that essential transformation of the human mind occurs within a context of total compassion and deeper wisdom and that changes everything. The results that emerge are different from those of the Hinayana path.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>The Mahayana Journey of the Five Phases of the Path</bold> </td></tr><tr><td><essential> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold>Phase 5: No Training</bold> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold> </bold> </essential></td></tr><tr><td/><td><essential> <bold>Phase 4: Cultivation</bold> </essential></td><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 10</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 9</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 8</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 7</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 6</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 5</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 4</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 3</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 2</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential> <bold>Phase 3: Insight</bold> </essential></td><td><essential>Bodhisattva Level 1</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential> <bold>Phase 2: Integration</bold> </essential></td><td><essential>"Highest Wordly"</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>"Forbearance"</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>"Summit"</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><essential>"Warming"</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td><essential> <bold> </bold> </essential></td><td><essential> <bold>Phase 1: Accumulation</bold> </essential></td><td><essential>Greater</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td><essential>Middling</essential></td><td/></tr><tr><td><essential>Lesser</essential></td><td/></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>The diagram above shows the five paths in the Mahayana context. It is characterised by the unique and all-important breakthrough of the Phase of Insight, described by bodhisattvas as the finest moment in their entire existence. Before that (area on green background), one is a "worldly being", going from one life to the next, in samsara, through the force of karma. Worldly beings are called "the immature" or "children" or "ordinary beings" or "individuals" in the texts. The terms can be deceptive, as many a great lama and some of the kindest people in this world still belong in that category.</paragraph><paragraph>At the Phase of Insight, lasting, direct insight—known as <italic>realisation</italic> —into the void nature of all things is not only gained but remains thereafter. Samsara is finished, as is rebirth through karma. One can understand why the Phase of Insight, which is also the 1st bodhisattva level, is called <italic>Supreme Joy</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>After insight, one traverses the ten bodhisattva levels ( pink background ) until all is perfect and one has become a buddha (yellow background ). The ten levels—technically known as the <italic>mahabodhisattva levels</italic> —are also a defining characteristic of the Mahayana path. The qualities and powers of the beings of light who dwell on those levels are greater than those of the arhat.</paragraph><paragraph>The final defining characteristic is that of the end result. As we saw above, in the Truth of Cessation, the "freedom from samsara" of an arhat and of a buddha is virtually the same. However, the very nature of a buddha's wisdom and purity, as well as the qualities and activity of a buddha, far exceed those of an arhat.</paragraph><paragraph><essential>Thus there are three distinct <bold>phases of being</bold>:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1) An "ordinary" being, or "immature" being, living in the six realms.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2) A great bodhisattva, experiencing "pure lands".</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3) A buddha.</essential></paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The bodhisattva vow" pagetitle="The bodhisattva vow" tocentry="The bodhisattva vow"><paragraph>Just as taking Refuge is the way in which one becomes Buddhist, taking the bodhisattva vow is the way in which one enters the Mahayana stream of Buddhism. As with Refuge, this is not merely a symbolic formality. The "vow" represents a heartfelt commitment and it is the influence of that commitment on the mind—or one could say its presence in the heart—that makes on a Mahayanist, or bodhisattva.</paragraph><paragraph><essential>The <bold>bodhisattva commitment</bold> has two distinct parts:</essential></paragraph><list kind="ol"><item><essential>The <bold>aspiration</bold> vow.</essential></item><item><essential>The <bold>practice</bold> vow.</essential></item></list><paragraph><essential>The first, <bold>bodhisattva aspiration</bold> , is often expressed as the profound wish to attain enlightenment, in order to be of benefit to all beings and bring them to enlightenment too. The implicit commitment is to nurture as purely as possible this wish, and its accompanying ethics, as the basic mental component of bodhicitta. The aspiration serves as a basis for the second—deeper— pledge, which is to commit this and future lives to the actual <bold>bodhisattva practice</bold> , resumed as the six <italic>paramita</italic> or perfections.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>These two vows are taken through ceremonies. In the Tibetan tradition, one would often wait until it were possible to take one or another of these vows from a very famous master—a great living bodhisattva. These vows and their ceremonies will be explored in depth in the coming modules and many modules will be devoted to advice about keeping bodhisattva motivation and practice alive and improving them.</paragraph><subsubsection title="The bodhisattva practice" pagetitle="The bodhisattva practice" tocentry="The bodhisattva practice">The bodhisattva practice<paragraph>Although the thirty-seven factors of enlightenment outlined above can all be found in the bodhisattva's practice, they are no longer the main way of cataloguing it or of understanding it. One simple way of approaching the Mahayana path, or bodhisattva path, is through three steps:</paragraph><paragraph>1. Putting the necessary components in place.</paragraph><paragraph>2. Making sure they do not degrade.</paragraph><paragraph>3. Learning to strengthen, deepen and expand them.</paragraph><paragraph>These three topics are the core of a famous prayer that we often use as a dedication. It is, in fact, the summary of Santideva's "Guide to the Bodhisattva Life", perhaps the most famous work on being a bodhisattva:</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Supreme bodhicitta, so precious: may it arise in those in whom it has not yet arisen (1) . Once arisen, may it never deteriorate (2) but become ever more magnificent (3) .</italic> </paragraph><paragraph>The main way in which we will study bodhisattva practice is through the combined cultivation of <italic>aspiration</italic> and <italic>practice</italic> . These two have to be inseparable because the state of mind of a person at any given moment will determine whether the actions they are performing are bodhisattva actions or not. When the aspiration—inspiration, motivation, guiding light—is not present, the action is not bodhisattva action. It may look good and may have all the outer form of generosity, pure conduct, meditation or whatever. But it is no longer <italic>bodhisattva generosity</italic> and <italic>bodhisattva conduct</italic> and therefore the results it generates do not contribute directly to enlightenment.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus, the motivating bodhisattva mind—known as <italic>bodhicitta</italic> —is all-important . It is a huge and vital task to radically change the mind until it reacts to circumstances naturally as a bodhisattva would. However, there is more. If a wonderfully loving mind, dedicated to enlightenment, never concretises into real action and if someone's life does not become devoted in very practical terms to the service of others ... then something is wrong, something is sorely missing.</paragraph><image width="162" src="module4_files.image023.png" align=""/><paragraph>Most of Year Two of this course are dedicated to bodhisattva motivation and practice, in detail, so we will leave the topic here for now, having touched on it briefly in the context of the Fourth Truth, the Truth of the Path.</paragraph><paragraph>There is one vitally important aspect of all Buddhist practice—Hinayana or Mahayana—that we will consider next: mindfulness. It is so important that it could deserve a whole module to itself. On another hand, it is the practice of it, in both meditation and daily life, not talking about it, which is the vital thing.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection></section><section index="3" title="Mindfulness, awareness and care" pagetitle="Mindfulness, awareness and care" tocentry="Mindfulness, awareness and care"><subsection title="Mindfulness, awareness and care" pagetitle="Mindfulness, awareness and care" tocentry="Mindfulness, awareness and care"><image width="306" src="module4_files.image024.png" align=""/><paragraph>Mindfulness belongs to a set of three absolutely crucial points: mindfulness, awareness and care. These days, "mindfulness" courses, based on Buddhist method, are very popular—not just for Buddhists—and they are bringing a benefit to many people all over the world. The value of mindfulness is being clinically proven in many trials. You'll perhaps see from the classical definitions below that they should rather be called "awareness" courses, in Buddhist terms. Also, "be mindful" is such frequent advice in dharma that it is good to have a clear idea of <bold>the Buddhist implication of "mindfulness", which is not simply one of being awake and aware, relaxed and in the present, but one of both remembering and fulfilling sacred purpose</bold> .</paragraph><paragraph>In the Mahayana, these three complementary factors correspond to the Four Foundations of Mindfulness (the first four of the Thirty-Seven Factors of Enlightenment). Here is a simple definition of each of the three, before we consider the details:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item><essential> <bold>Mindfulness</bold> or <italic>recollection</italic> is very much to do with memory. A modern way to put it may be, "Don't lose the plot". In everyday life or in a session of meditation, one should not forget sacred purpose. In all Buddhism, it means remembering impermanence, suffering, no-self and voidness. In Mahayana, it means remembering the bodhisattva teachings and applying them more and more to each situation until they become second nature. It means recalling one's own teacher's personal instructions about how to act or react. It also means recalling the particular objective: for instance, in meditation it means remembering to stay with the particular focus of that practice.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Awareness</bold> is the natural companion of mindfulness. It is the "eye in the sky" that maintains awareness of body, speech and mind. Like a CCTV camera, it observes whether the purpose, the sacred intention, is actually being fulfilled or else being betrayed by what one is doing. This self-awareness needs to be very compassionate and wise. There is no point becoming a bag of nerves, constantly self-critical, riddled with guilt and paranoia. The awareness should have peaceful kindness, as its own part of the mind observes the rest of the mind, with a view to improvement. The development of this peaceful, relaxed kindness to oneself is one of the key benefits emerging from modern "mindfulness" courses.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Care</bold> is a general attitude towards oneself, towards life and the teachings, through which someone does genuinely care about actions (karma) and sincerely wishes to apply the teachings. For care to be cultivated, pride and anger need to be overcome and devotion and respect need to be developed—towards enlightened beings and to all other beings.</essential></item></list><paragraph>The above can also be the more appreciated by thinking of their opposites, being:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item>scatterbrained, with no ethical dynamic, driven by feelings and emotions,</item><item>totally unaware of what actions are doing to oneself or to other people and the world and</item><item>basically someone who couldn't care anyway...</item></list><paragraph>The three skills help and support each other and form a healthy whole. Let us now consider them one by one.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Mindfulness" pagetitle="Mindfulness" tocentry="Mindfulness"><paragraph>Mindfulness is a living thing. Like beautiful music or the feel of a warm, breathing animal in the hands, it cannot be described but needs to be directly experienced. In order to get the feel of mindfulness, we train in it progressively. At first it is artificial but, with time, it becomes natural. It has two aspects—a meditation aspect and a wisdom aspect. The first is the development of an attentive calm; a living "presence" in the moment. This usually starts with physical things: mindful walking, mindful eating, mindfulness of breathing and so forth. When the meditative aspect is familiar, the light of wisdom needs to be brought in to join it.</paragraph><paragraph><essential>There are four main steps in mindfulness training:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1. <bold>Body</bold> - all things physical.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. <bold>Feelings</bold> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3. One's own <bold>mind</bold> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>4. <bold>Phenomena</bold> in general.</essential></paragraph><subsubsection title="1. Mindfulness of Body." pagetitle="1. Mindfulness of Body." tocentry="1. Mindfulness of Body.">1. Mindfulness of Body. <paragraph>Remember: <italic>mindfulness</italic> means <italic>recollection</italic> ! Mindfulness of body is where many people start: often with walking meditation, so let's take that as an example. The object is to keep mind (awareness in a very general sense, not in the specific sense described above) with the body. At first the mind finds it hard to remain with the sensations of the feet: it run away here and there, remembering things of the past, imagining the future or just flitting around like a butterfly from one thought or idea to the next. By repeatedly bring it back to, and anchoring it to, the sensations in the feet, one trains in mindfulness and of developing recollection. Each time there is <italic>distraction</italic> and the mind flies away in its reveries, one has <italic>forgotten</italic> the intention: to keep the mind with the body. Only when one realises that attention has wandered can the <italic>recollection</italic> be re-established. With time, the distractions become fewer and shorter-lasting and the calm joy and actual feel of mindful presence can be experienced. In this process, as a spin-off, one gains more objectivity about the habit-patterns of one's own mind, although that sort of naturally-occurring psycho-analysis is not the main point.</paragraph><paragraph>One then extends this type of training to other physical activities, such as eating. The important thing is to persist assiduously during the practice session until the feel and joy of mindfulness is appreciated. The next step is not to lose the benefit the moment that the meditation session is over. A lot of the day is spent walking, even if it be from one room to another. All walking can become mindful, as can all eating and, with time, most physical activities. Without becoming lost in the sensorial, a whole new physical relationship with material reality emerges: a feeling of being awake, alive and in the present; breathing each breath as a new person and moving through a world of awakened odours, flavours and tactile sensations. More than that, the meaning of "presence of mind" becomes vivid. One gains a new awareness of:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item>One's own body and physical functions.</item><item>Of the body's inter-relation with other people's bodies and</item><item>The "body" of the surrounding world, the environment.</item></list><paragraph>At this stage, meditation needs to be enhanced by the light of wisdom: <underline>then there will be true mindfulness rather than simply peaceful awareness</underline> . This is done by understanding the Buddha's teachings about the body and by testing their veracity—not in one's intellect or through pre-formed opinions but in the actual reality of mindful experience.</paragraph><paragraph>In particular, one considers habitual <bold>illusions of beauty and ugliness, of permanence, of purity and desirability</bold> and so forth, recognising the power of these illusions over ourselves and other people, making things attractive or repulsive and sometimes making those things seem longer-lasting than they naturally are. This could be applied to sexual attraction, which is one of the most powerful factors in many lives. It could also be applied to the time, effort and money spent making the home a "beautiful" place, a pleasant place, or in making the body beautiful.</paragraph><paragraph>In Buddhist India, in order to counteract a romanticising of bodies, monks and nuns would go to meditate in charnel grounds—places where dead bodies were left to be eaten by the birds and jackals. There, they would contemplate the various exposed components of a body, especially the thirty-six <bold>impure</bold> substances (see annexe and mindfulness sutra). Their objective was not to persuade themselves into a different illusion (Buddhist illusion) but to unveil, to witness, the truth: simple, uncom-promising and unassuming vivid knowledge of what physicality really is.</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Comment by several contemporary lamas:</italic> These days, in "highly-developed" countries, there are of course no charnel grounds and it becomes increasingly rare to even see a dead body. In hiding away old age and death, our civilisations plunge themselves deeper into illusion and deprive themselves of a natural understanding of the truth of ageing and mortality. The fact that those who <italic>have</italic> nursed the dying often say, <italic>It was such a privilege</italic> shows us the rarity of the experience. It is so different from former times in Europe and present times in villages in underdeveloped countries, where old age and dying are a natural part of everyday existence and in which everyone participates. <italic>End of comment</italic> </paragraph><paragraph>By understanding bodies for what they are, and material goods for what they are, rather than the illusions which we spin or others spin around them, we understand better our own processes of clinging and involvement with them and the karma that these pull us into. This leads us into the next step.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="2. Mindfulness of Feelings" pagetitle="2. Mindfulness of Feelings" tocentry="2. Mindfulness of Feelings">2. Mindfulness of Feelings<paragraph>"Feelings" is a very loose term in English, covering physical sensations, emotions and even opinions: <italic>What do you feel about proportional ballots? I feel lonely..</italic> . It has been used universally to translate the Sanskrit dharma term <italic>vedan</italic>  <italic>ā</italic> , which is, on the contrary, something very limited and precisely-defined. There are only three vedana: <italic>feels good, feels bad</italic> and <italic>neutral (no feeling)</italic> . These can be stretched to five: physically pleasant, mentally pleasant, physically unpleasant, mentally unpleasant and neutral.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus the new skill of mindfulness, developed with physical things, now becomes awareness of mind's instant reaction to sense experiences. In the very instant following seeing something, or smelling it, hearing it etc., there will be this immediate, reactive "feeling" of pleasantness or unpleasantness or else there will be no feeling at all. In the instant following the feeling, the feeling is given voice in the mind's inner chatter: <italic>This colour is ugly!, Oh, gosh that's soft! What delicious plums! Horrible noise!</italic> etc. Although the latter are primarily thoughts, they reveal the feelings that preceded them and they testify to the power and nature of those feelings.</paragraph><paragraph>The quest for the pleasant and the fleeing of the unpleasant dominates life and is the motor force behind actions.</paragraph><paragraph>Humans find excrement repulsive: dogs are quite attracted to it. "One man's meat is another man's poison." Some people like hot climates. Others prefer the cold. Some people become excited by certain, natural body odours, others find them repulsive.</paragraph><paragraph>It is very useful to become mindful of one's own habitual feelings, as described above. Just as, in the early training, one maintained awareness with the sensations in the feet, here one maintains awareness with the ever-changing feelings provoked by sights and sounds. Once there is mindfulness of feelings provoked by data coming in through the five senses, one turns to feelings provoked by thoughts—by being mindful of how one's own mind reacts so differently to the thoughts that are none other than itself, its own creation. Some thoughts engender sheer delight, others trigger unbearable pain. As one becomes aware of what one's own mind does to itself, in this respect, the process is seen as quite amazing (and often out of control).</paragraph><paragraph>All the above is the meditative aspect of mindfulness of feelings. Once mindfulness becomes a familiar companion to feelings, it is important to develop the wisdom aspect, by understanding the Buddha's teachings on feelings. In particular, at this point, it is important to come to an intimate <bold>understanding of suffering</bold> , as the three types of suffering described in Module Two. These leads one to appreciate that often, what <italic>feels</italic> good is not necessarily good for us! And what is good for us can feel difficult or uncomfortable! Mindfulness of feelings is to be aware of their role in one's own life and of their role in the processes of interdependence in general. <italic>Feelings</italic> are important because they trigger <italic>craving</italic> . Craving gives rise to all the other mind poisons and it is craving which causes one to become involved with situations and <italic>create karma</italic> , through actions. Being mindful of this, a factor of <italic>choice</italic> develops, supplanting habit. The feelings can be either followed or re-channelled wisely, according to the teachings on karma.</paragraph><paragraph>The texts describe feelings as being 'like a water-tree'. This is often translated as a plantain or banana tree, which has no heartwood and is hollow. Some Tibetan lamas take the meaning as 'driftwood', in the sense of something useless while others keep the plantain meaning but translate the description as meaning 'useless', inasmuch as one cannot make furniture or build houses with plantain wood. Whichever the case, feelings are a very vivid example of how the mind makes solid something which has no existence of its own and which comes and goes and changes in seconds. These chimeras of feelings dominate life and lead humans into all sorts of actions.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="3. Mindfulness of Mind" pagetitle="3. Mindfulness of Mind" tocentry="3. Mindfulness of Mind">3. Mindfulness of Mind<paragraph><essential>Mindfulness of feelings starts to make us more aware of our mind's constructs around those feelings and in particular the thoughts of "I". First, the meditative aspect of <italic>mindfulness of mind</italic> is cultivated, by placing quiet awareness with one's thoughts and mental activity, just as one did with the soles of the feet in walking meditation. Here, one is being mindful of mind, mind the observer; mind, the experiencer; mind, the subject as opposed to other people and things; mind that usually feels like "me".</essential></paragraph><paragraph>When there is meditative familiarity with the subjective mind, one needs then to cultivate the wisdom aspect of <italic>mindfulness of mind.</italic> We will use parts of a traditional teaching from the great Jamgon Kongtrul Rinpoche as a basis for explaining this.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus far, mindfulness has been focussed on body and feelings. These correspond to the first two of the five aggregates.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>The Five Aggregates</bold> ( <italic>skandha</italic> )</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>1. Form</bold> </td><td>specifically: what one sees, i.e. shape and colour more generally: the human form and all physical or mental forms</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>2. Feelings</bold> </td><td>pleasant, unpleasant, neutral</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>3. Cognition</bold> </td><td>recognition of things, with or without thought</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>4. Mental creations</bold> </td><td>51 main mental activities</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>5. Consciousness</bold> </td><td>the 5 senses and their objects + (6) mind and its 'objects' + (7) defiling consciousness + (8) universal basis consciousness</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph><essential>The notion of self—the way one thinks of oneself or of another person—is based upon the person's mind. What it is commonly considered to continue from one life to the next is mind, since the five senses depend upon the body and cease at death. Mind itself is primarily consciousness, an ability to know, a clarity or spaciousness that allows experiences to happen within it. <bold>Therefore mindfulness of <underline>mind</underline> is focussed on <italic>consciousness</italic> , the fifth aggregate.</bold> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>Some Buddhist traditions only talk about the six consciousnesses. In that case, mind is the sixth of the consciousnesses. In the traditions that discuss consciousness as eightfold, 'mind' ( <italic>citta</italic> ) means the eighth consciousness, the 'universal basis consciousness'.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Whichever system one uses, mind is observed meticulously. It is discovered to be <bold>impermanent</bold> . Mind is different from one life to the next, from one decade to the next, from one year to the next and so on. Even the mind of one shortest instant of awareness is different from the next one. No lasting thing can be found that we could call "mind". But still we entertain the idea of a lasting mind, a lasting self, even though it is never found. We entertain a total illusion. That illusion dominates life. Thus we need to examine it again and again to reverse our mistaken habits.</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Looking again and again at the mind, which cannot be looked at,</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>there is deep insight into the true point, of not seeing anything.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>May there be self-recognition of what one really is,</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>by the very act of cutting through doubts about mind existing or not</italic> </paragraph><paragraph>HH the IIIrd Gyalwang Karmapa</paragraph><paragraph>Why do we bother to meditate like this? Belief in a personality, a self, lies at the root of our actions which cause the suffering of this and future lives. Most Buddhists—who technically do not hold the view of a personal self as truly existing—mostly act, in their daily lives, as though they did believe in a self. It is very helpful to reflect upon such glaring contradictions between our beliefs and our actions.</paragraph><paragraph>Aryadeva says</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Believing in a stream, one believes in a lasting self</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Believing in skandhas (as one), one believes things to truly exist.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph>Thus people believe the skandhas to be lasting and take one or more of them for a "self". By mindfulness of mind, one witnesses the truth of what the skandhas really are, and discovers them to be non-lasting and not to have a single entity.</paragraph><paragraph>The above is an investigation of the ultimate nature of mind. The most refined form of such investigation is found in the traditions based on the teachings of <italic>prajnaparamita</italic> , the perfection of wisdom teachings from Nagarjuna.</paragraph><paragraph>On a relative level, it is by long-term, observation of mind that we come to understand directly and intuitively how the successive instants of consciousness relate to and trigger each other. It becomes clear how habits are formed and how they repeat themselves, from year to year, from life to life; how they can be weakened and how they can be strengthened.</paragraph><paragraph>The best outcome of developing mindfulness of mind is to understand the continuity of the stream of consciousness from life to life, without falling into the 'extremes' of permanence (believing in a lasting self that is reborn) or nihilism (dismissing relative reality, cause and effect, reincarnation etc. through a misunderstanding of voidness). The IIIrd Gyalwang Karmapa says:</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>It is not something which exists: even the Enlightened Ones have not seen it.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>It is not something which does not exist; it's the basis for all of samsara and nirvana.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>There is no contradiction in this but the two-in-union Middle Way.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph> <italic>May the very nature of mind, free of these extremes, be realised.</italic> </paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="4. Mindfulness of Phenomena (dharma)" pagetitle="4. Mindfulness of Phenomena (dharma)" tocentry="4. Mindfulness of Phenomena (dharma)">4. Mindfulness of Phenomena (dharma)<paragraph>This is the most subtle step of mindfulness, as it is to remain mindful of the very nature of things. One way of expressing this would be <italic>the unity of interdependence and voidness</italic> . In a limited interpretation of this point, the objects of mindfulness are <italic>dharmas</italic> . Just as shapes and colours are the objects of visual consciousness, <italic>dharmas</italic> are whatever the subjective mind can be conscious of. These can be ideas, memories, imaginary situations, a mathematical puzzle etc. etc. The wider understanding of the term <italic>dharmas</italic> is of the vary nature of all things—the whole of the Buddha's teachings being precisely about that. Let us consider some points emerging from Kongtrul's teachings on this. Concerning the meditative aspect:</paragraph><paragraph><essential>"Here we turn our attention to the third and fourth aggregates.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>The third aggregate is <bold>cognition</bold> , the way in which the mind recognises and labels things. Based on all the references we carry in our minds, complex notions of reality develop and these colour the whole tonality of our life experience.</paragraph><paragraph>The fourth aggregate is very global. In fact, in one way, it contains all the others. It is called <bold>mental events</bold> or <bold>karmic formations</bold> (Skt: samskara) Fifty-one important ones are given. They become fifty-six when erroneous views (no. 26) is expanded into the five misconceptions.</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, this fourth skandha also includes various lists (often twenty-four are mentioned) of abstract concepts which also play an important part in our lives. Examples of those would be notions like <italic>loss</italic> or <italic>gain</italic> , or of things being <italic>similar</italic> to each other.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>The 56 samskaras</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>5 Universals</bold> </td><td>Focussing the mind (1) , feeling (2), cognition (3), holding the mind on its object (4) and sense contact (5)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>5 things which determine the object</bold> </td><td>aspiration (6), certainty (7), recall (8), concentration (9) and understanding (10)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>11 virtues</bold> </td><td>trust (11), care (12), proficiency (13), equanimity (14), self-respect (15), sense of shame (16), non-attachment (17), non-aggression (18), absence of confusion (19), non-violence (20) and diligence (21)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>6 basic non-virtues</bold> </td><td>ignorance (22), desire and attachment (23), aggression and rejection (24), pride (25) and erroneous views (26)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>5 misconceptons</bold> </td><td>attitudes related to skandhas ("destructible complex") (27), extremists' attitude (28), perverse attitudes (29), rigid convictions (30) and rigid convictions about morality and conduct (31)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>21 subsidiary non-virtues</bold> </td><td>wrath (32), resent (33), rage (34), irritation (35), jealousy (36), discontent (37), deceit (38), pretence/hypocrisy (39), absence of self-respect (40), absence of a sense of shame (41), dissimulation (42), avarice (43), narcissism (44), absence of trust (45), time-wasting (46), negligence (47), no mindfulness (48), no awareness (49), torpor (50), agitation (51) and total distraction (52)</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>4 variables</bold> </td><td>sleep (53), regret (54), thinking (55) and examination (56)</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>The wisdom aspect and the reason why we turn our mindfulness to cognition and the samskaras is in order <bold>to understand quite what is happening with rebirth</bold> . There are many aspects to this, summed up in these bullet-points but not developed here in detail:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item>Each notion and each mental event has its own nature. The 'mind' is not one thing , like an actor wearing many masks, but an endless series of different flashes of experience, the previous one triggering the next . We call this the 'mind stream'. The stream is not a thing in itself, just as a mountain stream is no more than the drops of water of which it is composed.</item><item>Just as one moment of mind triggers, and leads to, another moment of mind in this life, so also does that stream of consciousness continue after death, carrying its imprints (programming) into the next life.</item><item>The mind of the past shapes the mind of the future and there is an infallible rule that virtue always leads to happiness and non-virtue always leads to suffering. One could say this good karma-bad karma conditioning in consciousness is like either gold dust or pollution being carried with the stream.</item><item>"Cause and effect" is more subtle than it first appears. On needs to contemplate deeply what the Buddha intended, in the Rice Shoot Sutra, when he said that, "Because there is this, that arises". He did not say, "This creates that". We do this through exploring the twelve links of interdependence through three aspects: invariability, impermanence and karmic programming. In the process, we apply the voidness teachings of the perfection of wisdom.</item><item>Sentient beings are highly complex, changing streams of results created by actions in the past. What they are doing now, through each of their complex personalities, is shaping the future.</item></list><paragraph>By becoming mindful of the reality of the above points—as moment after moment this or that skandha manifests and disappears—a heightened sensitivity develops to the actual nature and power of actions, and to the motivation which underpins action. Life processes become illuminated by wisdom. Long-held illusions—the myths of reality, of future possibilities, of luck, of God and so forth—evaporate in the morning sunlight of truth. Great compassion arises for our fellow sentient beings lost in confusion.</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Summary of above</italic> </paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td>Minfulness of:</td><td>Meditative aspect focuses on:</td><td>Wisdom aspect recollects Buddha's teachings on:</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>BODY</bold> </td><td>walking, eating, speaking, physical contact with people, material objects - all these make the <bold>form aggregate</bold> </td><td> <bold>impurity</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>FEELINGS</bold> </td><td> <bold>feelings</bold> </td><td> <bold>suffering</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>MIND</bold> </td><td> <bold>consciousness</bold> </td><td> <bold>impermanence</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>DHARMA</bold> </td><td> <bold>cognition and mental events</bold> </td><td> <bold>voidness</bold> </td></tr></tbody></table></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="Awareness" pagetitle="Awareness" tocentry="Awareness"><paragraph>The development of mindfulness, described above, relies on being aware, from a beginner's general awareness of physical sensations through to an experienced Buddhist's subtle awareness of interdependence at play. The awareness we will explore in this section is called <italic>samprajanyam</italic> in Sanskrit. In this context, it means <italic>cultivating vigilance</italic> . It is a process of self-awareness that checks that all is going as it should. Although far from perfect as an example, a good modern metaphor for this would be the security camera, constantly watching to make sure there is no danger, or signalling the danger when it happens so that something can be done. A good point about this example is that a camera is unemotional, non-judgemental. It just gives an image of what is happening. <italic>Samprajanyam</italic> is a high-quality mind camera that gives an excellent view of what is happening each second. What is then done about it is very much the next topic, <italic>care</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>In vajrayana Buddhism, we have a special way of getting the right feel of such awareness, in practices where, one way or another, the Buddha or guru is constantly present. The "feel" of this checking awareness should be that of the peaceful, benevolent wisdom of the Buddha. As we know that the Buddha is the true essence of our being, there is no internal conflict, no splitting oneself into two. It is simply the wiser part of the mind observing the old habits of the less-wise part. In applying this, we discover the meaning of <italic>compassion for oneself</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>The <italic>mahamudra</italic> system of meditation has many skilful and subtle techniques for helping to deepen and stabilise <italic>awareness,</italic> this insightful part of one's mind. First, there needs to be a healthy basis of peaceful stability ( <italic>samatta</italic> ). Then the peaceful mind can be used to know itself more profoundly. This opens up many unexpected doors of insight and a quality of awareness never before experienced.</paragraph><paragraph>Simply being very aware is not necessarily in itself virtuous. One could be vividly aware yet doing horrible things and enjoying them. Therefore, the essential characteristic of this Buddhist awareness is to be aware of whether or not one is being mindful of sacred purpose . Put another way, it is helping us to live to our highest ethical standards and not "turn a blind eye" to the more negative habits.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Care" pagetitle="Care" tocentry="Care"><paragraph>Whereas mindfulness and awareness are very much things which take place "in the moment", <italic>care</italic> is something developed generally, over time. It grows or weakens from year to year, according to enthusiasm and many other factors. There is a very famous quotation from Guru Rinpoche <a href="#_ftn10">[10]</a>:</paragraph><paragraph>Keep your view as broad as space</paragraph><paragraph>And your action as fine as flour.</paragraph><paragraph>This is a healthy reminder not to let slip everyday values of human goodness as the view of voidness and understanding of illusion deepen. The greatest masters—those who had a "view" as broad as space itself—are famous for never considering any good thing too trivial to bother doing and never considering any harmful thing so small it could be ignored: action as fine as flour.</paragraph><paragraph>Care is usually increased by awareness of how fleeting and precious this human life is and, by consequence, awareness of death and impermanence.</paragraph></subsection></section><footnotes><footnote id="1">Rose Apple Land ( 'dzam bu gling, jambudvīpa ) was an epithet for our world, at the time referring principally to India.</footnote><footnote id="2">The four results are, in Pali, respectively: sotapanna, sakadagami, anagami and arhat .</footnote><footnote id="3">500 was the ancient Indian way of saying "hundreds and hundreds" and is not to be taken as meaning exactly that number.</footnote><footnote id="4">It is expressed like this in Tibetan too. There is no one who acquires, there is no thing to acquire yet, nevertheless, somehow it makes some sense to describe it like that.</footnote><footnote id="5">Tib: 'od gsal , often translated literally as «clear light».</footnote><footnote id="6">The word is used in spoken Tibetan to mean intelligence and clarity of mind in genera.</footnote><footnote id="7">so-called because the prowess in meditation which is developed at this stage gives rise to the six clear cognitions and many other extraordinary abilities.</footnote><footnote id="8">Gross gross, middling gross, subtle gross, gross middling, middling middling, subtle middle, gross subtle, middling subtle and subtle subtle. As one progresses through these, working with them becomes a finer and longer-lasting process.</footnote><footnote id="9">The four are: forbearance, awareness, subsequent forbearance and subsequent awareness.</footnote><footnote id="10"> Guru Rinpoche was the person who established dharma in Tibet in the 8th century.</footnote></footnotes></chapter></book>