<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book"><chapter index="3" title="The Second Truth: the Causes of Suffering" pagetitle="Module 3" tocentry="The Second Truth: the Causes of Suffering"><section index="1" title="" pagetitle="" tocentry=""/><section index="2" title="Reflections on Causality in General" pagetitle="Reflections on Causality in General" tocentry="Reflections on Causality in General"><subsection title="Reflections on Causality in General" pagetitle="Reflections on Causality in General" tocentry="Reflections on Causality in General"><image width="470" src="module3_files.image001.png" align=""/><paragraph>We shall explore this in the following seven ways:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>By considering causality in general.</item><item>By working backwards, from effects to causes, to establish an overview.</item><item>By examining karma, and in particular non-virtuous karma, the immediate cause of suffering.</item><item>By examining the cause of karma: the afflictions.</item><item>By examining the cause of the afflictions: primarily notions of ego but also dualistic delusions of self and other.</item><item>By examining the cause of dualistic delusions: ignorance of the true nature.</item><item>By investigating interdependence and in particular outer interdependent origination in its twelve classical links and inner interdependence through the six elements.</item></list><image width="452" src="module3_files.image002.png" align=""/></subsection><subsection title="Causality" pagetitle="Causality" tocentry="Causality"><paragraph>Why do things happen? Is there some hidden programming, some master-plan, behind life? Is there some point to it all? In particular, why do we suffer? These questions have intrigued both everyday humans and philosophers of East and West for thousands of years. We can witness short-term cause-and-effect on a material level, such as observing a seedling growing into a flower or CO <subscript>2</subscript> emissions changing the Earth's climate. We see them on a psychological level when a person's behaviour is affected by life experience. Other than obvious cause-and-effect, is there some even greater logic behind everything: a longer-term causality? Some common ways of answering have been:</paragraph><paragraph>· No, things just happen, biologically and otherwise, with no particular "greater" cause, such as God or karma. A thorn is sharp, water is wet. The kidneys produce urine and a brain produces thoughts and emotions. It's simply like that and any attempt to attribute meaning to a meaningless universe is merely human vanity and an attempt to deny mortality and our relative insignificance. Suffering simply happens.</paragraph><paragraph>· Or, some say it is, as above, inherently accidental, with no deep meaning or purpose, but that as intelligent humans we can give it meaning. Suffering happens and this gives the opportunity for us to form a noble and useful relationship to it, in ourselves and in others <a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>.</paragraph><paragraph>· Or, some consider the whole universe, including its sentient beings, is the creation of, and the play of, immortal beings: gods. The gods have their purpose, beyond our grasp; a mystery. Their will and power is all-determining. If we suffer, it is their will and perhaps their displeasure with us. Or their way of testing us.</paragraph><paragraph>· Or, some see it as above but with just a single creator god.</paragraph><paragraph>· Or, without god or gods, some see "life" as a sort of cosmic 'test'. We will be reborn again and again into similar situations until we find the correct response.</paragraph><paragraph>· And so on...</paragraph><paragraph>The list could become endless and would lead us into all the details of the great faiths and philosophies with their fine differences of opinion. Intellectualism aside, pinpointing the cause of things—and especially of suffering—is a major issue in all human life. To put it simply, when things get tough, who or what do we blame? Into what framework falls our reaction?</paragraph><paragraph>The Buddha denied any divine and purposeful creation of the universe and taught extensively that things happen because of other things, in a continuously changing process of interdependence. Part of that overall process is for one conscious existence to give rise to another one, and another, in a series of reincarnations where what occurs in one life is the result of what happened in the previous. And what someone does in the present life is determining how the future one will be. However, the Buddha's teaching—dharma—is not a simple determinism, even though some people describe it as such <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>. This is because any idea of a material universe in Buddhism is not purely a mechanistic one but one tempered by the all-important description of that universe as being <italic>like a dream or a conjuration</italic> . In other words, " <underline>the</underline> universe" is a word a human gives to "my universe"—the narrow slice of everything that his or her human senses and intelligence enable that person to perceive. Actual reality is something far more.</paragraph><paragraph>The Buddha's teachings on cause-and-effect provide us with a good explanation for the way things seem to be happening in this relative and highly-subjective dream of life. They deal with the happenings in the material world around us and in the mind, following their evolution from day to day and from life to life. At the same time, the Buddha's other teachings, on absolute truth, show clearly that nothing ever produced anything. Just as a horse in a dream never needed to have been sired by a father stallion and borne by a mother mare, so things in the apparent universe are not all they seem to be!</paragraph><paragraph>We find a parallel to this in modern physics, where causality is still a practical and common-sense way of understand the mechanisms of the world in which we live.</paragraph><paragraph>Acid + alkali gives salt + water.</paragraph><paragraph>What goes up must fall down, in a gravity field.</paragraph><paragraph>A poppy seed gives rise to a poppy flower.</paragraph><paragraph>Yet, causality theory disappears totally on a level of the chaotic behaviour of the tiniest sub-atomic particles. Nevertheless, the new understanding of quantum physics doesn't stop the seeds we plant in the garden from growing into vegetables nor does it stop the kettle from boiling when we plug it in. Likewise, the semblance of order on our level of perception (gardens, kettles) does not prevent us from believing in utter chaos on a finer level.</paragraph><paragraph>As Buddhists, we have the very practical application of dharma, helping us to sort out our daily lives and our karma, in terms of predictable cause and effect. We also have the luxury of a fine philosophical analysis to help us penetrate the absolute truth of things. This is an extraordinarily helpful blend!</paragraph><paragraph>Before we do enter into the details of the causes of suffering, here are a few useful points which often come up, explained by Khenchen Thrangu Rinpoche and the Goshir Gyaltsabpa:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item> Not everything that happens is a result of past karma . If someone catches a cold, or meets an unknown person today, is does not necessarily mean that there is a specific cause for that somewhere in a past life. It is not always "my karma for this to happen".</item><item> There is no "learning purpose" conspiracy behind everything . Although almost anything can give us the opportunity to learn something or other—and it can become our teacher, our guru—there is not some divine plot where the guru or the Buddha is constantly and intentionally putting each and every thing in our path as a specific test with a specific significance at that time.</item><item> Not everything we do creates karma . Six factors need to be reunited for karma to be established.</item><item> On a relative level, we definitely have choice , and making the right choices is an important point of Buddhist ethics and practice. Thus, we are not fatalists.</item><item>At a certain—and wonderful—point in the practice, there may come a time when there will be no choice . This is not fatalism either, as the lack of choice results from previous choices: for instance, an astronaut may have made hundreds of choices which ended up in him or her being launched in the space capsule. Once it is up in orbit: no choice, no turning back!</item><item> Karma actually creates the circumstances we generally call suffering but not suffering itself . Whether one actually suffers or not depends upon the way the person relates to those circumstances. Wealth can be a torture for some and sickness can be deeply liberating.</item></list><paragraph>These and other points will be explained in this module.</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="3" title="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering" pagetitle="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering" tocentry="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering"><subsection title="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering" pagetitle="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering" tocentry="The Overview of the Causes of Suffering"><paragraph>The following is the master template for this module. Please learn it by heart.</paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Ignorance</bold> of the true nature of things <italic>causes</italic> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Dualistic thought</bold> projecting an experiencer—"I"—and something experienced—"other", <italic>causing</italic> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Afflictions</bold> of "I"-centred passion, anger, pride etc. <italic>causing</italic> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Action</bold> (karma) to get what is desired or avoid what is disliked etc. <italic>causing</italic> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Rebirth</bold> in "samsara" with its inevitable suffering.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>This process will be studied in more detail and sophistication through the <italic>twelve links of interdependence</italic> , which can be applied over a series of lives, over two lives, within one life or in the very moment.</paragraph><paragraph>At this point, it is probably helpful to clarify the terms <italic>tainted</italic> and <italic>untainted</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Tainted action</bold> can be positive or negative, good or bad, virtuous or non-virtuous, helpful or harmful (whichever terms you prefer). It is <italic>tainted</italic> because it results in samsara. The virtuous actions create the pleasant things of samsara—health, wealth, friendship, harmony—and the non-virtuous ones create the unpleasant things—illness, poverty, enmity, disharmony etc. The "taint" is the presence of the illusion of self when the action is performed. It has already sown the seed of the "someone", in the future, who will experience the consequence.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>Untainted action</bold> is performed without the driving thought of "I". It happens in a state known as "beyond triplicity", where three things—the notion of subject, object and interaction—are transcended or absent. Untainted action is the way out of samsara, to nirvana.</paragraph><paragraph>To describe the above master template in a few more words, before we enter into the details:</paragraph><paragraph>The mahayana view of the real truth, of everything, of our own being, of mind, is the <italic>awakened mind</italic> or <italic>buddha mind</italic> . It is pure, eternal, perfect, unchanging and filled with wisdom, loving kindness and power to help beings. This can be interpreted in many ways, but let's leave it like that for now. The Hinayana view is that it is total peace and purity. Buddha mind or simply peace: that is the true <italic>identity</italic> . Not to <italic>be</italic> that, and hence not to know that, is what is meant by <italic>ignorance</italic> . This ignorance is the heart of the problem. Due to it, the natural feeling of inner identity becomes mistaken for a personal self and once there is that feeling of a self—a perceiver, a subject—there will instantaneously be a perception of "other"—something or someone perceived, an object. For most people, this happens moment after moment, every moment, before even thoughts can put it into words. This instant-by-instant fractioning of awareness into two halves is called <italic>duality</italic> or <italic>dualistic perception</italic> and the way our thoughts rationalise it is called <italic>dualistic thinking</italic> . The latter is the constantly-updated story that the chatter of the mind is recounting: a tale of oneself and other people and the world. This has been going on since time immemorial.</paragraph><paragraph>Once the stories about oneself, the people in one's life and the world around one have become solid realities in the mind, through being rehearsed and repeated over and over again, all sorts of interactions naturally follow. If the inner story says <italic>I love Tibetans</italic> then when one meets Tibetans one feels good and wants more, planning trips East and so on. When the inner story says <italic>wasps are horrible and dangerous</italic> , someone will not think twice about destroying them, even if they have caused no personal harm. The two main polarities of this stage of the story are attraction and rejection. The attractive and repulsive forces motivate our lives, since much of our time and effort goes into trying to get what we want and to avoid what we don't like. When these motive-forces have the ego-delusion at their heart, they are called <italic>klesha</italic> , in Sanskrit, meaning <italic>affliction, defilement, canker, poisons</italic> etc.</paragraph><paragraph>Because of the klesha, one will act. Some actions bring happiness to their doer, in the long term (usually next life) while others bring suffering. The Sanskrit for <italic>action</italic> is <italic>karma</italic> . Unlike the English understanding of the word <italic>action</italic> , which finishes once the initial or immediate action has terminated, the word <italic>karma</italic> includes both immediate and long-term consequences. This is a very interesting way of looking at actions: it is like a gardener who plants a seedling but who can already see the future mighty tree in his mind. "Planting a poppy seed", for Westerners, is an action which finishes once the earth has been tamped around the seed and it has been watered. In Buddhist thought "planting a poppy seed" includes everything up to and including the red flower that appears months later. It is for this reason that the texts speak of <italic>karma, cause <underline>and</underline> effect</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>Be it virtuous or non-virtuous, tainted karma generates samsara. With samsara comes suffering, as we saw in the previous module.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering" pagetitle="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering" tocentry="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering"><paragraph>In more technical presentations of the Four Truths, four main aspects are underlined for each truth <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>. For this Second Truth, the four are:</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>1. Cause 2. Universal origination 3. Total production 4. Condition</bold> </paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Cause</italic> </bold> is a key term signifying that suffering does not just happen but that it is caused, by actions ( <italic>karma</italic> ), afflictions ( <italic>klesha</italic> ) and ignorance. The term cause—as opposed to the term <italic>condition(s)</italic> , which occurs later, refers to a prime cause. This means something that has the ability to give rise to a certain result. For instance, a poppy seed has the genetic coding which produces a poppy flower. Nothing else in the universe possesses that same coding and potential. A human being's eye colour, blood type etc. are already pre-coded, uniquely, in the genes of the embryo. With <italic>prime causes</italic> , we are considering the power of each action to imprint the mind and thereby later cause a certain type of experience to manifest.</paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Universal origination</italic> </bold> signifies the power to give rise to an entire reality, including the person and world that the person experiences. Thus we humans are born with a similar lot, experiencing other humans and a typically-human world. This world is the production of our group karma: group in the sense of family, society, nation etc.</paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Total production</italic> </bold> refers to a more personal aspect within this generality of being humans. Although we are all humans, no two people are the same. The total production of one human being occurs through that person's actions and mind habits generated by the past. While we are somehow connected and trigger each other's personal karma in our shared realities, we are totally unconnected with other realities.</paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph> <bold> <italic>Condition,</italic> </bold> as opposed to <italic>cause</italic> (above) refers to general conditions which are necessary for something to happen. The poppy seed needs light, heat and moisture for its genetic coding to make a flower. The embryo needs nourishment to grow. This fourth point highlights the fact that once humans (or other beings) exist in their particular realities, with their individual karma and habits, there is already the condition for more karma to be generated, thereby perpetuating the cycle of suffering.</paragraph><paragraph>These four names came about because the Buddha, when explaining the source of samsara's painful shortcomings, explained,</paragraph><paragraph>"It has four hallmarks:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>Karma and affliction create the painful shortcomings of samsara. Therefore, in the manner of a seed, it is the cause.</item><item>The three realms and the continua of the five realms [4]arise in full from it so, in the manner of a harvest arising, it is origination.</item><item>Strong karma and affliction produce immediate retribution. Therefore, through inter-relationship, it is highest production.</item><item>Because the unsatisfactory skandhas in the places of the three realms are actually produced from karma and affliction, it assists the production of the outcome like water and fertilizer, so it is the condition." [5]</item></list><paragraph>We will not use this classical and rather technical exposition as the basis for this module but rather concentrate on the way samsara's causes have been explained many times over the years by our lineage masters at Samye Ling.</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="4" title="Karma: The Cause of Samsara" pagetitle="Karma: The Cause of Samsara" tocentry="Karma: The Cause of Samsara"><subsection title="Karma: The Cause of Samsara" pagetitle="Karma: The Cause of Samsara" tocentry="Karma: The Cause of Samsara"><paragraph>We will now start working back from the Six Realms of suffering, studied last month, to the immediate causes of those sufferings; previous karma, meaning previous actions. Although the variety of actions a being can perform is infinite, they are categorised into three areas—physical, verbal and mental—and these in turn have their sub-categories, giving us a tenfold guide to non-virtuous and virtuous action that is very famous in Buddhism.</paragraph><paragraph>The order in which we consider these is important. First things first: the priority for the Buddha was always to help us to stop harming others (and ourselves in the process, through the long-term play of karma). Although doing positive, wholesome things is important, our priority too should be to reduce as much and as urgently as is possible actions that cause harm. In order to do that, we first need to understand what "harm" means. Thus, our study of action starts by considering the famous Ten Non-Virtuous Actions. Then we will consider virtuous karma and thirdly the special karma of meditation, known as Immobility Karma.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Ten Non-Virtuous Actions" pagetitle="The Ten Non-Virtuous Actions" tocentry="The Ten Non-Virtuous Actions"><table style="background:#CCFFFF;border-collapse:collapse" class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td>Physical Verbal Mental</td><td>To kill To steal To commit sexual misconduct To lie To create division and enmity To speak woundingly To speak uselessly Malevolence Avarice Aberrant belief</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>Although each of the above actions will have immediate consequences, on the doer and on the done-to, here we are considering primarily the aspect that most people ignore: the long-term effect on the doer. The following is a tremendously important point, highlighted again and again by our teachers:</paragraph><paragraph><essential>Nobody wants to suffer, everyone wants happiness. The world is striving vigorously for happiness yet happiness is rare and suffering is widespread. Something is very wrong! Something is really not working. What is wrong is that we do not understand the long-term causes of happiness and of suffering and, in such ignorance, efforts for short-term happiness often become the very causes that trigger needless suffering in the long-term future.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>An example to illustrate the above would be that of someone who kills animals for sport. The thrill of hitting the target and taking a pheasant home to put in the freezer is an immediate pleasure but could the killer only but perceive the physical sickness, pain, short life etc. that will result from that action in the next life, s/he would probably never fire the shot in the first place. Even then, human nature can be perversely unintelligent and sometimes even opts for the short-term pleasure despite clear knowledge of the long-term drawbacks. Smoking is one example. Elected politicians' reluctance to implement obvious long-term solutions is perhaps another. Dharma is long-term work and part of the training is a new learning, finding joy in letting go of instant pleasure, sometimes accepting hardship, in the knowledge that one is working for long-term sanity <a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a>.</paragraph><paragraph>We will consider the long-term consequences of actions in three areas:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item> Full maturation , meaning a type of rebirth in the six realms. Whether the worst-case-scenario happens or not, or how many times it happens, depends upon the frequency and the power of the action (see below).</item><item> Results resembling their causes , relating to the quality of life within that rebirth.</item><item> Environmental effects experienced during the future birth.</item></list><subsubsection title="1. Killing" pagetitle="1. Killing" tocentry="1. Killing">1. Killing<paragraph><essential>This means intentionally bringing the life of another sentient being to an end. Harming life, without necessarily killing a being, is a sub-category of this non-virtue. The motive force behind killing can be <italic>desire</italic> —for meat or animal products, for the thrill of hunting, for financial gain or to protect one's goods and loved ones. It could be through <italic>anger and aversion</italic> —fighting enemies, eliminating competitors, vengeance and the like. It could be through <italic>ignorance</italic> , such as killing animals to make sacrificial offerings.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation of killing could be rebirth as a hell-being. The result corresponding to the cause is that even if one is reborn human, one will have a short life and many sicknesses. The environmental influence is to be reborn in an ill-fated and unattractive land .</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="2. Stealing" pagetitle="2. Stealing" tocentry="2. Stealing">2. Stealing<paragraph><essential>The actual wording of this is <italic>taking what is not given</italic> . The motive force behind stealing is usually desire, although it could be through malevolence or confusion. There are three main types of stealing: robbery with violence, burglary and other "stealth" thefts and, thirdly, fraudulence.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth as a deprived spirit. The result resembling the cause is that even if one is reborn human, one will live in poverty or in dissatisfaction. The environmental consequence is to be reborn in a place of much frost and hail.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="3. Sexual Misconduct" pagetitle="3. Sexual Misconduct" tocentry="3. Sexual Misconduct">3. Sexual Misconduct<paragraph><essential> <bold>Comment:</bold> Some people question vigorously some aspects of what follows, especially traditional teaching concerning oral or anal sex. Our lamas are often at a loss to answer and would be only too happy if the Buddha would come back to guide us in these modern times. One must remember also that most lamas are monastics, coming from a reserved culture. Many are uncomfortable speaking publicly about these things and often lack personal or cultural experience of the questions asked.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>Were these karma teachings old social conventions, from India and Tibet, irrelevant today? Were they, on the contrary, in whole or in part, based on an understanding of natural energies and the karma that certain sexual activities generate and, if so, have our societies something to learn, even if it challenges modern assumptions?</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The very fact of the strength of people's reaction to this topic is proof in itself of the powerful emotions and karma at play with sexuality and hence of the importance of getting it right. All we can do here is to present the traditional advice and leave each person to draw his or her own conclusions.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>"Misconduct" here is defined by two sorts of factor: natural ones (that apply universally) and ones related to social convention (and hence varying from culture to culture). The <italic>natural ones</italic> arise because of the way the human mind-body mechanisms function, because of the energies around certain places and holy people, through the power of certain times in the calendar and so forth. As always, with teachings on karma, the Buddha is not setting down an arbitrary ethic but simply pointing out what happens, "If one does this now, later this will occur..." (regardless of whether one would wish it to be that way or not).</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The <italic>social conventions</italic> are concerned with mental suffering created by personal conditioning or social stigma. The impact of having sex with someone who already has a partner will be very different in a totally-promiscuous society from in a one-partner-for-life society. The underlying Buddhist guideline, even in our complex modern world of overlapping values, is not to cause suffering on account of selfish passion.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>There is no idea of marriage as something sacred in Buddhism, as it is in the Abrahamic <a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a>religions. Nevertheless, commitment of couples is honoured as a way of reducing selfish passion, of learning to be satisfied with what one has and as being one way of creating social harmony.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>There are three areas of preclusion:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1. Through genetic proximity: <bold>incest <a href="#_ftn8"> <bold>[8]</bold> </a></bold> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. Through <bold>commitment to another</bold> . This concerns sex with someone already married or committed exclusively to another person.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3. Through <bold>dharma considerations</bold> . This third covers all situations of sexual relationship—albeit with a person not in the above two categories— which are considered inappropriate by Buddhist convention. It speaks of five areas of inadmissible intercourse:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1. <italic>Inappropriate organs</italic> , meaning oral or anal intercourse.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. An <italic>inappropriate place</italic> is in the proximity of a holy being, temple, stupa or a large gathering.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3. <italic>Inappropriate times</italic> are those when lay precepts are being observed, during pregnancy, while the mother is breastfeeding or during daylight hours.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>4. An <italic>inappropriate degree</italic> is five or more times consecutively.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>5. <italic>Inappropriate forms</italic> of intercourse means principally rape but it also includes anal or oral intercourse with a person of the same sex or a hermaphrodite.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation of sexual misconduct could be rebirth as a deprived spirit. The result resembling the cause is that even if one is reborn human, one's partner will become like a hateful enemy. The environmental influence is to be reborn in a very dusty, desert land.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="4. Lying" pagetitle="4. Lying" tocentry="4. Lying">4. Lying<paragraph><essential>Given the elusive and sublime nature of real truth, we cannot define this as "not telling the truth". Its scope falls within what one believes to be true or untrue and it means knowingly lying for selfish interest. Three main areas are defined: wrecking lies, big lies and trivial lies. The first are lies about dharma accomplishment, intended to mislead followers or potential followers. To pretend or imply that one has achievements that one does not have is one of the four root downfalls for monks or nuns, as well as for dharma teachers. It is karmically very heavy. Big lies are those told with an intention to deceive in order to gain personal benefit or to benefit kith and kin or to bring harm on others. Trivial lies are a bad habit of speech.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation of lying could be to be reborn an animal, although the wrecking lies can cause false gurus to endure far worse, terrible karmic consequences, depending upon the damage they cause. The result resembling the cause is that even if one is reborn human one will be denigrated by others, who will not believe one's words or take them seriously. The third type of result is not environmental, in this case, but that of having bad breath.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="5. Divisive Speech" pagetitle="5. Divisive Speech" tocentry="5. Divisive Speech">5. Divisive Speech<paragraph><essential>This mainly involves saying things which cause friends, or people in harmony, to separate or to have bad feelings for each other. This can be done in three ways: by directly and vehemently denigrating people, by underhand insinuation or via third parties (whereas the first two are in the direct presence of the people concerned).</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation of this could be rebirth in the hell-realms. The corresponding result is that even if one is reborn human one will be separated from friends and loved ones. The environmental result is to have to live in a place where the landscape is dangerously erratic.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="6. Wounding Speech" pagetitle="6. Wounding Speech" tocentry="6. Wounding Speech">6. Wounding Speech<paragraph><essential>This is of three types: direct, insinuated or via third parties. The first is to tell someone openly of their faults and weaknesses. The second means to say hurtful things, in a half-disguised manner mingled with jest, relevant to someone present. The third is to gossip about someone's faults or weaknesses to their friends and third parties.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth in hell. The corresponding result is that, even if one is reborn a human, the sounds and words that one hears will be disturbing. The environmental influence is to be reborn in a hot and arid place where there is much evil.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="7. Useless Speech" pagetitle="7. Useless Speech" tocentry="7. Useless Speech">7. Useless Speech<paragraph><essential>This is of three types: deluded useless speech, useless worldly chatter and true yet useless speech. The first concerns the formulas and recitations of deluded belief systems <a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a>. The second concerns silly talk: jokes and the like. The third concerns attempts to explain dharma to those lacking respect or an appropriate frame of mind.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth as an animal. The corresponding result is that, even should one be reborn human, one's words will carry no weight. The resulting influence is to be reborn in a place where the seasons are completely erratic.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="8. Avidity (one could equally say cupidity or greed)" pagetitle="8. Avidity (one could equally say cupidity or greed)" tocentry="8. Avidity (one could equally say cupidity or greed)">8. Avidity (one could equally say cupidity or greed)<paragraph><essential>This is of three types: avarice concerning one's own things, other people's things and those things which belongs to neither. The first is a grasping attachment to one's own family status, physical appearance, qualities, wealth and possessions thinking, <italic>There is no one quite like me, Mine is the best</italic> etc. The second is to covet the good things others possess, thinking <italic>If only this were mine</italic> . The third involves attachment to things which belong neither to oneself or to others, such as the precious substances buried in the earth and so forth, thinking, <italic>If only I could have that</italic> .</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth as a deprived spirit. The corresponding result is that even if one is reborn human avarice will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence is to be born in a place where the quality of food is poor.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="9. Malevolence" pagetitle="9. Malevolence" tocentry="9. Malevolence">9. Malevolence<paragraph><essential>This is of three types: due to hatred, jealousy or resent. The first is to contemplate killing another because of hatred, as happens in times of war. The second, due to competition and the like, is to think about killing or harming another through fear of being surpassed. The third, due to long- standing resent, is to contemplate killing or hurting someone who has previously wronged one.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth in hell. The corresponding result is that even if one is reborn human, hatred will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence is to be reborn in a place where the food is bitter and coarse.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="10. Aberrant Belief" pagetitle="10. Aberrant Belief" tocentry="10. Aberrant Belief">10. Aberrant Belief<paragraph><essential>This is of three types: aberrant beliefs about actions and their consequences, about the truth(s) and about the precious refuges. The first of these means not believing that virtuous or harmful actions produce their respective consequences—happiness and suffering. The second is to consider that liberation will not be achieved by the proper spiritual practices. This is expressed technically as, "To believe the truth of cessation <a href="#_ftn10">[10]</a>will not be obtained by one who practises the truth of the path <a href="#_ftn11">[11]</a>". The third is to deprecate the three precious refuges <a href="#_ftn12">[12]</a>, believing them to be untrue.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>The full maturation could be rebirth an animal. The corresponding result is that even if reborn human, stupidity and confusion will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence is to be reborn in a place without harvests.</essential></paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="A Closer Look at Full Maturation" pagetitle="A Closer Look at Full Maturation" tocentry="A Closer Look at Full Maturation"><paragraph>Three kinds can be distinguished according to the affliction present, the frequency of action or the person acted upon:</paragraph><paragraph>1. If the actions were done through anger or hatred, one is more likely to be reborn in hell. If they were done through passion or attachment, one is more likely to be reborn as a deprived spirit. If they were done through stupidity and confusion one is more likely to be reborn as an animal.</paragraph><paragraph>2. Innumerable non-virtuous acts lead to rebirth in hell. A great deal of non-virtuous acts lead to rebirth as a deprived spirit. A few such harmful actions lead to rebirth as an animal.</paragraph><paragraph>3. If the non-virtuous act is committed on a special person (see below) then one may be reborn in hell. If committed against a medium object then one may be reborn a deprived spirit and if against a lesser object one may be reborn an animal.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="How Precise Can We Be?" pagetitle="How Precise Can We Be?" tocentry="How Precise Can We Be?"><paragraph>The teachings on karma, cause-and-effect, are not there so that when we see something happening in the world around us, we can cleverly deduce, "Ah, that is because in a previous life..." Unless they have reached the stage of clear cognition, even erudite lamas cannot use the karma teachings to "calculate" either the precise consequences of present actions or the reason behind present results.</paragraph><paragraph>Why then did the Buddha give these teachings? It was to give us a general idea of what is happening—the "drift", as is said in English—and especially to indicate the sort of actions to avoid at all costs. As mentioned above, the Buddha realised that ignorance of long-term karmic consequences was the main problem for humans and the cause of our inefficient, harmful, disappointing struggle for happiness. Thus he gives us these key elements so that we have some idea of what is going on and a clear guideline for action. But it is said that what is really taking place with karma only becomes clearer with profound insight, achieved at advanced stages of the path. "Only those from the seventh bodhisattva levels onwards truly understand karma," it is said. And another famous quote says that the Buddha alone knows the reason for each of the hues in a peacock's tail.</paragraph><paragraph>Now let us return to our analysis of karma.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Ten Virtuous Actions" pagetitle="The Ten Virtuous Actions" tocentry="The Ten Virtuous Actions"><table style="background:#CCFFFF;border-collapse:collapse" class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td>Physical Verbal Mental</td><td>1. To protect life 2. To be generous 3. To maintain a pure sexual conduct 4. To speak the truth straightforwardly 5. To dispel discord among people and bring them to harmony 6. To speak peacefully, sincerely and in a way that is pleasant for others 7. To speak in a way that is meaningful 8. To reduce desires and be content with what one has 9. To cultivate loving kindness and so forth 10. To penetrate the highest meaning</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>The full maturation is rebirth in the higher realms, i.e. as a human, demi-god or sense-dimension god (lower six god realms). The corresponding results are, respectively:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>To have long life and good health.</item><item>To have wealth and to be satisfied with what one has.</item><item>To have harmonious, long-lasting relationships where the partner is a joy. Or else to be happy with one's own company, if solitary.</item><item>To meet non-deceitful people and circumstances and receive dharma. To be believed, trusted and respected when one speaks.</item><item>To have good, trustworthy friends.</item><item>To be loved, hear pleasant sounds and have a pleasant voice.</item><item>To have powerful speech.</item><item>To feel satisfied and have natural generosity of spirit.</item><item>To have a loving mind and be loved.</item><item>To have insight and compassion.</item></list><paragraph>The environmental consequences are to be born in safe, harmonious places, with good crops and climate, pleasant landscapes, freedom from war and social tension, presence of dharma teachers and so forth.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Karma of Immobility" pagetitle="The Karma of Immobility" tocentry="The Karma of Immobility"><paragraph>This topic can become a little complicated in the classical texts. It defines the successive steps of a concentration-meditation practice and then takes us through the natural unfolding of the classical concentration meditation journey of the Four Absorptions ( <italic>dhy</italic>  <italic>ā</italic>  <italic>na</italic> ) and the Four Limitless Absorptions. This is a 'natural' journey, where one step of focusing the mind simply leads to another, as peace and concentration progress. Buddhists use it, Hindus use it and, in part, it is found in other faiths.</paragraph><paragraph>The karma teachings examine rebirth consequences <underline>when there is this concentration meditation alone, not channelled by Buddhist motivation.</underline> They show how reaching a certain degree of accomplishment in such meditation in this life will produce rebirth into a similar state of absorption after death. Such rebirth is still within samsara and although it lasts a long time and is pleasant, it eventually ends and whatever other karma one had created takes over. Therefore, these states have the suffering of fall, experienced by the gods (as explained in previous module). Besides the actual meditation practice, it takes a general basis of virtuous karma (generosity, loving mind) and a general absence of non-virtuous karma for there to be rebirth in the god realms.</paragraph><paragraph>When factors such as Buddhist motivation and prayers accompany exactly the same concentration meditations, they can become a vital factor for liberation. We could compare the power of concentration meditation to the wind in the sail propelling a boat. Motivation is like the intelligence of the captain, using the wind to reach the destination he wants, even to sail into the wind, if need be. Otherwise the boat will go wherever the wind takes it.</paragraph><subsubsection title="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:" pagetitle="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:" tocentry="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:">The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:<list kind="ol"><item><essential>A " <bold>launching phase</bold> " in which one acquires properly the technique and any instructions necessary, overcomes the awkwardness of unfamiliarity and becomes familiar with the practice.</essential></item><item><essential>An <bold>obstacle-removing stage</bold> , in which the technique interacts with habitual being. For instance, for beginners, simple concentration needs to overcome the constant pull and interruption of distractions. Each meditation tackles specific weaknesses or lack of skill in the mind. This stage is characterised by hard work and not too much result, with occasional breakthrough. However, due to it, and only through it, one reaches</essential></item><item><essential>The <bold>stage of absorption</bold> (also called 'Stage of Freedom'), when the mind can enjoy the true meditation and is comfortably resting in its focus.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Stage of transcendence</bold> , where the practice is now a fully-acquired part of one's being: second nature and innate skill.</essential></item></list><paragraph><essential>  </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>  </essential></paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration" pagetitle="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration" tocentry="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration">The Eight Major Classical Steps of ConcentrationThe Four Dhy ā na<paragraph><essential> <bold>First dhy ā</bold>  <bold>na</bold> where absorption is accompanied by intentional thought, analysis, mental joy and physical bliss. There is a second stage to this dhy ā na, know as its "special aspect", where the intentional thought is dropped.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Second dhy ā</bold>  <bold>na</bold> where intentional thought and analysis have been abandoned, as being gross and being obstacles to finer absorption, but mental joy and physical bliss are retained.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Third dhy ā</bold>  <bold>na</bold> where mental joy is abandoned (for equanimity) but physical bliss remains.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>Fourth dhy ā</bold>  <bold>na</bold> where physical bliss is also abandoned and there is but equanimity.</essential></paragraph>The Four Infinite &amp; Formless Contemplations<paragraph><essential> <bold>"Limitless Space"</bold> is mind absorbed in infinite space <a href="#_ftn13">[13]</a>.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>"Limitless Consciousness"</bold> , where it is realised that space is an aspect of consciousness and that consciousness is infinite.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>"Nothing Whatsoever"</bold> , where no substance is found of consciousness and mind rests in the nothingness.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>"Neither Cognition Nor Absence of Cognition"</bold> , where although there is nothing, there is nevertheless some awareness of there being nothing.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>We will look more into the use, in the various Buddhist systems, of these meditations in a later module. Here, we will content ourselves with understanding the karmic outcome of simply cultivating them as such (not in a Buddhist context where they are "steered" towards liberation or enlightenment). This is the same as the table at the end of Module 2.</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>Overall Category</bold> </td><td> <bold>Class</bold> </td><td> <bold>Realm</bold> </td></tr><tr><td>Formless Devas</td><td>Samsaric levels resulting from the Four Formless meditations</td><td>Neither Cognition Nor Absence of Cognition</td></tr><tr><td>Nothing Whatsoever</td></tr><tr><td>Infinite Consciousness</td></tr><tr><td>Infinite Space</td></tr><tr><td>Form-Dimension Devas</td><td><essential>Non-samsaric levels resulting from 4th dhyana meditation</essential></td><td><essential>"Highest" <a href="#_ftn14">[14]</a></essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>"Exceptional Sight"</essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>"Magnificent Appearance"</essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>"No Distress"</essential></td></tr><tr><td><essential>"Not Greater"</essential></td></tr><tr><td>Samsaric levels resulting from 4th dhyana meditation</td><td>"Greater Result"</td></tr><tr><td>"Produced by Merit"</td></tr><tr><td>"Cloudless"</td></tr><tr><td>Levels resulting from 3rd dhyana meditation</td><td>"Extended Virtue"</td></tr><tr><td>"Measureless Virtue"</td></tr><tr><td>"Lesser Virtue"</td></tr><tr><td>Levels resulting from 2nd dhyana meditation</td><td>"Illuminating"</td></tr><tr><td>"Measureless Light"</td></tr><tr><td>"Lesser Light"</td></tr><tr><td>Levels resulting from the 1st dhyana meditation</td><td>"Great Brahmas'"</td></tr><tr><td>"Leading Brahmas'"</td></tr><tr><td>"Brahma's"</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>Having taken a glimpse at the principal elements of virtuous, non-virtuous and meditation karma, we will now consider some very important points about karma in general.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="What does it take to make karma?" pagetitle="What does it take to make karma?" tocentry="What does it take to make karma?"><paragraph><essential>Not every action performed by body, speech and mind creates karma. It takes six factors for a karma to be produced:</essential></paragraph><list kind="ol"><item><essential>There needs to have been the definite intention to do it.</essential></item><item><essential>It needs to have been carried out as intended.</essential></item><item><essential>It needs to be an action capable of producing karmic consequences.</essential></item><item><essential>The action needs to have been completed.</essential></item><item><essential>The doer is pleased with doing it, at the time it is done, and has no regrets.</essential></item><item><essential>No remedial action <a href="#_ftn15">[15]</a>is taken before fruition commences.</essential></item></list><paragraph>When all six combine, an action is known as a <italic>karma enacted and established.</italic> "Established" means that an imprint has been programmed ("established") in the universal basis consciousness <a href="#_ftn16">[16]</a>and it will later generate results.</paragraph><paragraph>If one of the six is absent, there is <italic>karma enacted but not established</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>If one or more of the six is weak—e.g. confused motivation, action not quite carried out as intended etc.—then the resulting karma is weaker. This is particularly true when remedial actions, which give rise to what is called "purification", are resorted to. The consequences of even very heavy karmas can be considerably reduced—and even totally neutralised—if the appropriate remedy is applied sufficiently.</paragraph><subsubsection title="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma" pagetitle="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma" tocentry="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma">Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma<paragraph>The actions of body and speech are the ones which involve other people. They are each quite specific and consequently each produces its karmic results in the future. There is also a cumulative effect (see below). In-between the initial action and its result, years and lifetimes can go by with nothing happening related to that initial action. All the time however, the imprint of the initial action remains in the doer's consciousness, waiting to be triggered by the right circumstances to produce its effect. It is very much like a seed that has been planted in the ground, in the autumn. When the spring warmth and rains come, it will germinate. To human eyes, it is as though the little green shoot is something entirely new, popping out of the ground. Thus it is with the things that happen to us in the world and with the people who are significant in our lives. The results of the physical and verbal karma of our past lives, as listed above, can seem to pop out of nowhere in the form of what other people say and do to us, along with the environmental consequences mentioned above.</paragraph><paragraph>Mental karma is something very different. It is a constantly-evolving story of conditioning, involving the person alone. One does not have to wait for lifetimes for the results of good mind karma to manifest. The impact is immediate, shifting the mind a little this way or that. This is very good news indeed for us and it is what enabled Milarepa <a href="#_ftn17">[17]</a>to become a Buddha in one lifetime.</paragraph><paragraph>Were this not the case, there would be an even greater need for faith than there is already, as we would just have to trust that our good thoughts, prayers, meditations and so on will bear their fruit in some future life alone, while we are condemned to have our habitual mind until we die. That is certainly not the case: a confused or unsettled mind can become serene and wise in just a matter of years. In spectacular cases, a person's mind can make a life-changing breakthrough from one day to the next. However, for the body, if someone lacks, strength, health and beauty then one has no choice but to put up with it in this life and to wait for good physical karma created in this existence to generate a beautiful, healthy, long-living body in the next.</paragraph><paragraph>Our mind is also the "king", determining what its subjects—body and speech—will do. Where the mind goes, body and speech will follow. Anger in the mind will lead to violence and abusive speech. The sexual cravings of the mind can lead a person into all sorts of sordid material realities. Spiritual beauty in the mind—as faith, inspiration, compassionate love—will lead one into wholesome physical and verbal habits and will attract the material circumstances where good things can be found and cultivated.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="Full Maturation" pagetitle="Full Maturation" tocentry="Full Maturation"><paragraph>As we have seen, the full maturation of acts is to be reborn in one or another of the six realms. The state into which a person is born in one life is mainly a consequence of the sum total of the actions done, i.e. the karma enacted and established, in the previous life. There will also be some "leftover" influence from lives before that.</paragraph><paragraph>For example, our own full maturation in this life is to be human and this in itself exposes us to certain general experiences and risks which are those of human beings. Thus, one needs to distinguish between generalised consequences ( <italic>full maturation</italic> karma), due to the type of birth, and specific consequences of specific past acts that are <italic>results resembling their causes</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph>Khenchen Thrangu Rinpoche explains therefore that <bold>not every single thing that happens is "my karma"</bold> If someone catches a cold today, because of not being dressed enough in a chill breeze, it is simply part-and-parcel of having a human body in this world of the elements <a href="#_ftn18">[18]</a>. It is a general <italic>full maturation</italic> result and not a specific <italic>result resembling its cause,</italic> where one becomes unwell because of a specific act of harming life at a precise moment in the past. This distinction also applies to less obvious things than catching colds. He made the point because some Buddhists have a tendency to read too much meaning into everything. They would think, "It's not for nothing that I caught a cold today. It's a sign!" and then continue to either attribute it to a specific past karma or to start to associate it with other factors, such as the person they met that day, putting two and two together to make eleven. One should always remember that, until the seventh bodhisattva level, what we understand of karma is just the tip of the iceberg.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Results resembling their causes" pagetitle="Results resembling their causes" tocentry="Results resembling their causes"><paragraph>Although it is generally not possible to remember past lives <a href="#_ftn19">[19]</a>—either at all or in any significant detail—it is said that <italic>you can know what you did in the past life by looking at your life now</italic> . This means that one can start to identify specific personal karma when patterns emerge and repeat themselves and one starts to recognise that the seeming problems lies not with the world or other people but with the karma that one carries, wherever one goes. A few examples:</paragraph><paragraph>· Someone works very hard but is always scraping to make a living. The person may try this job or that, may change profession or even country in an effort to get some financial comfort but somehow prosperity always eludes. There is a good likelihood of lack of generosity, or perhaps dishonesty, in a former life.</paragraph><paragraph>· Attempts to find a soul-mate fall flat on their face, time after time. Even though the companion is quite different each time, somehow the same problems, a similar darkness, a similar reaction, crops up. There is a likelihood of unskilful sexual karma in the past life. Also maybe the perpetuation of a mind state—mental karma—seeking the impossible.</paragraph><paragraph>· A person speaks the truth and can express it well but nobody wants to listen. People have no respect for that person's speech and often look down on them. This can be a sign of untruthful speech or much useless speech in past lives. An interesting counterpart is the powerful speech of great masters. They may say just a few words but those words remain engraved in the heart for years and the disciple can still hear the teacher saying them, in her or his mind, decades later. This is the result of lifetimes of teaching the truth, in a way that suits each person.</paragraph><paragraph>· In Tibetan medicine, some health problems (not the majority by the way), known as "long-term wind-element disorders", are attributed to specific karma. These are remarkable proofs, in a way, of karma, because they can generate one clinical condition after another. When the one has been treated, another appears, as though the "wind" had left one organ and entered a different one. Treating it can be like trying to chase a rat out of a room: it runs first into this corner, then that. These are the result of harmful physical actions in a past life.</paragraph><paragraph>On a more positive note, meeting the dharma and meeting pure beings is an exceptional positive result from our past life or lives. As one connects once again with the teachings and the practice, a whole world of experience is trawled up from the psyche: it seems like a new world at first but gradually becomes recognised as the return of an old and familiar one. Flashes and moments of past blessing can be remembered but also the old problems—the places where we got stuck or faltered before—will also emerge as time goes by. Each practice can awaken an old karma, to be taken forward, and special things, such as long retreats, have their own, unpredictable karma, for those who had the chance to do them in past lives.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Other points about karma" pagetitle="Other points about karma" tocentry="Other points about karma"><subsubsection title="Karma does not fade with time" pagetitle="Karma does not fade with time" tocentry="Karma does not fade with time">Karma does not fade with time<paragraph>Unless a remedy is applied, a specific karma can remain completely dormant for one or more lifetimes, sometimes many lifetimes, yet its power does not fade with the passing of time. When the conditions which trigger its fruition are united, it will emerge with all its power.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Generally, karma is non-transferable" pagetitle="Generally, karma is non-transferable" tocentry="Generally, karma is non-transferable">Generally, karma is non-transferable<paragraph>"The results of karma always ripen in their doer," it says in the <italic>Compendium of Knowledge</italic> . There will never be a cosmic mix-up, like a bank account error where one client's money or debt is shifted to another client's account. There is good reason for this. Creating a karma programmes the consciousness of the doer, who then carries that programming throughout the rest of his or her life and on into the next life. We can understand the mechanism by considering the trauma of a dog bite. A person bitten may think no more of it for fifty years but then one day meet a dog exactly like the one that bit him or her in childhood. The mind carries the memory of the event: where or how is a mystery but it obviously does. That particular conditioning is not somehow going to be transferred from the person and turn up in someone who was never bitten.</paragraph><paragraph>Each individual's stream of consciousness is unique and so the karma in one consciousness (we could say "mind") stays in that consciousness, through death, into the next life and on and on until triggered to fruition. Therefore when we say the results ripen in "the doer", it is in some ways enigmatic, as the person we are in one life is quite different from the person we may become in the next. Nevertheless, the karmic programming from the old "person" is there, like it or not. In some ways, it can seem very "unfair", yet it is simply like that. It is like the pollution thrown into a river upstream being experienced by the inhabitants downstream. Or, to take a truer example, like the physical or psychological damage of an ex-drug-taker persisting long into a future where they have no more interest whatsoever in drugs and have become "cleaner-than-clean". This "unfairness" of inheriting karma from the person we were in a past life is one of the reasons the Buddha, in his compassion, shines light on action, so that we can become lucid and make the future life how we would like it to be.</paragraph><paragraph><essential> <italic>Exercise and Topic of Reflection:</italic> Some people get very upset at the idea of karma being the cause of ailments in this life. Taking the example of someone who is severely disabled, physically or mentally, they see it as an insult to the person, implying they have something evil about them for which they are being punished: that they have somehow deserved it. The Buddhist response it that there is neither punishment nor reason for guilt. It is just the nature of things and that also the "person" now, although being the ongoing consciousness stream of the "person" in previous lives, is quite a different being. Anything could have happened in between the ancient cause and this present result. Please consider the above paragraphs and try to understand and argue each side of the case until you come to your own conclusion.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>A second possible step to this exercise is to consider examples at the other extreme. There are those who are healthy, long-living and prosperous now yet who seem not to be good people. The prosperous are not necessarily generous now and the handsome and fit are not necessarily pillars of moral conduct.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>Karma is not <italic>instant karma <a href="#_ftn20"> <bold>[20]</bold> </a></italic> . It works itself out over long time periods and is very complex.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Are there exceptions to this non-transferability of karma? In some ways, there are. It is possible, through the coming-together of the power of interdependence and the power of compassion, for one person to alleviate the sufferings of another being. It is exceptional but it does happen, as was the case with Dharmarakshita, a lama who winced and cried out in pain one day in a teaching. When asked why, he said that some people outside the temple had thrown a big, sharp rock at a dog and that he had taken the dog's pain. The disciples were a little incredulous and first went outside where indeed a dog had been stoned. Returning to the temple, the lama lifted his robe and they saw the wound and a bruise emerging, in an equivalent place to where the dog had been hit.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Karma is infallible" pagetitle="Karma is infallible" tocentry="Karma is infallible">Karma is infallible<paragraph>It will never happen that a "virtuous" karma produces suffering for its doer in the next life. It will never happen that a non-virtuous action produces happy consequences for the doer in the next life. The seeds of a poisonous plant produce a poisonous plant, by their very nature. The data for that is programmed into the seed from day one. The seeds of a delicious fruit will similarly produce a delicious fruit. It will never happen that you plant a plum stone and it produces a deadly nightshade bush the following year.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Karma and Morality" pagetitle="Karma and Morality" tocentry="Karma and Morality">Karma and Morality<paragraph>Ethics are a fundamental part of each person's life. Everyone has some sense of g <italic>ood</italic> and <italic>bad</italic> conduct, of <italic>right</italic> and <italic>wrong.</italic> These are defined variously in the different faiths and belief-systems. In the Abrahamic faiths—the so-called "religions of the book" <a href="#_ftn21">[21]</a>—the guidelines come from God, via prophets or his son. For Humanists, they arise from reason and a basic sense of human dignity. For Buddhists, although we have our dharma teachings on "virtue" and "non-virtue" from the Buddha, we do not adopt them as a set of ethical values <italic>just</italic> because he taught them. Rather, we see them as the natural way things happen and it is simply that the Buddha opens our eyes to what "is":</paragraph><image width="436" src="module3_files.image006.png" align=""/></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Buddhist Values" pagetitle="Buddhist Values" tocentry="Buddhist Values">Buddhist Values<paragraph> <italic>Virtuous</italic> or <italic>good</italic> or <italic>meritorious</italic> (one finds all those terms in the texts, and more) actions are <underline>self-defined through their own effects</underline> —in both the short and long term. Generosity helps other people in the immediate present, it beautifies the mind of the giver and also generates happiness, wealth and satisfaction for the doer in future lives. Thus it is <underline>innately virtuous</underline> , not virtuous because someone, the Buddha, declared it so.</paragraph><image width="436" src="module3_files.image007.png" align=""/><paragraph>Similarly, <italic>non-virtuous, evil</italic> or <italic>damaging</italic> actions are self-defined by their effects. Killing or violence hurts other beings in the immediate present, it sullies the mind of the doer in the present and it brings the painful consequences of illness and early death for the doer in future lives. It is innately non-virtuous.</paragraph><paragraph>Please contemplate this point, and all its implications for Buddhist morality, at length. Further, be careful not to become confused about the absolute-truth teachings of <italic>"no good, no evil", "no samsara, no nirvana", "samsara and nirvana are the same"</italic> and so forth <italic>.</italic> A very advanced degree of meditation experience is necessary before the meaning of those phrases is properly known. Beware of taking them at face value and thereby letting them throw into question the value of strictly applying conventional Buddhist ethics. None of our great masters ever wanted that and so many of the greatest (Saraha, Karmapa etc.) warned against it.</paragraph><paragraph>Those absolute-truth teachings are there, on a verbal level, to help us understand that ultimately any value-judgement, such as <italic>good</italic> or <italic>evil</italic> , will be transcended by direct perception of truth. They help us establish a horizon of going beyond presumptions and fixed ideas, both about the world and about enlightenment. In the end, these and all concepts are always subjective and highly-limited.</paragraph><paragraph>Understanding the nature of our own projections about relative reality is one thing. Understanding what is actually happening in relative reality, above and beyond our subjective labelling, is another. The karma teachings are there to help us with the latter. This is why Guru Rinpoche said, so famously:</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Make your view as broad as space but your action as fine as flour.</italic> </paragraph><paragraph>In other words, even for those who have mastered <italic>mahamudra</italic> or <italic>dzogchen</italic> and other great teachings, and who have an enlightened view as broad as space, there is no virtuous action that is too small to not be worth doing and likewise no harmful action that is so trivial it is not worth avoiding. This attention to detail while remaining ever mindful of voidness is something we can observe and admire in the best lamas we meet.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="Scale and Proportion in Karma" pagetitle="Scale and Proportion in Karma" tocentry="Scale and Proportion in Karma">Scale and Proportion in Karma <paragraph>The outcomes of actions are not easily calculable. It is nothing like "an eye for an eye" and it does not mean that exactly the same thing done in this life will happen, in return, to the doer in the next life. It is not a simple reversal of roles, where someone who steals a car will have to have a similar car stolen, with a similar <italic>modus operandi</italic> , in the next life. That sort of thing can happen, as some spectacular stories of karma in the sutras illustrate, but it does not at all have to be like that. The scale can be enormously different: a small cause can produce a great effect and many causes can produce only a single result.</paragraph><paragraph>If the mind informing an action is very strong indeed—powerful hatred or powerful compassionate love, for instance—then it is said that just one instant of action can produce hundreds of lifetimes, and in some cases aeons, of result. In those moments when our minds are uplifted, filled with faith in the absolute and loving care for all beings, the karmic consequences are great indeed. It is compared to a single powerful seed, which with time produces a great harvest. On the other hand, bitter, hateful abuse directed towards a holy being or one's parents (see below) is compared to poison, which may be small in volume but which spoils the whole feast of the future and leads to downfall.</paragraph><paragraph>What determines the scale of the outcome? Several factors: the motivating mind, the action itself and the "field", meaning the person to whom it is done.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="The Four Special Fields of Action" pagetitle="The Four Special Fields of Action" tocentry="The Four Special Fields of Action">The Four Special Fields of Action<paragraph>Either because of their own very nature or because of their strong karmic links with us, there are four special fields of action which generate much more powerful results than other, more "indifferent", fields. They are:</paragraph><paragraph>1. Those particularly designated by their qualities, i.e. gurus, the Three Most Precious Refuges etc.</paragraph><paragraph>2. Those particularly designated by the benefit (they have brought us)—father, mother etc.</paragraph><paragraph>3. Those particularly designated by their sufferings—the sick, the unprotected etc.</paragraph><paragraph>4. Those particularly designated by the harm (they have done us)—enemies etc.</paragraph><paragraph>For this reason, although one needs to be mindful and aware of action all the time, there is a particular need to be mindful in what one says and does when in the company of the above. Of all instances, karma enacted in the presence of a buddha is strongest.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection></section><section index="5" title="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma" pagetitle="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma" tocentry="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma"><subsection title="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma" pagetitle="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma" tocentry="The Afflictions ( klesha ), the Cause of Karma"><image width="443" src="module3_files.image008.png" align=""/><paragraph>Why does someone do the harmful actions described in the previous section? Mind is the king and body and speech are its slaves. It is a non-virtuous mind that causes someone to do non-virtuous actions, just as it is a virtuous one that leads them to virtuous acts.</paragraph><paragraph>Without anger towards animals (for instance towards aphids for damaging the roses) or desire for their meat to eat and their skins to wear or the ignorance of animal sacrifice, why would one kill or harm them? Without self-centred passion, why would someone engage in non-virtuous sexual conduct? Without self-interest, why would one lie? In general, actions are performed to get what is wanted—for oneself or one's kith and kin—or to avoid the unwanted. One simple analysis often referred to in Tibetan literature is that of the Eight Worldly Concerns, i.e. seeking:</paragraph><list kind="ol"><item>To gain what one needs or wants.</item><item>To avoid losing what one has.</item><item>To seek pleasure .</item><item>To avoid what is unpleasant or painful .</item><item>To be praised .</item><item>To avoid blame .</item><item>To gain respect .</item><item>To avoid bad reputation .</item></list><paragraph><essential>The Eight Worldly Concerns - Mnemonic</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>Loss and gain, pleasure and pain, praise and blame, fame and bad name</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Taken together, all the motivating emotions and mind-states behind non-virtuous karma are known as <italic>klesha</italic> , a word meaning <italic>afflictions, defilements, poisons, cankers...</italic> If one simply represses the harmful actions themselves, without working on their causes, there will be bottled-up anger, passion and so forth. Besides making people uncomfortable, suppressed feelings may well one day erupt, in moments of weakness, and do untold damage. Therefore it is important to understand clearly these klesha and to learn how to recognise them, reduce them and eventually remove them by the very root.</paragraph><paragraph>As we are investigating the Truth of the Causes of Suffering, we should only be considering here the klesha, the thoughts and feelings—known technically as <italic>mental events,</italic> the fourth aggregate—which make a person do the non-virtuous acts defined above in the <italic>karma</italic> section. However, since in that section we also considered virtuous and meditative karma then, for completeness, a list of the virtuous <italic>mental events</italic> are included in the Annexes, at the <a href="#virtuous">end</a>of this document.</paragraph><paragraph>As far as non-virtuous mental events are concerned, there are the six basic non-virtuous mental events and the twenty-one related or <italic>subsidiary</italic> non-virtuous mental events. The following is taken from Ju Mipham Rinpoche's <italic>Entering the Ways of the Wise</italic> , as taught in Samye Ling by the Goshir Gyaltsab Rinpoche.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The 6 basic non-virtuous mental events" pagetitle="The 6 basic non-virtuous mental events" tocentry="The 6 basic non-virtuous mental events"><list kind="ol"><item><essential> <bold>Ignorance</bold> - not to know about karma, cause-and-effect, the truth(s) or the Three Precious Refuges <a href="#_ftn22">[22]</a>. This gives rise to the afflictions.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Desire and attachment</bold> - to be stickily involved with the tainted aggregates of the three dimensions of existence: this engenders the sufferings of existence. It is said to be of two types:</essential></item></list><paragraph><essential>1. <italic>Involvement with desires and the objects of the sense fields</italic>: attachment to the sense dimension.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. <italic>Involvement with existence itself</italic>: attachment to the two higher dimensions.</essential></paragraph><list kind="ol"><item><essential> <bold>Anger and hatred</bold> - a state of mind very irritated by other beings, sufferings or the circumstances that provoke suffering. It is this which prevents one from enjoying happiness and which forms a basis for unwholesome action.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Pride</bold> - to be arrogant and high-minded due to one of the 'destructible complex' attitudes (see below). There are seven main sorts <a href="#_ftn23">[23]</a>. Generally they are a basis for not respecting others and for the arising of suffering.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Doubt</bold> - to be "in two minds" about the truths and their meaning/significance. This stops one from engaging in what is virtuous.</essential></item><item><essential> <bold>Negatively-affected views</bold> - form the basis for all the various mistaken views (attitudes).</essential></item></list><paragraph>The last of these points can be developed into <bold>The Five Main Misconceptions</bold> </paragraph><list kind="ol"><item> Attitudes related to the "destructible complex" - these are inner attitudes, mental postures, philosophical stances—and sometimes religious beliefs and dogmas—that mistakenly attribute the idea of "I", "mine", "we" or "ours" to the "five aggregates which attract suffering" (the skandhas). For example, the first aggregate is form: in our case the human body. Some people take the physical body as "I", the self, or as "Mine", belonging to the self. Other people attribute the self to the third aggregate, perception: "I am what I perceive the world to be." Altogether there are twenty such permutations known, not very elegantly, as the Views of the Twenty Destructible Complexes, so-called since the illusion of a lasting self is attributed to something which is impermanent and subject to destruction [24]. These twenty constitute the basis for the other mistaken attitudes.</item><item> The extremists' attitude —Eternalist or nihilistic beliefs, i.e respectively thinking the ego or the five aggregates are eternal (permanent) or nothing at all. These create obstacles to emancipation through (practice of) the middle way.</item><item> Perverse attitudes —that consider conditions which do exist—such as cause and effect etc.—to be non-­existent. These bring about the destruction of the roots of virtue.</item><item> Conviction that one's own attitude is best —to view the three harmful attitudes above and/or their bases (the five aggregates) as being supreme and holy. For instance, an extremist may attribute the idea of self to consciousness (fifth aggregate) and define it as eternal, making it God, and then refuse any thought which puts that into question. This makes solid entrenchment in misconception.</item><item> Conviction that one's moral discipline and code of conduct are best —this follows on from the previous points. It is to consider moral disciplines a nd rules of conduct w hich are innately impure and unemancipated — and their bases, the five aggregates — as being able to actually liberate one. This renders austerities and hardships useless.</item></list></subsection><subsection title="T he 21 Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events" pagetitle="T he 21 Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events" tocentry="T he 21 Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events"><list kind="ol"><item> Wrath - a n intensification of anger, which makes one ready to inflict real harm by beating etc;</item><item> Resent - an other aspect of anger, whereby one will not let go of thoughts of harm or make place for forbearance.</item><item> Rage - arises through wrath and resent. It causes one to lose patience and shout abuse.</item><item> Irritation - also part of anger. It causes one to lose compassion and love and to scorn others.</item><item> Jealousy - also an aspect of anger. A deeply distre ssed mind caused by attachment to one's own reputation, honour etc. and by not being able to bear the good things which happen to others.</item><item> Worldly Discontent - a mind not naturally at ease: this forms a basis for the unwholesome.</item><item> Deceit - to conceal one's shortcomings through attachment to fame and respect etc. this is a devious state of mind that maintains the unwholesome. It is part of desire, aversion and stupidity. It creates obstacles to encountering (heeding) the most useful advice.</item><item> Hypocrisy or Pretence - through attachment to fame , honours and the like, to pretend to have qualities that one does not really possess. Thereby one attempts to deceive others by such untruths. It is an aspect of stupidity and desire. It creates a support for the main and subsidiary afflictions as well as laying a foundation for a corrupt way of life.</item><item> Absence of Self-Respect - in one's private conduct, one does not try to overcome darker habits. This belongs to the three poisons and provides nourishment to the afflictions and their subsidiaries.</item><item> Absence of a Sense of Shame - this is similar but in terms of relations with others: one does not shun non-virtu ous activities but blatantly pursues tham. This is part of the three poisons and a support for all the affliction s.</item><item> Dissimulation - part of both stupidity and desire , whereby one does not respond to useful advice but prefers (instead) to cover up shortcomings. It acts as a basis for not following up regret.</item><item> Avarice - through desire and attachment, personal possessions become considered to be something special. This prevents generosity and simplification of life.</item><item> Narcissism - the sort of state of mind that loves and clings to whatever tainted good things are present, such as good health , youth etc ., with complete disinterest and contempt for anyone who does not hold you in great esteem. This is a contributory factor to the prim ary and secondary affliction s.</item><item> Absence of Trust/Faith - an aspect of stupidity. It is an absence of interest for all that is wholesome and virtuous. It forms a basis for wasting precious life time .</item><item> Laziness - it is involvement with unworthy activities , such as delighting in sleep, lounging, hang in g around etc. It makes people t a ke life too easily without either enthusiasm for virtue or its application. It is the enemy of diligence.</item><item> Negligence - arises through the three poisons and laziness: one does not pay careful attention to the principles of action (adopt the good, shun the bad). This is the enemy of c are, bringing about an increase of non-virtue and a decrease of virtue.</item><item> Lack of mindfulness - one forgets or becomes vague about virtuous intentions. It is the basis for distraction and a giving way to the affliction s connected with the contrary of mindfulness as well as to the wrong sort of mindfulness that accompanies them .</item><item> Unawareness - intelligence that is distracted and a ccompanied by the affliction s. When acting through the 'three doors' of body, speech and mind, there is little or no awareness. Things are done just any old way: this creates opportunity for mistakes to happen.</item><item> Torpor - is part of stupidity - a physical and mental heaviness where the mind is unworkable and unable to be directed to its object. Instead it is drawn into an inner obscurity. This lays the foundation for the negative affliction s.</item><item> Agitation - part of desire/attachment: to chase after attractive characteristics. The mind vacillates towards its object and is no longer w orkable . It loses its peace. This constitutes an ob stacle to samatta (tran­quility) .</item><item> Total Distractedness - part of the three poisons: the mind is pulled to its object and wanders. This prevents it being concentrated on a worthwhile goal. There are various types (of distraction) - outw a rds, inwards, to be carried away by detail etc.</item></list><paragraph>These 21 affliction s are called "the subsidiary affliction s" because they are part of, and close to, the primary one s.</paragraph><paragraph>end of extract from Mipham Rinpoche text</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="6" title="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other" pagetitle="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other" tocentry="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other"><subsection title="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other" pagetitle="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other" tocentry="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of Self and Other"><image width="461" src="module3_files.image009.png" align=""/><paragraph>Once it is well understood that the afflictions described above are the reason why people act—to get what they want and to avoid what they don't want—the next question is of course, "Well then, why are these desires, jealousies, pride, fears and anger in the mind?" The main reason is because the mind has a fixed and deluded notion of self, of "I" (of ego, of persona, however you prefer to express it). The Theravada and Hinayana teachings focus almost uniquely on this <bold>ego-illusion</bold> as being the <bold>prime cause of the afflictions</bold> . In Mahayana Buddhism, this delusion of self is taken as part of a twofold process of projecting dualistic delusions concerning:</paragraph><paragraph>· Oneself and</paragraph><paragraph>· Other people and the world.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Ego-illusion" pagetitle="Ego-illusion" tocentry="Ego-illusion"><paragraph>Many people misunderstand non-ego. The Buddha's teaching is not that a person does not exist <italic>at all</italic> , that there is nothing there whatsoever. By one day understanding non-ego, we do not suddenly disappear in a puff of smoke! The Buddha teaches very clearly that we each exist relatively as an exceedingly complex, ever-changing stream of the five aggregates. What does not exist lastingly and substantially is <underline>the imagined self</underline> that is projected—very grossly—onto that real stream of the aggregates. It is only an idea, with all the frailty and changeability that ideas have. It is called a delusion or an illusion. One could equally say <italic>projection of self</italic> , <italic>assumption, preconceived idea</italic> etc.</paragraph><paragraph>The illusory idea of "I", "me", "us", "mine" etc. is the root of our passions and hates, pride and jealousy. By understanding the nature of the five aggregates (what we truly are) and by dismantling these fixed delusions of self, freedom from samsara can be attained, definitively.</paragraph><paragraph>Overcoming the enormous power of delusions of self is equally a fundamental part of Mahayana Buddhism. It is the only way to freedom. However, by tackling <italic>all</italic> dualistic delusions—of both self <underline>and</underline> other—not only freedom but also enlightenment can be attained. There are two main aspects to dualistic delusion: the "dualistic split" and dualistic thought.</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="The Dualistic Split" pagetitle="The Dualistic Split" tocentry="The Dualistic Split"><paragraph>In year three, when we study the transformation of the eight consciousnesses into the five wisdoms, we will investigate the seventh consciousness, known as the <italic>warping consciousness</italic> . It performs two functions:</paragraph><list kind="ul"><item>It splits the awareness of the present moment arbitrarily into two.</item><item>It simultaneously triggers the following moment of consciousness.</item></list><paragraph>This happens instant after instant, every instant, and is part of the fundamental mechanism of mind, until one reaches the 8 <superscript>th</superscript> bodhisattva level. In actual fact, the information in the mind at any instant has no compartments, no two sides, no inner and outer. Yet the seventh consciousness provokes an arbitrary split, giving the impression that some things within any instant of awareness are the inner subject while other things are the outer object. It creates a strange, invisible borderline, wherein the inner observing awareness feels like "I" and the outer thing observed seems much more distant and feels like something else or someone else. The line is arbitrary as it changes from moment to moment.</paragraph><image width="472" src="module3_files.image010.png" align=""/><paragraph> <bold>Exercise:</bold> In a quiet moment, perhaps during meditation, look out of a window at an object in the far distance. Become aware of your awareness and feel how one part of the experience feels like "you", looking. Then become aware of the distant "thing" that you are looking at, and how it feels "other". After a while, become aware of both sides—you and the thing—at the same time and of the combined feeling of subject-object, perceiver-perceived. Then, quietly, let your gaze shift from the distant object to the window itself: look at the window. Then look again at the object. As you do this, shifting focus from the window to the distant object, be aware of how this invisible boundary between subject and object shifts. You can continue the exercise by shifting your awareness next from the window to your own body. Recognise how your body, which felt like part of "me", the subject, when you were looking at the distant object, has now shifted from being on the inside to being on the "outside" and it has become "the object".</paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Dualistic Thought" pagetitle="Dualistic Thought" tocentry="Dualistic Thought"><paragraph>The above split of consciousness happens—whether one likes it or not—every single instant, for all beings of the six realms.</paragraph><paragraph>On the basis of this split, the conceptual mind of a being capable of constructive thought, such as a human, builds up stories. These stories are very important as they determine the nature and quality of life. In fact, for the most part, they <italic>are</italic> the nature and quality of life. For example, if someone lives in a land of much rain and has an inner dialogue repeating the story that "I adore the rain", then he feels blessed to live there. Perhaps the person living next door detests rain and feels cursed to live in such a place. The climate is the same: the inner hermeneutic is different.</paragraph><paragraph>One facet of the inner dialogue is the story told about "me". It has built up over time, with some parts deeply, sometimes secretly, entrenched and other parts more superficial. The other facet of the inner dialogue is that of the many stories told about "other": other people—mother, father, brother, sister, friend, enemy, colleagues and so forth— and other things—the world, politics, places, situations and the like.</paragraph><paragraph>Although all of those inner reference cards of other people are never any more than ephemeral thoughts, they can become seemingly very "solid" over time. They turn into fixed ideas and rigid preconceptions, so much so that when one pulls up an image of the person in the mind, it can bring floods of emotion—tenderness, anger, nostalgia, passion... The same happens with more abstract concepts: ideas about politics, religion, nationality, culture and the like. People would die or kill on account of the thoughts and images in their "head".</paragraph><paragraph>The "I" side of the story complicates itself into four departments: "I" and "mine" and the extended self of "we" and "ours". In other words, ego extends to encompass family, or friends, or nation, or religious group. It also extends to material and intellectual possessions.</paragraph><paragraph>The ideas of "I" and "other", as described above lead to the afflictions. This is because once "I" has been defined in a certain way and "other" has been defined in a certain way, then it will follow that "I" will <italic>crave</italic> for certain "others" and <italic>detest</italic> other "others". The imaginary "I" will be <italic>proud</italic> of itself compared to some others and <italic>jealous</italic> of other "others". There are very vivid examples of this in the way people fall in and out of love, or in the religious or racial conflicts that beleaguer our world, or in the pride of a football supporter. It is happening everywhere, all the time.</paragraph><paragraph>On a positive note, there is an extraordinary potential in this process. Although one has no power at all to alter the dualistic split itself, one <bold>can</bold> change the inner dualistic storytelling—about each side of the split—to great advantage. In Mahayana and Vajrayana Buddhism, it is done in a systematic way using skilful method. However, it can happen even in ordinary life in quite a spectacular way. By changing the story, a person who was formerly deeply loved can become a detested enemy overnight. Something once scorned can become cherished. A person can become proud of his or her origins, whereas previously there was shame. Meat, previously relished, can become repulsive for someone who turns vegetarian.</paragraph><image width="472" src="module3_files.image011.png" align=""/>Exercise:<paragraph><essential> <bold>In Mahayana Buddhism delusions of ego are gradually and harmoniously replaced by the bodhisattva ideal.</bold> </essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential> <bold>In Vajrayana Buddhism, the delusions are replaced by identifying with the "deity" <a href="#_ftn25"> <bold>[25]</bold> </a>.</bold> </essential></paragraph><paragraph>We will return to these later in the course. The point in this section is to recognise the power of dualistic thought to give rise to, and then nourish, the afflictions.</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="7" title="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality" pagetitle="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality" tocentry="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"><subsection title="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality" pagetitle="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality" tocentry="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"><image width="461" src="module3_files.image012.png" align=""/><paragraph><essential>Why is there the instant-by-instant dualistic split of awareness? It occurs because of the ignorance veiling mind's true nature. When will it end? The veil is torn apart when ignorance becomes primordial wisdom.</essential></paragraph></subsection><subsection title="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance" pagetitle="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance" tocentry="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance"><paragraph><essential>These are the two main aspects of ignorance:</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>· <bold>Concomitant ignorance</bold> or <bold>simultaneous ignorance <a href="#_ftn26"> <bold>[26]</bold> </a></bold> dates back to time without beginning and accompanies each moment of awareness. It is karmically neutral. What is ignored is absolute truth: the true nature.</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>· <bold>Conceptual Ignorance</bold> is one of the mind poisons. By solidifying the chronic ignorance into fixed ideas of self and other, it gives rise to karma that perpetuates samsara. It is therefore one of the afflictions. Further, it causes specific ignorance and confusion about the relative truth and in particular the nature of cause-and-effect.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Ignorance is the way we translate the Sanskrit term <italic>avidy</italic>  <italic>ā</italic> or the Tibetan term <italic>ma rig pa</italic> . In both cases, it is a negative, meaning <italic>not-knowing, unaware</italic> . The opposites are important terms in dharma: <italic>vidy</italic>  <italic>ā</italic> and <italic>rig pa</italic> (pronounced <italic>rikpa</italic> ) meaning intelligent awareness. The term has the feel of bright, awakened clarity.</paragraph><paragraph>In the case of <bold>chronic ignorance, w</bold> hat is not known is defined as:</paragraph><paragraph>· Non-ego, in the Hinayana and Theravada systems, and</paragraph><paragraph>· Non-dual <a href="#_ftn27">[27]</a>, pure, enlightened nature of mind (voidness or buddha nature) in the Mahayana.</paragraph><paragraph>It is (fortunately) karmically neutral, as otherwise, since it occurs in each instant and it has been happening since time immemorial, the harmful karma generated would be devastating and unbearable, with no hope of ever being free of it.</paragraph><paragraph>This ignorance is brought to an end by wisdom but not by wisdom as thoughts. The wisdom which ends ignorance is a vivid, direct awareness of the nature of things. In the Hinayana and Theravadin systems, this means becoming directly aware of the meaning of the Four Truths of the Realised. This happens in sixteen "moments" of awakening: four for each truth. Profound realisation of non-ego is accomplished during those sixteen.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Mahayana, one realises the non-dual purity of everyone and of every thing. There are many names for this and the various traditions each have their favourites. It is called buddha nature, the true nature of mind, <italic>sunyata</italic> , voidness, <italic>mahamudra</italic> , the great perfection, the great middle way, <italic>prajnaparamita</italic> , the one-and-only, <italic>dharmata</italic> , the unique bindu, buddha mind, primordial wisdom, pristine awareness and so on.</paragraph></subsection></section><section index="8" title="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination" pagetitle="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination" tocentry="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination"><subsection title="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination" pagetitle="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination" tocentry="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent Origination"><paragraph>Nothing simply <italic>is</italic> . Nothing exists all by itself. Everything and everyone <italic>depend</italic> upon other things in order to be what they are. There are two aspects to interdependence: momentary interdependence and historical interdependence:</paragraph><paragraph>· <bold>Momentary interdependence</bold> is the way one thing depends upon other things for its seeming existence <underline>in the instant</underline> . For instance, a "yellow wall" seems to be yellow in its own right—a yellow thing—yet the yellow we see when we look at "the wall" is in fact the <italic>yellow of sunlight</italic> reflected off the wall, not the yellow of the wall at all. The wall absorbs some of the spectrum but "bounces" off the yellow part. Without light shining on the wall, there is no yellow. Furthermore, without an eye to see it, there is no "yellow" either, as yellow is an experience that happens in a human brain. No actual yellow colour travels through space but whatever (if anything) does travel through space triggers the eye which triggers the brain which produces the yellow experience. It is the coming-together of many things—a human eye, the substance of the wall, the sun's rays etc.—that produces the momentary experience of yellow. This is simply an example that is easy to understand, using "modern" scientific intelligence. It demonstrates to anyone that in each instant, each seeming "thing" is in fact the coming-together of many circumstances and not something fixed forever in its own nature. It is not what it at first seems.</paragraph><paragraph>· <bold>Historical interdependence</bold> follows the cause-and-effect process <underline>through time</underline> . The eye that sees yellow was created by the person's parents, along with the rest of the child. It was sustained, protected and developed through food and other conditions until this moment. The wall was built from bricks, because of someone's idea to build it there. The bricks themselves came out of mud due to silt deposited over centuries by a river and so forth. The light shining on the wall comes from nuclear reaction in the Sun. Each circumstance during a moment of interdependence has its own history and causality.</paragraph><paragraph>One could simplify the above and talk of <italic>interdependence in space and in time</italic> . In this section, we are investigating interdependence in relation to suffering. The main process has already been outlined, step by step:</paragraph><paragraph> <bold>ignorance</bold>  <bold>a</bold>  <bold>ego illusion</bold>  <bold>a</bold>  <bold>affliction</bold>  <bold>a</bold>  <bold>karma</bold>  <bold>a</bold>  <bold>suffering</bold> </paragraph><paragraph>The classical way of looking into the historical interdependence of this is through a topic known as <italic>Interdependent Origination</italic> or <italic>The Twelve Links of Interdependent Origination</italic> . These twelve are presented clearly as a chain-reaction. Interdependent origination shows us that once a certain number of factors are gathered together, the consequences will surely be triggered, like putting a match to dry gunpowder. They also show, in the opposite sense, that if any single link in the chain is destroyed, then none of the subsequent links will happen. <underline>With the "Twelve Links of Interdependence", we have the genetic code of samsara</underline> . It is a sort of universal master-plan that can be applied over a series of lifetimes, over two lifetimes or to a single instant of time.</paragraph><image width="481" src="module3_files.image013.png" align=""/></subsection><subsection title="Outer Interdependence: the Twelve Links" pagetitle="Outer Interdependence: the Twelve Links" tocentry="Outer Interdependence: the Twelve Links"><paragraph><essential> <bold>Ignorance</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>creations</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>consciousness</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>name and form</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>perceptual gateways</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>contact</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>feeling</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>craving</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>grasping</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>becoming</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>birth</bold>    <bold>a</bold>  <bold>ageing and death</bold> </essential></paragraph><paragraph>  </paragraph><paragraph>We shall now study Gampopa's presentation of the Twelve Links, supported by images from the outer ring of the Wheel of Life thangka <a href="#_ftn28">[28]</a>: In the explanation below, links in <bold>blue</bold> are afflictions ( <italic>klesha</italic> ), links in <bold>red</bold> are action ( <italic>karma</italic> ) and the <bold>others</bold> are suffering itself.</paragraph><subsubsection title="The Twelve Links of Interdependence" pagetitle="The Twelve Links of Interdependence" tocentry="The Twelve Links of Interdependence"><image width="136" src="module3_files.image014.png" align="left"/>The Twelve Links of Interdependence<image width="11" src="module3_files.image015.png" align=""/>confused ignorance[29]<image width="142" src="module3_files.image016.png" align="left"/><paragraph>2. There is the actual doing of <bold>tainted action</bold> , be it virtuous or non-virtuous, represented by a potter (fabricating a reality by his own actions). This is known as " <bold>creation</bold> due to the condition of ignorance".</paragraph><image width="11" src="module3_files.image017.png" align=""/><image width="115" src="module3_files.image018.png" align="left"/>consciousness<image width="144" src="module3_files.image019.png" align="left"/><image width="136" src="module3_files.image020.png" align="left"/>name and form<paragraph>5. The various sense and mind faculties—of sight, smell etc.—become complete. They are known as the " <bold>six perceptual gateways</bold> due to the condition of name and form", represented by a house with six sections.</paragraph><image width="146" src="module3_files.image021.png" align="left"/><image width="135" src="module3_files.image022.png" align="left"/>contact<paragraph>7. <bold>Feeling</bold> , or sensation, in the sense of a pleasant, unpleasant or indifferent experience, represented by a person with an arrow in the eye. This is known as "feeling due to the condition of contact".</paragraph><image width="139" src="module3_files.image023.png" align="left"/>craving<image width="85" src="module3_files.image024.png" align="left"/><paragraph>9. Mental striving in order either not to lose the experience or to bring it back. This is known as " <bold>grasping</bold> due to the condition of craving", represented here by picking fruit from a tree. Due to this striving one</paragraph><image width="84" src="module3_files.image025.png" align="left"/><paragraph>10. Performs actions—physically, verbally or mentally—which generate rebirth. This is known as " <bold>becoming</bold> , due to the condition of grasping" and is represented by a pregnant woman.</paragraph><image width="133" src="module3_files.image026.png" align="left"/><image width="114" src="module3_files.image027.png" align="left"/>birth<paragraph>12. The development and maturity of the actual existence is ageing and its destruction is death, depicted by a man carrying a shrouded corpse to the cremation ground. These are " <bold>ageing and death</bold> due to the condition of birth".</paragraph><paragraph>The section accompanied by a green line can represent the inheritance from past lives, in which case we are considering timeless ignorance and all the things done in the past that have made the unique consciousness coming into this life.</paragraph><image width="11" src="module3_files.image028.png" align=""/>[30]<paragraph>Let us consider four of the less-obvious links above:</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Link 3: Consciousness</italic> is the consciousness moving from one life to the next. Having left the body of the last life, it is in the <italic>bardo</italic> or in-between state. It carries with it all of its past, including all the karmic programming generated by actions in the previous life.</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Link 4:</italic>  <italic>Name and Form</italic> is another way of saying the five aggregates or, to put it simply, the new life, once the <italic>bardo</italic> is over. <italic>Form</italic> covers the tangible aspects and means the new body whereas <italic>Name</italic> means the intangible things—mind—in the sense of feelings, cognition, mental events and consciousness. In this link the <italic>bardo</italic> consciousness has joined the sperm and ovum of the parents to make a new sentient being. Although technically the new life has started, there are not yet eyes, ears, nose and so forth and so many aspects of consciousness and cognition are only there nominally. That is one of the reasons it is called <italic>Name</italic> .</paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Link 5: Six Perceptual Gateways</italic> develop as the body of the foetus grows, enabling its world to be perceived. As the ear and brain develop, a "gateway" opens to the world of sound and likewise for the other four fields of the senses: sights, odours, flavours, tactile sensations. The sixth perceptual gateway is that of the mind. This has two aspects, the first of which is simply to receive and process inputs from the five senses. It is a little like a switchboard, with attention shifting continuously from one sense to another, first to sound, then to physical sensations, then to odour and so on and so forth. The second aspect of the mental perceptual gateway is for mind, as a subject, to be aware of mind as an object.</paragraph><paragraph>To illustrate this, if just now you think of a childhood memory, then your mind, the thinker, is contemplating its object, another aspect of your mind, its memory. Just as your power to see opens out to the world through the gateway of vision to the world of visible objects, so does your mental power to be aware open out through the mental perceptual gateway to the world of things you can be aware of <a href="#_ftn31">[31]</a>. If we apply this to the newly-conceived child, then while still in the womb, there is already a sense of identity within the child and there are mental reactions to the environment of the womb. With birth comes a whole new set of subject-object situations at play in the baby's mind. With the acquisition of language, names can be given to the various components of the already-established mental landscape. With time, this becomes the inner dialogue about self and other. <a href="#_ftn32">[32]</a></paragraph><paragraph> <italic>Link 10: Becoming</italic> maybe does not sound as important as it is. It covers <italic>all</italic> the actions of the present lifetime, in other terms all the karma created in the present lifetime. These actions contribute, one by one and inescapably, to creating the future person. By performing actions, we are becoming what we will be in the future. Some people sensitive enough to be aware of the process, will feel that all-important shift from being inclined to do something (link 9, intense mental involvement and grasping) to actually giving way to the impulse and performing the action. This critical step is what link 10, becoming, is all about. By creating karma (action), we not only give reality to what we have thus far only imagined but we also have made a future: we are <italic>becoming</italic> what we will be.</paragraph><paragraph>Having clarified these three links, let us return to the overall process of the twelve steps of interdependence. In one discourse, the <italic>Rice Shoot Sutra</italic> , the Buddha uses the example of a rice plant to illustrate interdependence:</paragraph><paragraph>Bhikkhus! Whoever understands this rice shoot understands interdependent origination. Whoever understands interdependent origination understands the nature of phenomena. Whoever understands phenomena understands buddhahood.</paragraph><paragraph>Monks! T hrough the existence of this, this will arise. Through this having arisen, (then) this arises. That is how it is. Through the condition of ignorance, there will be creations <a href="#_ftn33">[33]</a>... etc. (up to) ... there will be birth and through that condition there will be ageing and death, sufferings and lamentations, pain, mental stress and upsets. That is how this great cluster of nothing but misery is produced.</paragraph><paragraph>In the above quotation, one needs to imagine the Buddha holding a rice seed in one hand and a rice shoot in the other. Note, in passing, that the Buddha does not say, "This seed makes a shoot" but more accurately points out that <italic>once there is this</italic> (the seed) <italic>then there will be this</italic> (the shoot).</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="The Twelve Links of Liberation" pagetitle="The Twelve Links of Liberation" tocentry="The Twelve Links of Liberation">The Twelve Links of Liberation<paragraph>By understanding the billiard-ball effect of one thing triggering another in the twelve links described above, one has the key to sabotaging the whole process of suffering. The removal of any one link means that none of the following links can happen. This means:</paragraph><paragraph>· Removing link 11 prevents link 12</paragraph><paragraph>· Removing link 10 prevents link 11 &amp; 12 etc. up to</paragraph><paragraph>· Removing link 1 removes links 2 - 12</paragraph><paragraph>In particular:</paragraph><table class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td> <bold>Action</bold> </td><td> <bold>Prevents this link</bold> </td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Wise action</bold> (link 10, becoming ) in this life will avoid the ten non-virtues and therefore links 11 and 12—unfortunate rebirth and suffering, due to non-virtuous actions—cannot occur. Until someone has completely transcended all samsaric action, there will still be rebirth, link 11, but in fortunate circumstances due to virtuous karma.</td><td>11 &amp; 12</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Self-control</bold> in the sense of not giving way to thoughts and impulses (link 9) will prevent non-virtuous karma</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Mindfulness and meditation</bold> help one be aware of how craving (link 8) for certain experiences of the mind or of the senses leads into intense mental activity (link 9) around those things craved for or detested. One learns to not let the mind wander into and dwell within those danger zones.</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>"Snipping it in the bud"</bold> meditation practices create the skill of immediately recognising when feelings (link 7) give rise to craving and of cutting off, in the instant, the processes described above.</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Bardo</bold> instruction <a href="#_ftn34">[34]</a>helps someone use consciousness skillfully to find a better rebirth. These are special vajrayana instructions, not part of the general twelve-links teachings. They help the transitions from links 2 to 3 and from links 10 to 11 to happen in a more helpful way.</td><td>3 or 11</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Purification practices</bold> help one to modify the content of conditioning carried in the universal basis consciousness (link 3) and this will change the type of existence one will be reborn into.</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td> <bold>Voidness wisdom <a href="#_ftn35"> <bold>[35]</bold> </a></bold> tackles the very root of samsara—ignorance (link 1). It is the best—the most radical—way to tackle suffering. In the Hinayana, this means understanding the voidness of ego. In the Mahayana, it means understanding the voidness of everything. One cannot overestimate the importance of centreing efforts on achieving direct realisation of voidness, as this solves all the problem of samsara in one fell swoop. When samsara, in all its complexity, is compared to a mighty, long-standing tree, then this is the equivalent of severing its trunk.</td><td>2</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>The <italic>Treatise on Interdependence</italic> says:</paragraph><paragraph>Also, to exemplify this: ignorance is like the one who sows a seed, karma is like the field, consciousness like the seed itself, grasping is like moisture, name and form like a shoot and the remaining links are like the branches and leaves (of the plant).</paragraph><paragraph>Were ignorance not to occur, creation and so forth could not occur ... (etc. up to) ... and were birth not to happen then ageing and death could not occur.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="No one's &#34;fault&#34;" pagetitle="No one's &#34;fault&#34;" tocentry="No one's &#34;fault&#34;">No one's "fault"<paragraph>The Buddha, in his great compassion, simply pointed out that this is the way things happen. In the Rice Shoot Sutra, he put his finger on it, "Once there is <italic>this</italic> , then there will be <italic>this</italic> ." Suffering and happiness are not the punishments and gifts of God, or of the gods. In many ways, the sufferings are not even the creation of the person one was in the previous life: who would intentionally create future sufferings for themselves? Simply, one thing inevitably leads to another, in a world confused by ignorance. Fortunately, just now, we have the intelligence to be able to understand the process and to do something about it. In this context, Gampopa says:</paragraph><paragraph>In these processes, ignorance does not plot, thinking, <italic>I will make creations truly manifest</italic> , nor do the creations have a mind which thinks, <italic>We were made to manifest by, and created by, ignorance</italic> ... etc. Likewise birth does not plot, thinking, <italic>I will make ageing and death truly happen</italic> nor do ageing and death consider themselves actually brought into being by birth.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, it is through the existence of ignorance that creations and so forth do become manifest realities and will occur and, likewise, through the existence of birth that ageing and death are made manifest and will happen.</paragraph><paragraph>The twelve links described above, are sometimes known as <italic>outer interdependence</italic> , since they deal with the world that we see, hear and touch. <italic>Inner interdependence</italic> adds another dimension—one which resembles very much our modern physics.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection><subsection title="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements" pagetitle="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements" tocentry="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements"><paragraph>Inner interdependent origination concerns general conditions, on an atomic level, rather than the prime causes in the tangible world, discussed above <a href="#_ftn36">[36]</a>.</paragraph><paragraph>It may seem surprising to use the word "atomic" here but that was precisely what was being discussed in Buddhist and other circles in India two thousand years ago. People speculated, with great intelligence, about what unchangeable components could be present in the tiniest of particles. In Buddhism, these components are known as:</paragraph><paragraph><essential>The Six Elements</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>1. Matter</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>2. Bonding</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>3. Energy</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>4. Movement</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>5. Space</essential></paragraph><paragraph><essential>6. Consciousness</essential></paragraph><paragraph>These were given respectively the symbolic names <italic>earth element, water element, fire element, wind element, space element and consciousness element</italic> .</paragraph><subsubsection title="The Indian System of the Elements" pagetitle="The Indian System of the Elements" tocentry="The Indian System of the Elements">The Indian System of the Elements<paragraph>The Buddha's teachings, 2,500 years ago, contributed to an already vigorous debate concerning the nature of matter, on its molecular level. The five elements, as they appear in Buddhism, are five universal components of all things animate or inanimate. They are each present in all material realities and one must be careful not to be misled by their simple names. The element 'fire' (see below) is really the energy present in a reality. This can be latent, stored-up energy or energy actually in the process of being released. Thus the 'fire' element is present in ice, in cold rock and so forth—anything that has reserves of energy—without any need for flames or heat. Actual fire is, of course, one vivid example of energy being released. Likewise, 'earth', 'water' and 'wind', as we experience them in everyday life, are metaphors of what those elements represent on a more subtle level.</paragraph><image width="13" src="module3_files.image029.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image030.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image031.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image032.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image033.png" align=""/>dimension<paragraph><essential>CONSCIOUSNESS element. The five elements as described above were part of scientific speculation in India thousands of years ago. Buddhism added a sixth element, that of consciousness. It is comprised of the five sense consciousnesses and the tainted mental consciousness. These will be described in a later module.</essential></paragraph><paragraph>Although not having our present-day means of investigation to confirm their theories, the sages of ancient India had our main tool: intelligence. They believed the universe to be—on an atomic level—a vast interdependence of matter, energy, movement and bonding. This ever-changing atomic maelstrom appears—on a gross level—as all the trees, rocks, ocean and living beings we perceive. A human body is a highly-complex manifestation of the five elements, just as the universe in which that body moves is an immensely complex manifestation of the five elements. On the atomic level, they share a similar character and depend upon similar things.</paragraph><paragraph>In Tibetan Medicine and Science, one finds two major Asian systems of the elements:</paragraph><image width="10" src="module3_files.image034.png" align=""/>Indian<image width="10" src="module3_files.image035.png" align=""/>Chinesestatus quo<paragraph>Although not strictly part of our Buddhist studies, below is a resumé of the Chinese system of the elements, as integrated into Tibetan sciences.</paragraph></subsubsection><subsubsection title="The Chinese System of the Elements" pagetitle="The Chinese System of the Elements" tocentry="The Chinese System of the Elements">The Chinese System of the Elements<paragraph>The names are similar to those of the system above, except that metal replaces space and wood is the name for wind.</paragraph><image width="18" src="module3_files.image036.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image037.png" align=""/><image width="13" src="module3_files.image038.png" align=""/><image width="18" src="module3_files.image039.png" align=""/><image width="13" src="module3_files.image040.png" align=""/><paragraph>There is a natural order in these elements and there are natural affinities and conflicts between them. It is obvious that a great release of energy will perturb the dormant state of a latent potential. Thus fire is the 'enemy' of water. That latent state of potential is the very source of what will happen as new realities take shape. Thus water is the 'mother' of wood. Four main types of relationship are described: <bold>mother, child, enemy and friend</bold> , represented in the table below:</paragraph><table width="498" class="MsoNormalTable"><tbody><tr><td>MOTHER</td><td>CHILD</td><td>ENEMY</td><td>FRIEND</td></tr><tr><td>WOOD</td><td>water</td><td>fire</td><td>metal</td><td>earth</td></tr><tr><td>FIRE</td><td>wood</td><td>earth</td><td>water</td><td>metal</td></tr><tr><td>EARTH</td><td>fire</td><td>metal</td><td>wood</td><td>water</td></tr><tr><td>METAL</td><td>earth</td><td>water</td><td>fire</td><td>wood</td></tr><tr><td>WATER</td><td>metal</td><td>wood</td><td>earth</td><td>fire</td></tr></tbody></table><paragraph>Recalling the Indian, Buddhist, system of the elements, let us return now to Gampopa:</paragraph><paragraph>Without the above condition of the six elements, a body cannot come into being. Furthermore, the presence of all six inner elements is universal and hence comprises everything. It is due to them that the body will have its actual manifest existence.</paragraph><paragraph>In these (processes), the six elements do not think, <italic>I will establish the body's firmness</italic> etc. and neither does the body think, <italic>I am generated by these specific conditions</italic> . Nevertheless, it is through these specific conditions that the body—life—occurs in all the ways it does.</paragraph></subsubsection></subsection></section><footnotes><footnote id="1">The view of Existentialists, among others.</footnote><footnote id="2">Wikipedia entry on determinism, for instance.</footnote><footnote id="3">see Module 2, Page 30 to refresh your memory about the four points for Truth 1</footnote><footnote id="4">Same as six realms but with asuras included with gods.</footnote><footnote id="5">From Illuminator Dictionary, sutra source not given.</footnote><footnote id="6">In all senses of this word: OED "Healthy condition, wholesomeness".</footnote><footnote id="7">I use this word for want of a better one. It covers any religion that includes Abraham in its history, i.e. Christianity, Judaism, Islam, Baha'i etc. and hence includes the religions of more than half the world's population.</footnote><footnote id="8">The texts actually say with mother, sister... assuming they are addressing monks. It goes without saying that the misconduct is obviously that of the person instigating the act or of those old enough and wise enough to understand it is wrong yet still willingly participating. Victims of incest are not committing sexual misconduct.</footnote><footnote id="9">Praying to imagined entities that either do not exist or do not have the power to deliver what is prayed for.</footnote><footnote id="10">This, the third of the Four Truths, describes the lasting peace of nirvana once suffering had been definitively eliminated.</footnote><footnote id="11">This, the fourth of the Four Truths, describes the metaphorical "path" of skilful conduct, meditation and wisdom-development which ends suffering and leads to nirvana.</footnote><footnote id="12">Buddha, dharma and sangha. As we discover what these really are, it becomes obvious that they are the three most precious, most meaningful things in the entire universe: the pure within the impure, the truth within delusion. To denigrate them is not wrong because it is insulting the mainstay of the Buddhist faith but because it is shutting and alienating the person's mind to the very things that can help.</footnote><footnote id="13">To the meditator, it feels as though this is what is happening: a oneness with infinite space. However, what is actually happening is that the mind is absorbed in the very subtle concept of infinite space and not actually united with space itself. It is the same for the following formless meditations, which are primarily conceptual but please note that once this practice has reached the absorption stage it is a fine, lasting, background concept not noticed by the meditator, whose mind has no apparent thoughts..</footnote><footnote id="14">You may see this one in modern Buddhist books, referred to by its Tibetan name og min (pronounced o-min).</footnote><footnote id="15">The four main remedies will be discussed in a later module.</footnote><footnote id="16">Universal basis consciousness is the aspect of consciousness capable of storing data which conditions the mind. This will be explained more fully in the module on the Two Truths.</footnote><footnote id="17">For the few students who do not know who Milarepa was, all I can say is, " You must read his story." He was an endearing character, forced by his embittered mother into causing the deaths of twenty-five of his kin. He later managed to purify the very heavy non-virtuous karma he had made and achieved enlightenment in one life.</footnote><footnote id="18">Bear this in mind when reading the last section of his module, on the elements ad inner interdependence.</footnote><footnote id="19">The teachings say that even if one placed the bravest hero in a simulation of nine months in the utterly-dark confines of the womb, how would he emerge? If one adds to that the traumas of death, in the previous life, those of seven weeks of non-stop hallucinations, in the between-life ( bardo) state and that of conception, not to mention the two years of dependency it takes, as a baby, to acquire a beginning of language and reason, it is not surprising that one does not remember what happened in the past life. This having been said, it seems that more than 20% of children between 2 and 5 years of age do have unaccountable memories of another existence, which dissolve as they acquire the conditioning of their home, school and culture.</footnote><footnote id="20">Instant karma is a very rare thing indeed. Most stories concerning it involve powerful acts done to the Buddha.</footnote><footnote id="21">Interesting misnomer, as the religious canons of Judaism, Islam and Christianity only overlap partially and they have no one major "book" in common.</footnote><footnote id="22">This list sounds "very Buddhist" and hence parochial. To understand what is really being referred to here, one needs to look behind the Buddhist lables (karma, Refuges) to the things themselves which are being ignored, i.e. the very mechanisms of existence (inevitable cause and effect), the presence within existence of the guiding light of truth (dharma teachings) etc. Then one can appreciate how such ignorance triggers deluded and harmful acts.</footnote><footnote id="23">The Seven Types of Pride: Mere Pride - to consider oneself superior when thinking of those with lesser qualities or to be proud of being the same as those with similar qualities. Great Pride - to believe oneself to be better than one's equals or equal to one's betters. Arrogant Pride - to consider oneself even superior to one's betters. Self-attributing Pride - to proudly think "that's me" when thinking of one or another of the aggregates and making them into a persona (e.g. a beautiful body). Obvious Pride - belief that one has attained higher qualities than one actually possesses. Consoling Pride - one feels "only slightly less but still pretty good" when considering those far superior. Mistaken Pride - conceited pride in possessing qualities that one does not have at all.</footnote><footnote id="24">For instance the cells of the body are constantly renewing themselves, some day by day, some month by month.</footnote><footnote id="25">This word—perhaps not the best choice but universally used—is used to refer to the various buddhas and enlightened beings that are visualised in vajrayana practice.</footnote><footnote id="26">The Sanskrit sahaja , Tibetan lhan cig tu skyes pa , means "arising at the same time. In most cases, it is best translated by innate . In this case however, ignorance is not innate to truth but arises with it.</footnote><footnote id="27">In Buddhism, the disappearance of duality does not lead to oneness , as it does in some faiths. Oneness is also an illusion, as far as Buddhists are concerned. "Non-dual" is, for us, what is technically known as a non-affirming negation, i.e. it negates the illusion of two but goes no further than that and does not affirm a specific "one". The Sanskrit for non-dual is advita in Buddhism but advaita in Hinduism, where a oneness is implied.</footnote><footnote id="28">A thangka is a Tibetan hanging scroll painting. The Wheel of Life depicts the Six Realms, the Three Poisons and the Twelve Links, all reflected in a mirror held by Yamaraja, the Lord of Death.</footnote><footnote id="29">Tathagatagarbha .</footnote><footnote id="30">This is based upon the Ten Dharmas Sutra .</footnote><footnote id="31">The objects of mental consciousness are technically known as dharmas in Sanskrit.</footnote><footnote id="32">We will study all twelve perceptual gateways, along with the process of consciousness, of which they form part, in a later module.</footnote><footnote id="33">Creations: Skt: samskara Tib: 'du byed . This term is often translated as "mental formations". As neither the Sanskrit nor the Tibetan contains a reference to "mind" and since mentioning mind creates certain problems, I have omitted it. The twelve links of interdependence can also be explained severally. Sometimes this refers to the immediate coming into being of the notion of self, then other etc. At other times it refers to the whole backlog of conditioning that one has at any given moment: one's own creations from the past that one has to live with. For these and other reasons, "creations" seems a best-possible but still inadequate translation. Another possibility would be "conformation" but the word is little used and unwieldy.</footnote><footnote id="34">Training for dying and for facing the post-death experiences</footnote><footnote id="35">"Voidness wisdom" is a pleonasm but it communicates the point. Voidness means wisdom by its very definition (see Module 1).</footnote><footnote id="36">Specific conditions as opposed to prime cause. Whereas the latter contains the very specific "programming" of the future consequences—as does the seed of a flower—the former are general and do not. For the flower, they would be the likes of the heat and moisture that help it to grow. They do not contain the genetics of its character.</footnote></footnotes></chapter></book>