<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book">
   <chapter index="5"
            title="The Fourth Great Truth: the Path of Peace,&#xA;Part Two, The Sangha, Taking Refuge"
            pagetitle="Module 5"
            tocentry="The Fourth Great Truth: the Path of Peace,&#xA;Part Two, The Sangha, Taking Refuge">
      <section index="1" title="" pagetitle="" tocentry="">
         <subsection title="The Fourth Great Truth: the Path of Peace,\Part Two, The Sangha, Taking Refuge"
                     pagetitle="The Fourth Great Truth: the Path of Peace,\Part Two, The Sangha, Taking Refuge"
                     tocentry="The Fourth Great Truth: the Path of Peace,\Part Two, The Sangha, Taking Refuge"/>
      </section>
      <section index="2" title="Purification and Accumulation"
               pagetitle="Purification and Accumulation"
               tocentry="Purification and Accumulation">
         <subsection title="Purification and Accumulation" pagetitle="Purification and Accumulation"
                     tocentry="Purification and Accumulation">
            <image width="245"/>
            <paragraph>At
the end of Module Four, we explored the topic of mindfulness. You may remember
that the four aspects of mindfulness (body, feelings, mind and dharma) are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·The
first four of the _thirty-seven factors of enlightenment_.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·Collectively,
the lower stage of the _Phase of Accumulation_.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
diagram of the previous module is repeated here. It is very useful (memorise?) </paragraph>
            <table class="MsoNormalTable">
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <td>*The Mahayana Journey of
  the Five Phases of the Path*</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>(eh)<img width="318" src="module5_files/image002.png"/>
                        <img width="303" src="module5_files/image003.png"/>(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)*Phase
  5: No Training*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)*<img id="_x0000_i1025" width="108" src="module5_files/image004.jpg"/>*(eeh)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)*Phase
  4: Cultivation*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 10(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 9(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 8(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 7(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 6(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 5(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 4(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 3(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 2 (eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)*Phase
  3:  Insight*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)Bodhisattva
  Level 1(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)*Phase
  2: Integration*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)"Highest
  Wordly"(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)"Forbearance"(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)"Summit"(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td/>
                     <td>(eh)"Warming"(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>(eh)*<img id="_x0000_i1026" width="85" src="module5_files/image005.png"/>*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)*Phase
  1: Accumulation*(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)Greater(eeh)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>(eh)Middling(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)*4
  eliminations*(eeh)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>(eh)Lesser(eeh)</td>
                     <td>(eh)*4
  mindfulnesses*(eeh)</td>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table>
            <paragraph>(eh)The next four _factors_, which
form the middle stage of the _phase of accumulation_, are the _Four
Eliminations_, described as:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*1.     **Eliminating what is harmful<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> in one's life.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*2.     **Making sure not to introduce
any new harmful thing.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*3.     **Increasing what is helpful<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> in one's life.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*4.     **Introducing new helpful
skills.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In Mahayana, these processes are usually spoken of aspurification and accumulation_*, sometimes expressed as _elimination
and adoption_. Whatever
we call them, they represent a huge part of the dharma work that needs to be
done--work that probably most of us are engaged in right now. Progressing a
little way through this stage is, for most Buddhists, what their whole life's
dharma practice is about. As Tai Situpa says:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Even if you advance by one per cent
each life, after a hundred lives you'll be Buddha. That's pretty good!</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One
could add that each life is that "one per cent of the overall
journey" better in quality than the previous! </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Purification
and accumulation" is the great turn-around, during which past karma is
progressively purified and offloaded, the mind's bad habits become understood
and transformed, new qualities of meditation, conduct and altruism are
discovered and doors of wisdom start to open as a consequence of changing into
a purer, more-awakened person. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>These
first two stages of the Phase of Accumulation are universal. Although the
practical details vary according to each person's karma--from very simple to
very complex--these stages are pretty much the same for everyone: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>first,
     some self-knowledge and moral awakening, through mindfulness, then </li>
               <li>decades
     of dharma work to improve the mind and to change one's life. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>After
that, the meditation journey of the upper stage of the Phase of Accumulation
and, following that, the discovery of voidness in the Phase of Integration,
will be much more singular. For these and other reasons, we will not continue,
in this stage of the course, through all the remaining twenty-nine _factors_.
However, as purification and accumulation are so common and so important, we
will turn our attention to them a little here and in more detail in our study
of the bodhisattva path.  </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The inter-activity of purification and accumulation"
                     pagetitle="The inter-activity of purification and accumulation"
                     tocentry="The inter-activity of purification and accumulation">
            <paragraph>These
two topics are intimately related. What need to be "purified" are the
harmful, painful things we carry within us. Some of these are recognisable and
others are hidden, like time-bombs.  Four main methods of purification are
resorted to<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>,
one of them being the antidote "power of practising virtue". Virtue--in
terms of concrete deeds of body and speech, along with refinement of the mind--is
a vital part of "accumulation". The other vital part is wisdom and developing
voidness-wisdom is the most powerful aspect of another of the four methods of
purification: the "power of support". </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Furthermore,
the elimination of the damaging things automatically creates a space for natural
goodness. It paves the way for natural goodness. Two examples:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>As
     stinginess and fear of personal loss dissolve away, the beauty, simplicity
     and relaxation of generosity can be discovered.</li>
               <li>As
     habits of wounding speech become seen for the harm they do, and as they
     are felt increasingly to be acts unworthy of our minds, then the motivation
     to do something about them grows. Skilful methods are learned and, with
     time and effort, harmful speech habits are eradicated. This process opens
     up, very naturally, a space in which to discover, and then nurture,
     pleasant, meaningful and aware speech.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>Moreover,
our lamas tell us that we live in the sixth of the ten 500-year periods of the
Buddha's teaching. It is known as "the time for virtue" and described
as a period in history when the general moral tendency takes a severe downward
turn. Self-centredness, sensual desire and corruption prevail. Therefore, a lot
of counter-current energy is needed even to recognise clearly where life's flow
is taking us. It takes effort to lead a pure and virtuous life. It is said that
in this age, simply to resist the dark and the negative ... is in itself a
strong virtue, equivalent to the great deeds of virtue accomplished in ages
when dharma practice is easier.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
dawn breaks, the darkness recedes. As rain falls, dryness disappears. With
purification, accumulation automatically increases. Accumulation automatically
purifies.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Purification" pagetitle="Purification" tocentry="Purification">
            <paragraph>(eh)What is there to be purified? The list
is exactly the same as the one we found in the causes of suffering, i.e. karma,
defilements, dualistic confusion and ego belief rooted in ignorance. For all of
those, the work of purification falls into two categories:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*Working with the past*, i.e. reducing
     whatever of these things are present in one's stream of existence,
     eventually removing them forever.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Becoming vigilant for the future*, i.e. making sure that
     no new harms develop.(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <subsubsection title="1.\Working with the past" pagetitle="1.\Working with the past"
                           tocentry="1.\Working with the past">
               <paragraph>There
are two ways in which harmful karma from the past can be purified: </paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>By
     using the skilful methods of the _four powers_ to remove it from
     one's stream of being _before_ it "ripens". This is like
     removing the seeds of poisonous plants from the soil before they
     germinate.</li>
                  <li>By
     living through its consequences.</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>Thus,
should it be the case that sickness occurs, life circumstances become
difficult, human relationships break down or the like, such events can be seen
as part of purification of karma. When such things happen, it is important to
learn how to shatter the "circle of samsara" and to practise
acceptance.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Samsara
is a cyclical or repetitive process. Let us take some examples. Stealing causes
poverty in future lives, poverty leads people to steal ... and so it goes on
and on. Anger and aggression lead to being born in conflict-ridden
circumstances in a future life, these make one angry ... and so it goes on and
on. Sexual misconduct leads to difficult couple relationships and these often
provoke further sexual misconduct... These repetitive processes could go on
interminably. It is vitally important to learn how to be skilful when facing
the maturation of harmful karma, so as not to fall into the trap of old habits,
thereby creating more pain for the future. One helpful factor in developing
such skill is _acceptance_. The key to this was expressed very clearly by
Santideva:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Whatever can be changed for the better:
change it!</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Whatever cannot be changed: accept it!</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Thus
Buddhist acceptance does not mean total passivity. It does not mean
"becoming a carpet for other people to walk over". It means finding
intelligent solutions that are positive and helpful all round and being careful
not to fall into the trap of samsara. When nothing can be done to change the
external circumstances of life, then there is no point compounding the pain by
resent, self-pity, frustration and so forth. Those things just make bad worse.
These topics will be developed more fully in the module on the _paramita_
of *forbearance*.   </paragraph>
               <paragraph>These
are habitual tendencies to aggression, desire, confusion, pride, jealousy and
the twenty-odd subsidiary defilements. The main tool that we have for becoming
aware of them, understanding them, reducing them and eventually taking them out
by the roots is meditation, both in formal sessions of meditation and as the
application of mindfulness in daily situations. This will be discussed further
in the module on the _paramita_ of *meditation*. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>These
are reduced and removed principally by applying the wisdom teachings while
meditating. As skill in doing this develops, it carries through into the _inter-meditation_
phase of ordinary life. This will be discussed more fully in the modules on the
_paramitas_ of *meditation* and *deep wisdom *(_prajnaparamita_).</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="2.\Working for the future" pagetitle="2.\Working for the future"
                           tocentry="2.\Working for the future">
               <paragraph>This
is accomplished through a combination of mindfulness, awareness and care. It
usually starts on the meditation cushion, with a growing awareness of our
mind's tricks and turns, habits and foibles, strengths and weaknesses, as
thoughts are seen with ever-growing clarity. Then the self-knowledge acquired
in meditation carries through into daily life and the "thin end of the
wedge" of old harmful habits or emerging new ones can be spotted before
becoming dangerous.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Accumulation" pagetitle="Accumulation" tocentry="Accumulation">
            <paragraph>This
has two aspects, preferably to be cultivated in parallel and in synergy but, on
a practical level, developed according to each individual's capacities and the
unfolding of their karma. The two aspects are:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>*Accumulation
     of virtue ("merit").*</li>
               <li>*Accumulation
     of wisdom.*</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>If
we consider these in universal Buddhist terms, the first is achieved by
practising the "*higher training of right conduct*" and the "*higher
training of meditation*". The second is achieved by the "* higher
training of wisdom*". </paragraph>
            <paragraph>If
we consider them in Mahayana terms, the first is achieved through the practice
of the two _paramitas_ (perfections) of generosity and right conduct. The
second is achieved through the _paramita_ of wisdom. The remaining three
paramitas--forbearance, diligence and meditation--are supports for both
accumulations.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
details of the above are vast. The bodhisattva scriptures describe the skills
to be developed as eighty main ones<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a>,
several hundreds of other ones<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a>
and so forth. They were described fully in the great treatises of Maitreya
(through Asanga) and developed in detail in the various commentaries of their
tradition.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="3" title="The Sangha" pagetitle="The Sangha" tocentry="The Sangha">
         <subsection title="The Sangha" pagetitle="The Sangha" tocentry="The Sangha">
            <image width="443"/>
            <paragraph>From the Lotus Sutra:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_[Ananda]: _Thus have I heard:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At one time when the Buddha was staying at _Rajagriha,
_the City of Royal Palaces, he assembled on Mount _Grdhrakuta _a great
multitude of leading bhikshus, in all twelve thousand. All were arhats,
faultless - their outflows exhausted, never again subject to earthly _klesas;
_their minds free, they had attained what was to their advantage, being emancipated
from all bonds of existence. Also assembled were eighty thousand
Bodhisattva-mahasattvas, none of them ever regressing on the path to Supreme
Perfect Enlightenment. All had mastered the _dharanis, _and being
eloquent, delighted in teaching and turning the irreversible wheel of the
Dharma...</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The significance of the term &#34;sangha&#34;"
                     pagetitle="The significance of the term &#34;sangha&#34;"
                     tocentry="The significance of the term &#34;sangha&#34;">
            <paragraph>Just as _Buddha_ simply means _awakened one_ and _dharma_
means _things_, so does _sangha_ simply mean "the
community". However, although this term could theoretically include all Buddhists,
its meaning has been precisely used for over two thousand years to refer to something
quite specific:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>Either a certain type of monastic gathering, in this world,
     or </li>
               <li>Deeply-realised beings (_arya_), in the vast expanse of
     mind. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>Since the sangha is one of the Three Jewels, i.e. the Refuges (see
below), the term has to refer to something worthy of being a refuge. Hence the loose usage that has developed
recently in the West, with people referring to the members of their local
Buddhist group as _our sangha_, is correct only etymologically but not traditionally,
unless of course the local members are all so liberated that they rank
alongside the Buddha and the dharma as refuges (I have yet to find such a
centre!). Our contemporary masters, such as the Tai Situpa, have made it clear
that it is better to refer to our local communities as precisely that--_my
local Buddhist community, the members of our centre_--and to keep the term _sangha_
in its traditional use.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>    What then
is the traditional definition? First, it refers to a gathering of monastics. In
this case, the qualification for the title _sangha_ varies, according to
the circumstances, depending upon whether a sangha needs to be constituted to
give a refuge ceremony, to give lay vows, to give novice vows or full ordination
but in general we can follow Jé Gampopa's definition of _any gathering of
more than four fully-ordained monastics who have properly maintained their vows_.
For the ceremonies, there also often needs to be an abbot<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a> who has maintained full ordination
purely for at least ten years.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>    The
celestial (for want of a better term) or _realised_ sangha consists of
those who have attained the four degrees of realisation (stream entrant,
non-returner, once-returner and arhat, particularly the latter) in the Hinayana
and the bodhisattvas who have transcended rebirth and abide in the ten levels,
for the Mahayana.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The sangha are
known as "our true friends on the path" and this explains the above.
In the case of the worldly sangha, there is a large enough gathering of
experienced monastics to transcend individuality and to represent the sangha as
a whole. In the case of the realised sangha, it is their clear, stable and
non-regressing insight that qualifies them to teach and be unbiased
"friends" for beings. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The Early Sangha: Buddha's Time"
                     pagetitle="The Early Sangha: Buddha's Time"
                     tocentry="The Early Sangha: Buddha's Time">
            <image width="234"/>
            <paragraph>In Module One,
we encountered the very first sangha in the form of the five ascetics, led by
Kondanna, who became the Buddha's first ordained<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a>
disciples in the forests around Sarnath. There were many amazingly-accomplished
disciples around the Buddha during his lifetime--some with spectacular stories,
such as Angulimala<a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a>--and
there were hundreds who became arhats. During the forty-five years of his
teaching and of the development of the Buddhist community around his presence,
hundreds of thousands of people became sangha members or supporters and the
sangha had the time to become strong and stable. It had the time for its
natural leaders to emerge. Their realisation was confirmed beyond any doubt by
the Buddha himself. We are so fortunate to have a founding figure who taught
for so long and who had plenty of time to form an enlightened community around
him that was sure of his message and able to perpetuate it through time.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Here we will
look briefly at some of the most famous names from the commonly-accepted sangha
of the Buddha time (and after his passing) as well as at the bodhisattva sangha
present during his life and the later appearance of mahasiddhas.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The\Commonly-Accepted Great Disciples"
                           pagetitle="The\Commonly-Accepted Great Disciples"
                           tocentry="The\Commonly-Accepted Great Disciples">
               <paragraph>In the Jataka
tales, which recount the former lives of the Buddha as a bodhisattva, Ananda
was often the bodhisattva's brother. Born in the Buddha's final existence as
his cousin<a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a>, he became the disciple who spent the most time
with the Buddha, serving him most devotedly. Thanks to this, he could act as
arbiter after the Buddha's passing, deciding which accounts of the sutras given
by the arhats were the most correct. He had total recall. Nyanaponika
Thera says:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Ananda had this
ability to a phenomenal degree. He could immediately remember everything, even
if he had heard it only once. He could repeat discourses of the Buddha
flawlessly up to 60,000 words, without leaving out a single syllable. He was
able to recite 15,000 four-line stanzas of the Buddha.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>It is hard to
find the correct term to describe Ananda's role; perhaps "right hand
man" would be our choice these days. Nyanaponika Thera says the following:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The term "attendant" is actually not
comprehensive enough. There is hardly an English word, which can do full justice
to his position. If we were to choose designations such as
"secretary" or "adjunct," then we would not express the
most intimate aspects of his attendance, extending to many little items of
personal assistance given to the Master. If we called him a
"servant," then we would omit the organizational and directing
aspects, which manifested on many occasions. And if we looked for examples in
the world's literature of a confidante of a great man, who accompanied him
constantly, we would not find his likeness.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>This loving attention for 25 years consisted of the
following services: Ananda brought water for washing to the Buddha and
tooth-wood, he arranged his seat, washed his feet, massaged his back, fanned
him for coolness, swept his cell, and mended his robes. He slept nearby at
night to be always on hand. He accompanied him on his rounds through the
monastery (Mv VIII.16)<a href="#_ftn10">[10]</a>
and after meetings he checked to see whether any monk had left anything behind.
He carried the Buddha's messages (Cv V.20) and called the monks together, even
sometimes at midnight (J 148). When the Buddha was sick, he obtained medicine
for him. Once when monks neglected a very sick fellow monk, the Buddha and
Ananda washed him and together carried him to a resting-place (Mv VIII.26). In
this way Ananda performed the many daily tasks and cared for the physical
well-being of his enlightened cousin like a good mother or a caring wife.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>But above all, he also had the duties of a good general
secretary, namely the smooth communication between the thousands of monks and
the Master. Together with Sariputta and Moggallana he tried to sort out, and
attend to, the manifold problems of human relationships turning up in a
community.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Ananda was a caring, motherly figure for the whole
sangha. He also made it possible for women to become nuns, something quite
novel for the time. He was
naturally humble and totally focused on the Buddha. This even caused one monk,
Udayi, to say that he should spend less time devotedly serving the Buddha and
more time working on his own liberation. The Buddha rebuked Udayi for this and prophesied
Ananda's liberation:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>"Not so,
Udayi, not so, Udayi! Should Ananda die without being fully liberated; he would
be king of the gods seven times because of the purity of his heart, or be king
of the Indian subcontinent seven times. But Udayi, Ananda will experience final
liberation in this very life."</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Ananda was a brilliant and very popular teacher, leaving his
disciples always joyous and wishing to hear more. Many times in the sutras, we find him as the main
interlocutor of the Buddha and the one to whom the Buddha addresses key
remarks. The Buddha praised him and his skill with the sangha on many occasions
(sometimes also reminding him of the thin veils remaining to be removed within
him!) and in one Jataka tells how he was previously his servant, accumulating
great merit. He again predicted his liberation.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>After the
Awakened One had foretold a second time that Ananda would soon attain
arahantship, he turned to the monks and once more proclaimed the praise of
Ananda: all the Buddhas of the past had had such excellent attendants and all
Buddhas of the future would have them too. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>In fact, due
to his relentless service, Ananda did not achieve the arhat state during the
Buddha's life. This lack of attainment almost prevented him from joining the
council of five hundred arhats<a href="#_ftn11">[11]</a>
that established the Buddha's teaching, after the Buddha's passing.
Fortunately, Ananda attained arhat state on the eve of that meeting.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>That Council
actually put Ananda on trial first, over three relatively minor matters and one
more important, namely saying that on three occasions the Buddha had given him
(albeit subtly) indications of his (the Buddha's) imminent passing and that
Ananda could, on those occasions , have successfully petitioned the Buddha to
remain on Earth for an aeon. By the time Ananda realised the Buddha's passing
was imminent, it was too late to make such a petition. The sangha accused
Ananda of lack of awareness and vigilance in this matter. Ananda's defense against
this and the other three accusations was at all times impeccable and reasonable
and he was acquitted, becoming a great leader of the sangha, second only to
Maha Kasyapa.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Ananda is said
to have lived to the remarkably old age (especially for the times) of one
hundred and twenty. At his death, in order not to trouble his disciples with a
cremation, legend has it that he concentrated on the fire element and
spontaneously combusted. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*In the
Mahayana*, Ananda is
credited sometimes with entrusting the Perfection of Wisdom (prajnaparamita)
teachings, on the Buddha's behalf, to the serpent-spirits (naga) for
safe-keeping until the time would be right for their recovery (some seven
centuries later).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>For a fuller
version of Ananda's hagiography, by Hellmuth Hecker<a href="#_ftn12">[12]</a> see <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/Ananda.html">www.khenpo.eu/Ananda.html</a>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img width="220" align="left" src="module5_files/image008.png"/>Shariputra, the "Son of Shari" (first called Upatissa) and
Maudgalyana, the "Son of Maudgal" (first called Kolita) are the two
disciples often depicted standing to either side of the Buddha. The former was
the arhat disciple greatest in wisdom and the latter the greatest in miraculous
powers. It is said that
they had profound dharma connections with each other from the past. In the
Jataka Tales, we find them thirty-one times born in close relationship with
each other and taking important parts in stories with the future Buddha in
thirty of those tales. In ancient India at the time of Sakyamuni, they were
conceived on the same day and were born on the same day. They also died within a
fortnight of each other, in the year of the Buddha's passing but before the
Buddha himself left the world. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>    As
children, they each became highly-gifted Brahmin scholars, with impressive
entourages, and they were great friends. Developing deep renunciation, they
first went to an eminent Brahmin guru for instruction. They soon surpassed
their Brahmin teachers and left their huge followings to seek "the deathless
state", wandering far and wide. Unsuccessful, they eventually returned to
their native Rajgir and decided to meditate apart: the first one to find the
deathless state would then inform the other. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>    Sariputra
met Assaji (one of the Buddha's first five monks) who was now an arhat. Just
hearing several words from him, Sariputra knew he had found his way to the
deathless state. In fact he heard just four lines but they were sufficient for
him to become, there and then, a stream-entrant<a href="#_ftn14">[14]</a>. He asked Assaji to stop
there, enquired where the Buddha could be found and explained that he had to
find his friend so that they could both go.  He soon found his friend, who
immediately recognised a difference in his presence and demeanour.  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>They both went
to the Buddha, who had been expecting them and who announced to those around
him the imminent arrival of two of his most important disciples, connected with
him and with dharma for countless lifetimes. He
gave them simple ordination and their new names, Sariputra and Maha
Maudgalyana. Within seven days, Sariputra attained full fruition of the path
and Maha Maudgalyana attained the same within half a month. The Buddha
established them as the two Elders of his community. This upset some of
the disciples, who expected such titles to go to the longest-ordained, and the
Buddha explained that this was destined to happen since at the time of a former
Buddha they had made an intense prayer to serve a future Buddha and to become
his main disciples.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Sariputra*'s wisdom was remarkable and many sutras were given both
to him and through him. His own teachings in the oldest parts of the Canon are
impressive and he is particularly known for having received the full transmission
of the abhidharma techniques,
during the three months in which the Buddha taught them intensively to his
mother in a deva realm, returning to Earth each evening and teaching Sariputra
the same. Sariputra's five hundred main disciples became guardians of these
methods. He had also achieved total selflessness, as justified by various
stories of people trying to upset him or falsely accusing him--all in vain, as
he was beyond pride, anger or resent. The Buddha said of him: </paragraph>
               <paragraph>"Bhikkhus,
it is impossible for Sariputta and his like to cherish anger or hatred.
Sariputta's mind is like the great earth, firm like a gate post, like a pool of
still water."</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Sariputra and Maha Maudgalyana were the
perfect example of friendship, kindness and sincerity within the sangha. The
Buddha often set their friendship as an example for the other monks to emulate.
Sariputra was a kind Elder, never severe, always just, and famous for bringing
out the best in people. He set an example--a model--to be followed by future
generations of sangha members bearing responsibility. For over forty years he
served the Buddha and the sangha like none other and it would be hard, nigh
impossible, to ever evaluate his immense service to dharma.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°°</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*In the Mahayana scriptures*, Sariputra is also the main
interlocutor of the Buddha when the Buddha gives the Perfection of Wisdom
(prajnaparamita) teachings and thus we can consider the second half of his life
as that of a bodhisattva playing the perfect Shravaka. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>For a fuller description of Sariputra's
biography, by Nyanaponika Thera, go to <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/sariputra.html">www.khenpo.eu/sariputra.html</a>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Maha Maugalyana* (see
above). In the magnificent story of his friendship with Sariputra, lasting over
hundreds of lifetimes and originating in other time-space dimensions, we come
to understand that each had developed his own specific qualities. Sariputra was
often amazed at Maha Maudgalyana's clairvoyant<a href="#_ftn15">[15]</a> and other miraculous powers and the
latter was amazed by Sariputra's wisdom and prowess in meditation (he had totally mastered the
Form and Formless Dhyana), as the following story recounts:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Once when the Venerable Sariputta was living with the
Elder Maha Moggallana at Kapotakandara, he was sitting meditating in the open
with his hair freshly shaved when he was given a malicious blow on the head by
a mischievous spirit. The blow was a very severe one, but at the time it was
given "the Elder was absorbed in meditative attainment; consequently he
suffered no harm." The source of this story is the Udana (IV.4) which
continues the account as follows:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The Venerable
Maha Moggallana saw the incident and approached the Venerable Sariputta to ask
how he fared. He asked him: "Brother, are you comfortable? Are you doing
well? Does nothing trouble you?" </paragraph>
               <paragraph>"I am comfortable, brother Moggallana," said
the Venerable Sariputta. "I am doing well, brother Moggallana. Only my
head troubles me a little."</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Whereupon the Venerable Maha Moggallana said: "O
wonderful is it, brother Sariputta! O marvelous is it, brother Sariputta! How
great is the psychic power, and how great is the might of the Venerable
Sariputta! For just now, brother Sariputta, a certain demon gave you a blow on
the head. And a mighty blow it was! With such a blow one might fell an elephant
seven or seven and a half cubits high, or one might split a mountain peak. But
the Venerable Sariputta says only this, 'I am comfortable, brother Moggallana.
I am doing well, brother Moggallana. Only my head troubles me a little.'"</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Then the Venerable Sariputta replied: "O
wonderful is it, brother Moggallana! O marvelous is it, brother Moggallana! How
great is the psychic power and how great is the might of the Venerable
Moggallana, that he should see any demon at all! As for me, I have not seen so
much as a mud-sprite!"</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Maudgalyana had also the qualities of
kindness, equanimity and justice that his brother Elder, Sariputra, possessed
as well as great teaching ability. He often shared a monastic cell with
Sariputra and important teachings, later to become doctrine, were given by them
in conversation with the bhikkhus who came to them for instruction. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Maudgalyana could enter into
conversation with the Buddha, even when the latter was many kilometres away,
through the power known as "divine ear". He could also perform miracles:
once the Buddha asked him to perform one to inspire the sangha to practice. He
shook the vihara (dharma dwelling) by placing his big toe against the wall and
causing an earth tremor. The Buddha told the community that Maudgalyana's
powers came from his mastery of the dhyana meditations. He could also see
other's minds clearly, as the following story tells:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Once on an
Uposatha<a href="#_ftn16">[16]</a>
day, the Buddha sat silently throughout the whole night in front of the
assembly of monks. When the morning dawned, he only said: "This assembly
is impure." Thereupon Moggallana surveyed with his mind the entire
assembly from monk to monk and saw that one monk was entirely corrupted. He
went towards him and asked him to leave. When that monk did not move though
asked thrice, Moggallana took him by the arm, led him out of the hall and
bolted the door. Then he begged the Exalted One to recite the Rules of Monastic
Discipline (Patimokkha), as the assembly was now pure again.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Maudgalyana's
great clairvoyant powers led him to tell many stories of beings in other
dimensions, describing their joys and sufferings and thereby confirming the
Buddha's teachings on karma and reincarnation, since many of the beings he met
in other realms could recall their former lives and the specific deeds that had
caused them to be reborn as they were. This clairvoyant power in fact led to his death, as more
and more people left their local gurus to join the sangha:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Particularly the very lowest type of Jains in Magadha
were so enraged about that loss of public esteem and support that they wanted
to get rid of Moggallana. Without investigating the causes in themselves, they
projected blame externally and concentrated their envy and hate on
Maha-Moggallana. Hesitating to commit a murder themselves, some evil-minded
Jains hired such a gang and ordered them to kill Moggallana.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>At that time, Maha-Moggallana lived alone in a forest
hut at Kalasila. After his encounter with Mara he knew that the end of his days
was near. Having enjoyed the bliss of liberation, he now felt the body to be
just an obstruction and burden. Hence he had no desire to make use of his
faculties and keep the body alive for the rest of the aeon. Yet, when he saw
the brigands approaching, he just absented himself by using his supernormal
powers. The gangsters arrived at an empty hut, and though they searched
everywhere, could not find him. They left disappointed, but returned on the
following day. On six consecutive days Moggallana escaped from them in the same
way. His motivation was not the protection of his own body, but saving the
brigands from the fearsome karmic consequences of such a murderous deed,
necessarily leading to rebirth in the hells. He wanted to spare them such a
fate by giving them time to reconsider and abstain from their crime. But their
greed for the promised money was so great that they persisted and returned even
on the seventh day. Then their persistence was "rewarded," for on
that seventh day Moggallana suddenly lost the magic control over his body. A
heinous deed committed in lives long past (by causing the death of his own
parents) had not yet been expiated, and the ripening of that old Kamma
confronted him now, just as others are suddenly confronted by a grave illness.
Moggallana realized that he was now unable to escape. The brigands entered,
knocked him down, smashed all his limbs and left him lying in his blood. Being
keen on quickly getting their reward and also somewhat ill as ease about their
dastardly deed, the brigands left at once, without a further look.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>But Moggallana's great physical and mental strength
was such that his vital energies had not yet succumbed. He regained
consciousness and was able to drag himself to the Buddha. There, in the
Master's presence, at the holiest place of the world, at the source of the
deepest peace, Moggallana breathed his last (Jat. 522E). </paragraph>
               <paragraph>For a fuller account of Maha
Maudgalyana's life, translated by Helmuth Hecker, visit <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/maudgal.html">www.khenpo.eu/maudgal.html</a>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Maha Kasyapa*<a href="#_ftn17">[17]</a> is famed as a disciple of the Buddha
but best known for leading the sangha after the Buddha's entry into
parinirvana. Before his passing, the Buddha made it clear that there should be
no human successor stepping into his role, acting as a refuge for the sangha.
Instead, his teachings--the dharma--were to be, from then onwards, the guiding
light of the community and the community should follow its Elder(s). </paragraph>
               <paragraph>"That which I have proclaimed and
made known, Ananda, as the Teaching and the Discipline (Dhamma-Vinaya), that
shall be your Master when I am gone" (D.16).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)As both Sariputra and
Maudgalyana had passed away some six months before the Buddha, the sangha
turned to its strongest figures, Maha Kasyapa and Ananda, for guidance. At that
point, Ananda had not yet attained the state of arhat and it was Kasyapa's task
to unite the assembly of five hundred arhats to establish the doctrine for
future generations.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Kasyapa had a long-standing bond with
the Buddha. He features in nineteen of the Jataka stories, six times being the
future Buddha's father. We have no certainty of his age, either upon meeting
the Buddha or when he died. Legend tells us that he was born a Brahmin son of a
minor monarch of Magadha. He had an innate tendency to reclusion and meditation
and did not want to marry. When pushed towards marriage by his parents, he made
a clothed statue in the likeness of the only woman he could marry and set them
the task of finding someone just like that. They did, eventually. She was
Bhadra Kapilani (see below), who had been linked with him for many previous
lives. She too was innately religious and did not want to marry but, due to
subterfuges by both sets of parents, they were eventually wed but lived in
celibacy, placing a garland of flowers between them in bed and resisting any
corporeal temptation, delighted to do so. Eventually, they both left the tiny
kingdom, with shaven heads and yellow robes, as was the custom for wandering
ascetics. After a while, to avoid gossip, their ways separated and they each
found the Buddha. The earth shook slightly when they parted and, on feeling the
tremor, the Buddha actually went to meet Kasyapa.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Within seven days of meeting the
Buddha, Kasyapa became an arhat. He was the only disciple ever to exchange
robes with the Buddha and it was he who was signalled by the Buddha as equal in
teaching authority. Some say that the Buddha did this in the knowledge that
Sariputra and Maudgalyana would pass away before him. Kasyapa's strength was in
his practice rather than in his teaching skill. He
was always reluctant to teach, even when asked to do so by the Buddha, and had
few personal students. He preferred retreat and meditation, setting a fine
example in the latter. The Buddha's trust in him was total:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The highest
praise given him by the Buddha, may be found in a sutta where it is said that
Maha Kassapa could attain at will, just like the Buddha himself, the four
fine-material and the four immaterial meditative absorptions, the cessation of
perception and feeling, and could also attain the six supernormal knowledges _(abhinna),_
which include the supernormal powers and culminate in the attainment of Nibbana
(S.16:9). Here his powerful meditative achievements, equalling those of the
Buddha, appear as a characteristic trait of Maha Kassapa's mind. It was because
of that deep meditative calm that he could adapt himself, unperturbed, to all
external situations and live as one of few wants, materially and socially.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>He was famed for his simplicity and
austerity but it is said that he was not a hard, cold person but simply someone
with no needs. He wore rags and ate whatever he was given in the alms round,
even though he was so senior. Yet this brought him even more honour and it is
said that the gods would not allow the Buddha's funeral pyre to ignite until
Kasyapa's arrival. Once he had prostrated at the Buddha's feet, it combusted
spontaneously. Kasyapa inherited the Buddha's alms-bowl.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>His wisdom was profound and he was
quick to realise, after the Buddha's passing, that the dharma needed to be purely
and most properly established. Many arhats remembered huge portions of the
Buddha's teachings and Ananda, who of all of them had accompanied the Buddha
the most, had total recall. Kasyapa set a date for the First Council, knowing
that setting the deadline would be all it took for Ananda's practice to move
forward that extra inch to arhatship. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)When he knew the time had
come for him to pass away, he handed the Buddha's alms-bowl to Ananda, thereby
effectively making him head of the order and Second Patriarch.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>For a fuller biography of Maha Kasyapa
visit <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/kasyapa.html">www.khenpo.eu/kasyapa.html</a>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Maha
Katyayana*<a href="#_ftn18">[18]</a>  was
similar in teaching prowess to Sariputra but different. He did not have the
latter's  skill of metaphor and story-telling but was particularly good at
developing short sayings of the Buddha with a clear, analytical mind, turning
them into instructive discourses for those who had not managed to gather the
full impact in the first place.
His own teachings were acknowledged, sometimes even given their names, by the
Buddha and they form part of the Canon. He too appears in the Jataka stories
and he too attained the state of arhat very quickly indeed: in fact, on the
very same day that he met the Buddha and received teachings. He was naturally
clairvoyant, as the following famous story, often told by Tibetans, shows: </paragraph>
               <paragraph>One
day he went out begging for food. He saw a
lady breast-feeding a baby with her milk, while eating a fish. Next to her was a very skinny dog anxiously looking at
her eating her fish. Seeing this,
Katyayana started laughing. The lady was surprised and asked, "Why are you
laughing?" Katyayana replied "The skinny dog was your late present-life mother
and the fish you are eating was your
present-life father. The baby you
are holding was the enemy whom you killed."</paragraph>
               <paragraph>For a fuller version of Katyayana's (Kaccana's
in Pali) life and his literary influence, visit <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/katyayana.html">www.khenpo.eu/katyayana.html</a>
               </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Female Members of the Early Sangha"
                           pagetitle="Female Members of the Early Sangha"
                           tocentry="Female Members of the Early Sangha">
               <paragraph>Most people know that, and understand
why, most Buddhist history, as most history in general, is male-predominated.
Even so, Buddhism has a very good record for allowing women to become
monastics, recluses and dharma teachers and this since the time of Buddha
himself. Most reasons for the male dominance are to do not so much with
religion but with social mores of the epochs and countries involved. A
distinction needs to be made between the "glass ceilings" of
organisational position and the unlimited possibilities of spiritual progress,
the latter being the main point of dharma. It is certain that the deeper
teachings (the fourteen root tantric precepts, for instance) make any feeling
of male superiority clearly a failing. It is also clear that the states that we
are aiming to achieve (arhat, arhani, bodhisattva, bodhisattvi, mahasiddha,
mahasiddhi and so forth) rely, in the most part, upon transcending both the
physical and mental aspects of sexuality to attain something far more sublime
and enlightened. One is aiming for a pure mind and the basic teachings on that
pure mind--as buddha nature--say that "dharmata knows no differences of
male, female, caste, race or the like". </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Let us look at some of the outstanding
women at the time of Buddha. Also, quite interestingly, we find in the Jataka
stories telling the former lives of these great beings--male and female--many
examples where they were formerly couples. To mention briefly a few of the most
famous early female sangha:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Mahaprajapati
Gautami*,
the Buddha's wet-nurse and the woman who raised him (his natural mother died
shortly after childbirth), was the very first nun and was declared by the
Buddha to be foremost in attainment among his female disciples. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The Buddha visited Kapilavastu to
settle the dispute between the Sakyans and the Koliyans concerning the right to
take water from a river. When the dispute had been settled, the Buddha preached
the Kalahavivāda Sutta, and five hundred young Sakyan men joined the Order. The
Sakyan wives, led by Prajāpatī, went to the Buddha and asked leave to also be
ordained. The Buddha refused and went on to Vesāli. But Prajāpatī and her
companions, undaunted, had barbers cut off their hair, and donning yellow
robes, followed the Buddha to Vesāli on foot. They arrived with wounded feet at
the Buddha's monastery and repeated their request to ordain as monastics. The
Buddha again refused but Ananda interceded on their behalf and Buddha granted
their request, subject to eight strict conditions.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>She first, and soon afterwards the five
hundred women she led, attained the state of arhani. It is said that the wonderful
manifestations surrounding her funeral rites were only equalled by those
surrounding the Buddha's own cremation.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Yasodhara* was
deeply connected with Prince Gautama from many previous lives and became his
principal queen. When he renounced palace life and left her and her newly-born
baby, she understood his quest and she herself lived, similarly to him, in a
simple yellow cloth, eating one meal a day and meditating as much as she could.
Having brought up their son, Rahula, she and he both joined the order and she
became an arhani.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Arya
Khema* was a queen who attended the Buddha's teachings in the
Bamboo Grove of Jetavana and who gained enlightenment on the spot, in her
beautiful royal gowns and jewellery, without having to go through a phase of
renunciation first. Thereafter, she joined the nuns and became famous for her
pithy and wise teachings.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Queen
Samavati*, a lay disciple of the Buddha, whom the Buddha
declared to be the most full of loving kindness and compassion of all his
female followers.
She brought the King and most of her court to dharma by her purity and goodness
but was cruelly assassinated, along with hundreds of her followers, by another
jealous queen. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Kisagotami* was a low-caste person who
could not let go of her newly-deceased child, going from house to house seeking
help, cradling its corpse. People ridiculed her (it was a time of high infant
mortality) but someone suggested she see the Buddha. She went to the Buddha,
hoping for some way to revive the corpse in her arms--some miracle or some
medicine. The Buddha asked her to collect a bowlful of mustard seeds, one seed
from each house where there had not been a death<a href="#_ftn19">[19]</a>. In trying to get the seeds,
she understood impermanence and mortality. Giving up hope for her dead child,
she eventually joined the Order and became an arhani.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Patacarawas
known as the foremost keeper of the Vinaya of the early nuns, as was Upali for
the monks. She had
lost her sanity after the death of first her husband, then her newly-born
child, then her other son, then her parents, all within hours. Wandering naked
and distraught, she was stoned and chased away by people until she met the
Buddha, who restored her sanity, taught her dharma and accepted her as a nun,
telling her:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Through many
existences, you have wept more tears over the loss of dear ones than could be
contained in the waters of the four oceans.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>She understood and thereafter so profoundly
appreciated the benefits emerging from observing the nuns' discipline that her
life became a shining example of purity and freedom, inspiring her sister nuns.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Bhadra Kapilani* (see first part of her
story above, under Kasyapa). After parting ways with Kasyapa at the crossroads,
she found her way to Shravasti and stayed with some non-Buddhist female
renunciates (perhaps widows) for some five years. She listened to the Buddha
teaching in the Jetavana Grove during this time. Then the order of Buddhist
nuns was established. She joined and swiftly became an arhani. Most of her life
was spent developing the order of nuns. The Buddha praised her as being the
female disciple with the best recollection of past lives.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>For more details of the some of the
above stories, by Hellmuth Hecker, visit <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/earlywomen.html">www.khenpo.eu/earlywomen.html</a>
               </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Notable Human Sangha after the Buddha"
                           pagetitle="Notable Human Sangha after the Buddha"
                           tocentry="Notable Human Sangha after the Buddha">
               <paragraph>We have a tremendous problem of
'absence of history' here. When one considers over seventeen centuries of
Indian Buddhism involving hundreds of millions of Buddhists, it is clear that
there must have been an unimaginable wealth of peaceful, realised, wise and
liberated beings: in all shapes and sizes. Some were scholars, some were
yogins, some in monasteries, some wandering hermits. The monasteries and
communities were themselves huge and illustrious gatherings of evolved human
beings, often in magnificent surrounding, such as the beautifully-endowed seven
square kilometres of Nalanda monastic university. Yet, due to a lack of written
records, we have only a few fragments of information. It may be helpful to
contemplate that enormous period of time and its richness a little before
moving on to the few significant names and lives we will mention below.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Nagarjuna* and *Asanga* were known as the *Two Beautifiers of the World<a href="#_ftn20">[20]</a>*
or as *The Two Who Set Great Traditions in Motion<a href="#_ftn21">[21]</a>*.
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>They are
credited with formulating, as practice methods and as expounded theory, the Mahayana
teachings given by the Buddha in the Second and Third Turnings of the Wheel of
Dharma.  They are generally viewed as being either earthly emanations of the
great bodhisattvas Manjushri and Maitreya (see below), respectively, or else as
being so inspired by those bodhisattvas that the result was the same.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>    Thanks to them we have the bulk of
our Mahayana teachings and thanks to their disciples we have the main
traditions of Mahayana Buddhism, with their various subtle differences of
views. Although many sources set Nagarjuna as the founder of the Middle Way
(Madhyamaka) school and Asanga as the founder of the Mind Only (Cittamatrins),
our contemporary teachers place their works above any of the traditions which
base themselves on their writings. Indeed, a close analysis of the five great
shastras of Asanga would incline two of them to Middle Way and two to Mind
Only. It is better to attribute the schools to these two masters' followers.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Nagarjuna's*
life is somewhat of a mystery. He was predicted in various sutras, such
as  The Descent into Lanka
Sutra.  There was:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·   
a Nagarjuna popularly attributed to the second century
CE (his dates are sometimes given as 150-250 CE approx.<a href="#_ftn22">[22]</a> but
could have been a century or more earlier<a href="#_ftn23">[23]</a>), born in southern India, and </paragraph>
               <paragraph>·   
another some five centuries later and</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·   
others. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Legend [taken as granted by Tibetans] has
it that they are one and the same person. He was decapitated in the third
century and his head and body were buried some kilometres apart. With time,
they drew closer together, underground, and he eventually resuscitated as
Nagarjuna II, the mahasiddha who plays an important role in the mahamudra
transmission, the discovery of the Hayagriva Tantra, the Green Tara tantra
transmission etc.<a href="#_ftn24">[24]</a> 
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>    Some historians take a more
rational approach and believe that several important Buddhist characters with similar
names have been "ambiguated" into one. This mystery will not likely
be solved in our lifetimes, if ever, and it matters little, as it is the teachings
attributed to Nagarjuna--and all that those teachings gave rise to--that count practically
for us. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)    Furthermore, if someone
understands Nagarjuna as being the human presence of the bodhisattva of wisdom,
Manjushri, then we can understand the possibility of the various lives of
"Nagarjuna" as being the key moments of philosophical advance in
Mahayanan Indian Buddhism. This is similar to the way in which we see Guru
Rinpoche's "life" as being the gathering of stories of the main
manifestations of the buddha mind as "guru" in ancient India and
Tibet. As mentioned before, _the proof of the pudding is in the eating_
and if we do aspire to have the clarity, peace, strength and beauty of mind of
our contemporary masters, such as the Karmapa, then their more fantastic
beliefs concerning Nagarjuna were ingredients of the "pudding" that
they ate to become as they are<a href="#_ftn25">[25]</a>.
We have Nagarjuna as:(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
The
philosopher who developed the voidness teachings of the second turning,
demonstrating the absence of entity in all things, not just in a persona or
soul.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
The
person who visited the naga realm to retrieve the Perfection of Wisdom (_prajnaparamita_)
texts entrusted to them by Ananda. There are many versions of these, from the
longest, in 100,000 lines down to (probably the earliest one in) 8,000 lines,
and their shortened and very popular versions as the Heart Sutra<a href="#_ftn26">[26]</a> and the Diamond Sutra.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
A famous
alchemist who, among other things, introduced the use of processed gems, heavy
metals and precious substances into _siddha medicine_. These require
considerably complicated refining and detoxification processes but are famed
for their results<a href="#_ftn27">[27]</a>.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
The
great siddha who found a copper casket containing the Hayagriva tantra and who
also introduced the Green Tara practice to India.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
A
lineage master in many different tantric lineages, including _mahamudra_..(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·  
The
abbot who made a thorough reform in Nalanda university, expelling eight
thousand monks for inadequate maintenance of the monastic code (vinaya).(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Nagarjuna's best-known disciple was
Aryadeva (see below). Many texts are attributed to Nagarjuna (see <a href="#mahatexts">Annexe</a>) but some say that only his keynote "Root
Verses on the Middle Way" was without doubt his. We will focus on it in a
later module.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Asanga* is
attributed to the third or fourth century CE. He was born in the region of Kashmir.
He had been predicted by Buddha Shakyamuni, who announced that about nine
centuries after his parinirvana, Asanga would appear in this world  to protect the
teachings of the Mahayana*.* His younger brother was  Vasubandhu . Their
mother, Prasannasila, a former nun, had made the powerful vow to give birth to
two sons whom she would rear to help spread and strengthen the teachings of the
Buddha, following a period of decline after the destruction of a great part of
the library of Nalanda by arson.
Asanga took monastic vows, studied the tripitaka and the Mahayana, and pursued
his search for a definite understanding of ultimate reality by entering the
path of the tantras. During an initiation, Asanga's cast flower fell on the
field of Buddha Maitreya. Consequently, Asanga meditated on future Buddha Maitreya . He
journeyed to the mountain called Bird Foot Hill and meditated in seclusion.
    After three years without result, he felt despondent and left his cave. On
his way he saw a pigeon leaving its nest through a small hole in the rocks.
Noticing how that hole had been worn smooth by the feathers of generations of
pigeons, Asanga was inspired to more diligence and returned to his practice.
After three more years of fruitless meditation, he again felt like giving up.
On his way to town he met a man who was rubbing an iron bar with a smooth
cloth. Upon asking the man what he was doing, he was told that he was making a
needle! So much diligence for such a small worldly aim encouraged Asanga to
return to his retreat place once more. A third time that he left, he saw a man
digging away a mountain, that cast shade on his cottage.
     After
12 years  of meditation, he still had not "met"
Maitreya face-to-face. Desperate and discouraged, he again left his retreat
place and on the way to the next town, he passed a sick old dog on the side of
the street. The dog's hind part was paralysed and eaten by worms. Although the animal
was aggressive towards him, Asanga only felt overwhelming compassion. He
thought of removing the worms, but realized that his fingers would squeeze some
of them to death. Therefore he decided to remove them with his tongue. He knelt
down, closed his eyes, unable to bear the sight and smell of the dog's festering
sores, lowered his head and ... touched the dusty ground. He opened his eyes and
 saw
Maitreya in front of him*. *
    Asanga, surprised, asked him why he hadn't appeared earlier. Maitreya
answered:</paragraph>
               <paragraph> « I have been with you since the
very beginning, but your mind was not open enough to see me. Now, because of your
great genuine compassion, your karmic obscurations have been purified, and you
are able to see me*. » *</paragraph>
               <paragraph>As as test, they left for a town. No
one was able to see Maitreya, only a pious old woman perceived part of a dead
dog on Asanga's shoulder. And so Asanga
understood what it meant to be veiled by mental obscurations: without great
compassion and understanding, karmic obscurations cannot be dispelled.
    Asanga's perception was now purified, and he experienced the pure dimension
of Tushita, the paradise of Maitreya. There he received the _Five Great
Treatises of Maitreya_. Returning with them to our world, he taught
them widely. His brother *Vasubandhu* had, in the meantime, become
a great scholar and teacher of Hinayana abhidharma. Under Asanga, he entered
the Mahayana and became the main commentator on his brother's works. Asanga
also authored important Mahayana texts in his own right (see <a href="#mahatexts">Annexe</a>). The influence of these two brothers was enormous
and it lasts until today.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Six Ornaments &amp; Two Great Ones of the World"
                           pagetitle="The Six Ornaments &amp; Two Great Ones of the World"
                           tocentry="The Six Ornaments &amp; Two Great Ones of the World">
               <paragraph>(eh)This grouping names the Six
Ornaments as Nagarjuna and Asanga, just described, and their two main
respective disciples Aryadeva and Vasubandhu, and also Dignaga and his disciple
Dharmakirti<a href="#_ftn28">[28]</a>.
The two great ones were two great masters of Vinaya: Shakyaprabha and
Gubnaprabha. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*Aryadeva* was born in Sri Lanka to a royal
family, and lived between the middle of the second and the middle of the third
centuries C.E. According to some accounts, he was born from a lotus. At an
early age, he became a monk and studied the Buddhist scriptures, the  Tripitaka , thoroughly there
before leaving to South India to study with Nagarjuna in the Shatavahana kingdom of King
Udayibhadra. King Udayibhadra was the recipient of Nagarjuna's famous  Letter to a Friend  and  Precious Garland . Aryadeva
accompanied Nagarjuna and continued to study with him at Shri Parvata, the holy
mountains overlooking modern-day Nagarjunakonda Valley in Andhra Pradesh.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>At that time,
Matrcheta, a devotee of Shiva, was defeating everyone at Nalanda in debate.
Aryadeva went to meet the challenge. Aryadeva defeated Matrcheta in both debate
and miraculous powers and, after that, Matrcheta became his disciple, changing
his name to *Ashvaghosha*. The latter went on to write  Fifty Verses on the Guru ,
the standard text for how disciples need to relate to a tantric master.  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Aryadeva stayed at
Nalanda for many years. Later in life, however, he returned to Nagarjuna, who
entrusted all his teachings to him before he passed away. Aryadeva built many
monasteries in that area of southern India and taught extensively, establishing
the Mahayana tradition and, in particular, the Madhyamaka tenets. He is famous
for composing the  Four
Hundred Verse Treatise on the Actions of a Bodhisattva's Yoga  . It is
known as  The Four Hundred 
for short. Like Nagarjuna, Aryadeva too wrote commentaries on the  Guhyasamaja Tantra . Before
passing away, Aryadeva entrusted the teachings to Rahulabhadra.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)A
split developed in the line of Aryadeva, between the followers of his
commentators Buddhapalita and Bhavaviveka. The former gave rise to the _Prasangika_
or Consequence Middle Way School and the latter to the _Svatantra_ or
Autonomy Middle Way School.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Chandrakirti*
was in the next generation of disciples after Rahulabhadra. He wrote the most
famous Indian commentary on  The
Four Hundred  and vigorously defended the stance of Buddhapalita and
therefore gave rise to the Consequence School. His texts on the Middle Way and
logic are great classics, very influential in Tibetan Buddhism.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Vasubandhu was one of the
most important figures in the development of Mahayana Buddhism in India. He is seen
by some later Buddhists as cofounder of the Yogacara school along with his half
brother Asanga.
At first he studied in the Sarvastivardin tradition but became dissatisfied
with the abhidharma explanations of the famous Great Commentary. He himself wrote
commentaries on many sutras, works on logic, devotional poetry, works on
Abhidharma classifications, as well as original and innovative philosophical
treatises. His "Treasury of
Abhidharma" _Abhidharmakosha_ and his commentary to same (_Abhidharmakoshabhāshya_)
became great classics, both summarising and criticising the Great Commentary
from what later became the Sautrantika point of view<a href="#_ftn29">[29]</a>. Some
of his writings have survived in their original Sanskrit form, but many others,
particularly his commentaries, are extant only in their Chinese or Tibetan
translations. Vasubandhu was a many-sided thinker, and his personality as it
emerges from his works and his biographies shows him as a man who was not only
a great genius and a philosopher, but also a human being who was filled with
great compassion.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>He
later converted to Mahayana and composed many other voluminous treatises,
especially on Yogacara doctrines. Most influential in Eastern Asia was probably
the _Trimśikā_, the Thirty Verses on the Merely Representative and its
companion _Vimśatikā_, but he also wrote a large number of other works. At
first, he found his brother's works unnecessarily complex and not at all to his
taste. He was not very complimentary about them. Asanga very skilfully feigned
serious illness and Vasubandhu met with him, for the first time in a long time.
As soon as they started speaking about dharma, Vasubandhu recognised the superiority
of his brother's realisation and system. So much so, he wanted to cut off his
own tongue for having denigrated him and it ... but Asanga told him it would be
better to use his tongue for dharma. His commentaries to Asanga's texts and
thinking give us a wealth of insight.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>For
more information on Vasubandhu, by K Sarao, in the Internet Encyclopedia of
Philosophy, visit <a href="http://www.iep.utm.edu/v/vasubandhu.htm">http://www.iep.utm.edu/v/vasubandhu.htm</a>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
Indian Buddhist philosopher and logician Dignaga
(A.D. 480-540), was a disciple of Vasubandhu. He laid the foundations for the
Buddhist teachings on cognition theory and logic. It is said that he had
composed some 108 papers on logic and then saw the need to distil them all into
one text. The result, his Compendium of the Means of True Knowledge (_pramanasamuccaya_)
is one of the greatest works on Buddhist logic, yet it is very dense and not
easy to follow.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Dharmakirti was the person
whose Seven Treatises on Valid Cognition develop Dignaga's works have given us
some our most masterly and useful texts on logic. He was born a Brahmin in the south of
India and, a remarkably intelligent child, went to study in central India,
where he mastered much of both Buddhist and Advaita philosophy. In particular
he studied under a disciple of Dignaga. He saw how close, in many ways, were
the theories of Dignaga and Advaita. Being as well-informed about Buddhist
philosophy as anyone could be, and, knowing that only a master of both
disciplines could truly judge any differences, he returned to the South, where
he studied for twelve years under the greatest Advaita teachers. He also
received Buddhist transmission of the Chakrasamvara Tantra and had what is
known as a face-to-face meeting with Chakrasamvara. He saw the subtle flaws in
Advaita philosophy and now possessed both the knowledge and the spiritual power
to match anyone in debate. His influence in India became enormous and he
brought many people to dharma. He is seen as an earlier incarnation of the Karmapas
and the Seventh Karmapa has particularly strong visions of him and composed
major treatises on his work, dictating huge passages to his secretary and
citing the original verbatim without ever needing to refer to the original
texts.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Gunaprabha
was a great spiritual master, said to have attained the third bodhisattva level
and to have been a "disciple of Vasubandhu". Perhaps this means he
was of the line of Vasubandhu, as some people date him in the 7th century CE.
He composed a famous text called _Root Text on the Vinaya_ as well as
various commentaries to it, such as the _Twelve Thousand Verses_. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Shakyaprabha
wrote a famous text, called _Three Hundred Verses of the Novice_, of
advice to novice sangha, and a commentary to it called _Light-Holder_.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
writings on monastic conduct by these two masters are said by Tibetans to have
had an influence all over the Indian sub-continent and through into Tibet. Due
to their kindness, many people came to practice properly within the sangha.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Famous Ones of Vajrayana" pagetitle="The Famous Ones of Vajrayana"
                           tocentry="The Famous Ones of Vajrayana">
               <image width="209"/>
               <paragraph>If we have little telling us about the
regular Buddhist sangha in India, we have even less information about the great
beings of Vajrayana. As often they lived away from monasteries, in jungles and
on mountain slopes, and as their practice was carried in the heart and
transmitted person-to-person, there are no archaeological or written remains to
give us a thorough picture of their lives. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>By far and away
the most famous text we have on the "greats" of Vajrayana is the
Indian historian Abhayadatta's text on the eighty-four male and female mahasiddhas.<a href="#_ftn30">[30]</a>  He
wrote this is in the 12th century CE and it survived in Tibet, where it was a
classic reference. Of
course, there were many more than those eighty-four, especially seeing as one
of the frequent characteristics of the siddhas is to live in secrecy and
anonymity: more about the siddhas in Module 8.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The Sangha who Took Dharma to Tibet"
                     pagetitle="The Sangha who Took Dharma to Tibet"
                     tocentry="The Sangha who Took Dharma to Tibet">
            <subsubsection title="The Eight Great Chariots" pagetitle="The Eight Great Chariots"
                           tocentry="The Eight Great Chariots">
               <image width="209"/>
               <paragraph>These will also be discussed more in
Module 8 or <a href="http://www.khenpo.eu/8chariots.html">else see web site</a>.
For the moment, we will just mention the names of the great masters who took
dharma to Tibet and the main teachings they established there.</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*Guru Rinpoche (Padmasambhava* and his twenty-five
     main disciples, including *Vairocana* and *Vimalamitra*) and *Abbot
     Santaraksita* who took the original (Nyingma)
     teachings to Tibet in the 8th century CE. This happened under the royal
     patronage of *Trisong Detsen*, himself a bodhisattva.</li>
                  <li>*Atisa* (*Dipamkara*) who took the Khadampa teaching to Tibet in the early 11
     century CE.</li>
                  <li>*Marpa the Translator* who, in the latter
     half of the 11th century, brought from India the Marpa"Kagyu" (Four Transmissions of
     Mastery), including Mahamudra and fourteen major tantras from the Father,
     Mother and Non-Dual tantras . His main teacher was the great pandita and
     mahasiddha Naropa.</li>
                  <li>*Khyungpo Naljor*, who was from central
     Tibet, at the same time brought similar transmissions from two female
     teachers: Nyiguma and Sukhasiddhi. These became the Shangpa Kagyu. </li>
                  <li>*Khon Konchog Gyalpo* and his teacher, *Translator
     Drogmi*, who brought the Path and Result,
     later called Sakya teachings to Tibet. </li>
                  <li>*Dampa Sangye* and his disciple *MachikLapchi Dröma*, who brought the Peace-Making
     (includes the Cutting Through _chod_ practice) lineages to Tibet.</li>
                  <li>*Jonangpa* who brought the Six Unions teachings and Kalachakra
     Tantra to Tibet.</li>
                  <li>The mahasiddha *Orgyenpa*
     brought yogic practices called the Three Vajras</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>Of the above, only the first five are
fully-functioning independent lineages today, with the fourth only just
surviving, mainly through the efforts of Kalu Rinpoche and Bokar Rinpoche. The
remaining three fused into the  principal four lineages. Although the story of
all that history is complicated, with a lot of "cross-fertilisation",
the simple diagram below shows the main origins of today's schools. Also, in
blue lines, we can see how the main teachings of seven of those eight chariots
have become part of the Kagyu tradition. Of course, we could draw blue lines
into the other three traditions as well showing, for example, the Chod
(Pacifying) practice within them. This has not been done both for simplicity
and for accuracy, as the author does not have enough accurate information from
those lineages to do this properly. </paragraph>
               <image width="455"/>
               <paragraph>Eight Chariots and their fusion into Kagyu Lineage</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="&#34;Celestial&#34;\Sangha" pagetitle="&#34;Celestial&#34;\Sangha"
                     tocentry="&#34;Celestial&#34;\Sangha">
            <image width="119"/>
            <paragraph>Up to this point, our study of the
sangha has been that mainly of the humans who have maintained the Buddha's
teachings. To that, we have to add innumerable hosts of non-humans:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>The great bodhisattvas, in the ten
     levels.</li>
               <li>The Pratyekabuddhas.</li>
               <li>Celestial beings known as _daka_
     and _dakini_.</li>
               <li>Various gods.</li>
               <li>Spirits, nagas, and the like.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>As the quotation from the Lotus Sutra
(at the beginning of the Sangha section) and the closing verse of the Heart
Sutra (Annexed) show, these were deemed to be present during the time of
Sakyamuni Buddha, when he gave the Mahayana sutras.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It is impossible to do justice to the
great bodhisattvas. Both the _extent_ and the _quality_ of their
immense activity, in all sorts of time-space dimensions, mean that any
description is merely a tiny drop from an ocean. Suffice it here to mention the
famous *Eight Great Bodhisattvas*:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Avalokiteshvara*<a href="#_ftn31">[31]</a> is considered here only as the
bodhisattva who appears in the Mahayana sutras, such as the Lotus Sutra (a special
chapter is devoted to him), Heart Sutra and Shurangama Sutra. In year three we
will consider him in the Vajrayana context, as a yidam. The same applies to the
other bodhisattvas below.  Avalokiteshvara
is the very embodiment of _compassion_. He is also associated with
liberation through the sense of hearing (Shurangama Sutra) and the mantra _Om
Mani Padme Hung_.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Manjushri* is
the bodhisattva embodying _intelligence_. He is also a key figure in the Lotus
Sutra, Heart Sutra and other Perfection of Wisdom (_prajnaparamita_)
sutras and quite a few others. He is seen as the key influence on Nagarjuna.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Maitreya* is
the bodhisattva who will be the next Buddha of our age. He is recognised as such in
all Buddhist traditions. He is an important character in the Sukhavati Sutra,
where he is shown the pure land of Buddha Amitabha. He is also found in the
Gandhavyuha. He is seen as the key influence on Asanga and as the real author
of the latter's Five Great Treatises.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Samantabhadra* is an important figure in
the Lotus Sutra as well as in the huge Avatamsaka (Flower ornament) Sutra. In
the latter, his <a href="http://www.buddhanet.net/pdf_file/samantabhadra.pdf">ten great promises</a>
become a template for a bodhisattva's intentions and he is seen as the
epitome of _right conduct_. The way he gave us of visualising offerings,
in vastness in purity, has become the benchmark for imagined offerings.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Vajrapani* embodies
the _power_ and protective ability of dharma. As such, he often appears as part of a
threesome: Avalokitesvara the compassion of Buddha, Manjushri the wisdom and
Vajrapani the power to help beings and protect the teachings from
deterioration.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Kshitigarbha* figures mainly in the sutra
named after him: the Earth Store Sutra. He is very popular in Chinese and
Japanese Buddhism, where he is noted for his compassionate ability to save
beings in the lower realms, especially the hells.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Akashagarbha* is sometimes referred to as
Kshitigarbha's twin brother. He appears in the Earth Store Sutra and in the
Space Store Sutra, named after him. He is a patron of _creativity_ and
intelligence.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Nirvaranavishkambi* is perhaps the least-known
of the eight. He is the "one who overcomes obstacles", the said
obstacles being desire, hatred, sloth, arrogance and doubt. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="4" title="Taking Refuge" pagetitle="Taking Refuge"
               tocentry="Taking Refuge">
         <subsection title="Taking Refuge" pagetitle="Taking Refuge" tocentry="Taking Refuge"/>
         <subsection title="The very basics" pagetitle="The very basics" tocentry="The very basics">
            <paragraph>(eh)"Taking Refuge" is
the *first step* in Buddhism. It takes place through a formal ceremony, by
which one becomes a Buddhist, affirming trust in the Buddha, Dharma and Sangha.
That trust *subsequently becomes the working basis* for all the work done
on the mind and in daily life. Refuge is renewed daily.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <image width="119"/>
            <subsubsection title="The meaning of &#34;Refuge&#34;" pagetitle="The meaning of &#34;Refuge&#34;"
                           tocentry="The meaning of &#34;Refuge&#34;">
               <paragraph>It has the following main meanings:</paragraph>
               <list kind="ul">
                  <li>_Seeking *shelter*_ from ignorance and
     confusion, within, and from the sufferings of samsara, both within and without.</li>
                  <li>_Seeking *guidance*_ in one's life path.</li>
                  <li>_Seeking *inspiration*_ from the Teacher, the
     dharma teaching and the lineage of sangha, all of which have proved their
     worthiness of trust over the ages.</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>(eh)To take Refuge is to
recognise that all alone, relying on one's own wits and judgement, one will
never gain total freedom nor will one fulfil one's life by awakening all
possible human qualities to the full. To take refuge is a recognition that
countless beings in the past _have_ achieved freedom and fulfilment by
travelling "the one and only way" taught by the most liberated,
wisest, kindest and compassionate being ever to grace this planet--the Buddha.
It is an understanding that no one, even Buddha, can just save us but that each
person needs to attain to freedom and wisdom by their own efforts. Thus *the
Buddha* is seen not as a saviour but as the *Teacher* and example.  That
work is achieved by the methods and counsel of *the dharma--as the teaching
and the path*. The living experience of the dharma teachings is maintained
by *the sangha-our companions on the path*.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Furthermore, the act of first taking
refuge, and then strengthening the refuge by re-confirming it every day--many
times a day--gives great strength to the mind. Indecision is by its very nature
something that saps strength. Although intelligent questioning has its place,
so also does conviction and determination. A mind that has decided where it is
going and is content with its choices is a happy mind and a strong mind. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The strength of
refuge comes not just through our own determination but also through it connecting
us with what is truly meaningful and does has the power to help, i.e. the buddha-mind
within and all the buddhas and bodhisattvas in the universe without. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Who cannot be a refuge?" pagetitle="Who cannot be a refuge?"
                           tocentry="Who cannot be a refuge?">
               <paragraph>An umbrella can protect you from the
rain. A rich friend or rich parents can protect you from poverty. A guide dog
can lead a blind person to the Post Office. A professor can teach astrophysics.
A "special place" can help re-establish perspectives. There are all
sorts of protecting, guiding and inspiring things. They each help in their own
way but they are more or less limited to that. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>When you are seeking
a refuge from samsara--the repetitive patterns of your own ignorance and
weaknesses, as well as the endless prospect of rebirth after rebirth--then you
need to turn to someone or something that itself has successfully transcended those
things: something that truly has the power to protect you from them. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The things we
normally turn to for sustenance--parents, worldly deities, friends, lovers,
music, beautiful places where we feel good and so on and so forth--cannot show
us the way to liberation and enlightenment. They are all stuck in samsara
themselves, despite their many qualities. How can they show the way out when
they themselves are trapped? This is the powerful message of the Buddha's own life
story. He had such a wonderful wife, loving parents, beautiful places to be in,
wise people with whom to talk (and later some of the finest yogis of India with
whom to meditate) but each time he enquired, _Can you take me beyond birth
and death?, _ the answer was _No!_</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="What can provide a true refuge?"
                           pagetitle="What can provide a true refuge?"
                           tocentry="What can provide a true refuge?">
               <paragraph>The short answer is the Buddha, the
dharma and the sangha. These are known in Sanskrit as the _triratna_, the _Three
Most Precious Ones<a href="#_ftn32">[32]</a>_,
most often translated as the _Three Jewels_. In Vajrayana, we add the _Three
Roots_: the gurus, the yidams and the protectors (see below).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The reasons that these are a worthy
refuge are that:</paragraph>
               <list kind="ul">
                  <li>The *historical Buddha *did
     achieve total liberation and total wisdom. He became those things and his
     protective, guiding power shines throughout the five thousand years his
     teachings remain in this world. Moreover, we have seen that Sakyamuni
     became the *three kayas*--the very embodiment of wisdom, compassion,
     freedom, purity and power to help others. The kayas are the eternal buddha
     and lasting refuge. Furthermore, since we all have the *buddha nature*
     as our true nature, we have the very essence of those three kayas within
     our very own mind. Everyone can attain to it. Each of these three aspects
     of buddha (historical being, kayas and buddha nature) is a worthy refuge.</li>
                  <li>The dharma is the tried-and-tested
     collection of universal truths that have provided the means for hundreds
     of millions of beings to work towards liberation of the mind. The Buddha
     cannot simply "save" us by his blessing [if that were the case
     we would have been saved aeons ago] but by teaching us how to follow this
     age-old way that he and everyone who became buddhas have followed. The
     dharma has a remarkable quality of total purity.</li>
                  <li>Transmission of those dharma
     teachings is a living thing, from human to human: simply reading the words
     and the methods in books will never provide enough for liberation to
     happen. The sangha, and especially the _realised sangha_, carry the
     inner light of dharma. They have stable realisation of its result and that
     serves as the basis for transmission of knowledge.  </li>
               </list>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Different forms of refuge" pagetitle="Different forms of refuge"
                     tocentry="Different forms of refuge">
            <paragraph>Although there are quite a few variants
as far as the actual refuge ceremony goes, there are three main forms of
refuge: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>Basic.</li>
               <li>Mahayana.</li>
               <li>Vajrayana.</li>
            </list>
            <subsubsection title="Basic refuge" pagetitle="Basic refuge" tocentry="Basic refuge">
               <paragraph>One takes refuge in the historical *Buddha*
as the *Teacher*, in the *dharma* as the *teachings* showing the
path to be followed and in the monastic community of the *sangha* as the *finest
companions* on that path.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>    The main *motivation* for
taking refuge comes from a recognition of the sufferings and dangers of samsara
and a heartfelt wish to work on oneself so as to diminish the suffering and
increase happiness as much as is possible.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>    The *duration* for which one
takes refuge is from the moment of the ceremony until death. In very early
times, any Buddhist could give refuge to another. The ceremony is taken before
representations of the Three Precious Refuges: an image of the Buddha, the
dharma texts and a gathering of the sangha headed by a senior monk. Refuge is
received by reciting the following formula three times after the preceptor:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>All
buddhas and bodhisattvas, please heed me I pray. Master, please heed me I pray.
I, ... by name, take my refuge from now until I die, in the Buddha, the most
sublime of all humans, in the dharma, the most sublime of all that transcends
desire, and in the sangha, the most sublime of communities.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>This
is the essential part of the ceremony. Often it is preceded by making three
prostrations to the shrine and/or to the preceptor as the representative of the
Refuges. The commitment itself is traditionally taken on bended knee (right
knee) with the hands folded at the heart. A small lock of hair is cut, in
remembrance of the Buddha cutting his hair when he left the palace, as a symbol
of leaving vanity, ignorance and worldliness. A dharma name is given as a token
of being "reborn" into a new phase of life. Sometimes water is
sprinkled on the head as well.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Mahayana refuge" pagetitle="Mahayana refuge" tocentry="Mahayana refuge">
               <paragraph>The fields of refuge (what one takes refuge in) are
more complete here:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
The *buddha* is understood on three levels--as the _historical_
Buddha, as the _three kayas_ and as the "_one-and-only true nature_"
(buddha nature).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
The *dharma* is understood as the _dharma of
representations_ (all the teachings, scriptures and methods) and as the _dharma
as realisation_ (the inner path of experience bringing out lasting wisdom).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
The *sangha* is understood in both the general _monastic_
sense but most especially as the _realised sangha_ of bodhisattvas of the
ten levels.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The *motivation*
for taking refuge is primarily one of compassion, as one cannot bear the fact
that beings suffer in samsara and therefore one seeks refuge in order to be
able to help them. Of course, the actual person taking refuge is included among
"all beings". </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The *duration*
of the commitment one undertakes is from the time of the ceremony until
whenever the very heart of enlightenment is reached. The difference between this and the
basic refuge is rather interesting. In the basic refuge, the logic is that one
is only in control of things until one dies. After that, the changes are so
traumatic that one cannot guarantee keeping any commitment. In the Mahayana
refuge, one is planting a strong seed in consciousness in the hope that it will
trigger awareness in future lives of the need for refuge, even though this life
and its promises will not be clearly recalled.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The actual ceremony can be given in
various ways. These days, it is nearly always given in a very similar way to
the basic ceremony (above), except that the compassionate motivation and
many-lives duration are taught by the preceptor and are implicit in the promise
made by the aspirant. There is a more complicated way, lasting three days,
described by Gampopa:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The _special ceremony_ is in three parts: a
preparation, the actual ceremony and a conclusion.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The preparation involves first offering a
mandala, together with flowers, to an appropriate preceptor, after which the
preceptor is requested to confer refuge. Provided that the supplicant is a
suitable person and someone with Mahayana potential, the preceptor, having accepted
the request, will, on the first evening, set up representations of the three precious
refuges, arrange  offerings and explain both the benefits of taking refuge and
the shortcomings of not doing so. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>      The actual ceremony takes place on the
second evening. First the supplicant cultivates the notion that the [symbols of
refuge] on the shrine are the real presence of the most precious [refuges] and
then pays homage and makes prostration. The following words are then repeated three
times, after the preceptor:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>All buddhas and bodhisattvas, please heed me I
pray. Master, please heed me I pray. From this moment onwards and until the
essence of enlightenment is reached, I ... by name, take my refuge in the
Buddhas, the Victorious Accomplished Transcendent Ones who are the most sublime
humans. I take refuge in the dharma which is peace and nirvana, the most
sublime of all that is free from desire and attachment. I take refuge in the
sangha of realized bodhisattvas who are beyond turning back, the most sublime
of communities.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Then, inviting the sources of refuge in terms of
direct realization and imagining them to be really present, one again pays
homage and makes offerings thinking, _Whatever I do, you are aware of it_.
Following this, one repeats the refuge prayer, as above.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>      Next, in terms of the one-and-only essence
as a source of refuge, homage is expressed, offerings are made and refuge is
taken in a way in which the three spheres<a href="#_ftn33">[33]</a>
are totally pure. Since all phenomena have been, from the very beginning,
without self and without any truly-existing nature, then the buddha, dharma and
sangha must be envisioned as also being thus. This is the inexhaustible refuge,
the permanent refuge, the eternal refuge. Thus the _Sutra Taught at the
Request of Naga King Anavatapta_ says:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>What is it to have taken refuge with a mind free
from pollution?  By knowing all phenomena not to exist, by not envisaging them
as being form, as possessing characteristics or as being something but as being
totally pure "awakened plenitude"<a href="#_ftn34">[34]</a>
one has taken refuge in the buddha. By envisaging all phenomena as being
consequent on dharmadhatu, one has taken refuge in the dharma. By envisaging
them in a way which is non-dual and without conceptual elaboration, one has
taken refuge in the sangha.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>On the third evening, there is the concluding
ceremony, during which one makes thanksgiving offerings to the most precious sources
of refuge.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Note_: In both the above forms of refuge
(basic and Mahayana), a person takes refuge in the Three Precious Refuges and
becomes a Buddhist. That is all. It is like entering the great gate into
dharma. One is +not+ taking refuge in that particular Buddhist lineage or
in the particular Buddhist master who gives the ceremony. Of course, there is
inevitably some connection but that is only incidental. No commitment whatsoever
has been taken to follow that teacher or that tradition. The choice of
tradition and teacher is another matter.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>   Another point that often comes up is the
question, "Can I take refuge a second time?" The answer is nearly
always _yes_, since once refuge has been taken it is renewed every day
anyway, and so participating in a second or third ceremony can be seen as a way
of refreshing or renewing the refuge commitment. However, when this is the
case, one only repeats the promise three times, along with everyone else, but
does not go forward for the hair-cutting or new name.  </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Vajrayana refuge" pagetitle="Vajrayana refuge"
                           tocentry="Vajrayana refuge">
               <paragraph>(eh)Vajrayana is characterised by the
guru-disciple working relationship. This will be the topic of much of our
studies in year three of this course. Vajrayana refuge is just mentioned here
for the sake of completeness. Unlike the basic and Mahayana refuges (which are
implicitly included in Vajrayana refuge), it is a commitment to a lineage.
Refuge is taken with the Mahayana motivation and until enlightenment is reached
and the field of refuge is "six-in-one":(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)1.    
_Buddha_.                                                        (as
in Mahayana)(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)2.    
_Dharma_.                                                       (as
in Mahayana)(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)3.    
_Sangha_.                                                        (as
in Mahayana)(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)4.    
_Gurus_ of the lineage (as the presence of
buddha in the person's life).(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)5.    
_Yidams_ (as the essence of dharma practice
best suited to the person).(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)6.    
_Protectors_ (as the living presence of the sangha
within that person's practice). (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>It
is more than likely that, at the time of taking refuge, one will not yet have
found or committed oneself to a personal guru. Nevertheless, when Vajrayana
refuge is taken there is an understanding that whenever that time comes, the
guru will be the very embodiment of all six refuges mentioned above. Taking
part in a Vajrayana refuge ceremony does not mean that you have taken the
preceptor as your guru.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Why go through a refuge ceremony?"
                     pagetitle="Why go through a refuge ceremony?"
                     tocentry="Why go through a refuge ceremony?">
            <paragraph>Some
people cannot see the point of taking a formal commitment of refuge, through a
ceremony. They feel that the inner trust they feel for the Buddha and his
teachings is enough. However, the
traditional teachings say that there is unimaginable benefit in going through
the ceremony, because it establishes a _root of virtue_. A root of virtue
is something that produces goodness non-stop, whether one is asleep or awake,
actually performing virtue or not. It is called "root" because it is
like planting a tree, which grows stronger each year, producing more and more
branches and fruits. Without a root of virtue, good karma is only
generated in the actual moments of virtuous mind and action. In the case of
refuge, virtue would only be generated in those moments, those seconds, when
the heart is in a state of trust and devotion to the Three Precious Refuges. Whereas
from the time of the refuge ceremony onwards (unless the commitment is broken
or handed back), _every_ moment is generating good refuge karma. This all
happens because of the way a profound commitment changes the entire mind--in
other words, the entire person.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>   
The _root of virtue_ of refuge can only be properly planted through the
circumstances of the ceremony, during which a very special interdependence
occurs as the aspirant's mind opens up and takes a promise in the presence of
what can respond to that commitment and promise. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The commitments of refuge" pagetitle="The commitments of refuge"
                     tocentry="The commitments of refuge">
            <paragraph>Refuge is a commitment and there are certain simple
rules or guidelines to be observed in order to maintain the sacred bond and
root of virtue that has been created. The nine main commitments are well
explained by Gampopa:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
*instructions* concerning refuge are nine-fold: three common instructions,
three particular instructions and three specific instructions.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Three
instructions _common_ [to all three refuges] are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>      1.   To
strive at all times to make offerings to the three precious refuges, at least
dedicating the first mouthful of food when eating.<a href="#_ftn35">[35]</a>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>      2.   To
never abandon the three precious refuges even should this cost life itself or
involve personal loss. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>      3.   To
develop the habit of repeatedly calling to mind the qualities of these three
most precious things and taking refuge in them.<a href="#_ftn36">[36]</a>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Three
_particular_ instructions are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>      1.   Having
taken refuge in the buddhas, refuge need no longer be sought in any other
divinity. In the _Great Nirvana Sutra_ it says:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
best of all those who love virtue are those who have taken refuge in the
buddhas. They will never go soliciting refuge from other divinities.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>      2.   Having
taken refuge in the dharma, harm should no longer be done to any sentient
being. A sutra says:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Having
taken refuge in the noble dharma, a person is far removed from a mentality of
harm and violence.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>      3.   Having
taken refuge in the sangha, trust should not be placed in the misguided<a href="#_ftn37">[37]</a>. The
sutras say:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Those
who have taken refuge in the sangha will not side with the misguided.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Three
_specific_ instructions are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>      1.   One
should show respect for images of the One Thus Gone, whatever they may be, from
a small image moulded in clay upwards, because they represent the real most
precious buddha. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>      2.   One
should show respect for the volumes and collected works of scripture, from a
mere letter of scripture upwards, because they represent the most precious
dharma.<a href="#_ftn38">[38]</a>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>      3.   One
should show respect for buddhist garb, from a simple patch of yellow cloth
upwards, because it represents the most precious sangha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the second of the _particular_ instructions above, it says that a natural
consequence of taking refuge in the dharma is to do one's best never to harm
any sentient being ((including oneself!). This is the very heart of dharma--the
"Path of Peace", "The Way of No-Harm" (_ahimsa_). Therefore,
the natural consequence of refuge is to take at least one of the precepts that
avoid harm. Such commitments are known as the _individual-liberation_
commitments / vows / precepts. The Sanskrit word is _prā_ _timoksha_. One is not obliged to take a precept
when taking refuge but many masters counsel it and many "refugees"
like to take advantage of this special moment in their life to make such a
sacred promise. At Samye Ling, people taking refuge are requested to observe
the five main lay precepts ( see below) for the twenty-four hours following the
ceremony.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="5" title="Vows of Individual Liberation"
               pagetitle="Vows of Individual Liberation"
               tocentry="Vows of Individual Liberation">
         <image width="245"/>
         <paragraph>These
_vows of individual liberation_ are so-called because they help free a
person from the shackles of karma. They are focused on actions of body and
speech. By not harming others, physically or verbally, a person is not only
making the world a more peaceful and harmonious place but also, at the same
time, not creating for himself or herself harmful karma that will rebound back
in a future life, as described in the karma teachings. The "rebound"
can be a lower type of rebirth, painful circumstances even if one is human or
an unhealthy, unpleasant environment. Furthermore, by thoroughly establishing
habits of non-harm and saying a definitive "goodbye" to old, harmful
habits, one is closing the door on what might have become an incalculable
number of harms in future lives. A brighter future is opened up.</paragraph>
         <paragraph>We
saw, in the refuge teachings, that a vow plants a _root of virtue_ that
works non-stop from the moment of taking it onwards, until it is broken or
given up or expires. It is dramatically different from the moment-by-moment
karma of ordinary life. Therefore, there is untold benefit in keeping precepts
and this is why Tibetan lamas are so keen on us taking them, provided that we
are ready and able to keep them. That's another kettle of fish!</paragraph>
         <paragraph>The
precepts of individual liberation fall into two groups:</paragraph>
         <paragraph>1.    
*Lay
precepts*, taking for
various time periods and based on the Five Precepts, known as the _Five Great
Gifts_ (to oneself) and called the Five Golden Rules in Samye Ling. These
are based on the Abhisanda Sutra. There are three categories<a href="#_ftn39">[39]</a>: 
                  Temporary precepts.
                  Upasaka (men).
                  Upasika (women).</paragraph>
         <paragraph>2.    
*Monastic
precepts*, mainly taken
for life but sometimes for one year or more, for novices<a href="#_ftn40">[40]</a>. These are based on the _Four
Root Vows_ and have five main categories. </paragraph>
         <paragraph>We
will return to this topic in Year Two<a href="#_ftn41">[41]</a>,
when we study the Paramita of Right Conduct, in which self-liberation precepts
play an important role. </paragraph>
         <subsection title="Lay Precepts" pagetitle="Lay Precepts" tocentry="Lay Precepts">
            <paragraph>(eh)The Five Great Gifts to Oneself<a href="#_ftn42">[42]</a> are the precepts:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.    
Not to kill
intentionally.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.    
Not to steal.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.    
Not to intentionally
lie (for self-interest).(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)4.    
Not to engage in
sexual misconduct.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)5.    
Not to take intoxicants.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These
are based on the Abhisanda Sutra<a href="#_ftn43">[43]</a>,
which is one of the nine thousand or so short sutras in the Anguttara Nikaya of
the Pali canon:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Now, there are these <a>five gifts</a>,
five great gifts -- original, long-standing, traditional, ancient, unadulterated,
unadulterated from the beginning -- that are not open to suspicion, will never
be open to suspicion, and are unfaulted by knowledgeable contemplatives &amp;
priests. Which five?</paragraph>
            <paragraph>"There is the case where a disciple of the noble
ones, abandoning the taking of life, abstains from taking life. In doing so, he
gives freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression to
limitless numbers of beings. In giving freedom from danger, freedom from
animosity, freedom from oppression to limitless numbers of beings, he gains a
share in limitless freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, and freedom
from oppression. This is the first gift, the
first great gift -- original, long-standing, traditional, ancient,
unadulterated, unadulterated from the beginning -- that is not open to
suspicion, will never be open to suspicion, and is unfaulted by knowledgeable
contemplatives &amp; priests. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Furthermore, abandoning taking what is not given
(stealing), the disciple of the noble ones abstains from taking what is not given.
In doing so, he gives freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, freedom from
oppression to limitless numbers of beings. In giving freedom from danger,
freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression to limitless numbers of beings,
he gains a share in limitless freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, and
freedom from oppression. This is the second
gift... </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Furthermore, abandoning illicit sex, the
disciple of the noble ones abstains from illicit sex. In doing so, he gives
freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression to
limitless numbers of beings. In giving freedom from danger, freedom from
animosity, freedom from oppression to limitless numbers of beings, he gains a
share in limitless freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, and freedom
from oppression. This is the third gift... </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Furthermore, abandoning lying, the disciple of
the noble ones abstains from lying. In doing so, he gives freedom from danger,
freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression to limitless numbers of beings.
In giving freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression
to limitless numbers of beings, he gains a share in limitless freedom from
danger, freedom from animosity, and freedom from oppression. This is the fourth gift... </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Furthermore, abandoning the use of intoxicants,
the disciple of the noble ones abstains from taking intoxicants. In doing so,
he gives freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, freedom from oppression
to limitless numbers of beings. In giving freedom from danger, freedom from
animosity, freedom from oppression to limitless numbers of beings, he gains a
share in limitless freedom from danger, freedom from animosity, and freedom
from oppression. This is the fifth gift...<a href="#_ftn44">[44]</a>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
first four of these Five Great Gifts were already discussed in the karma
chapter. The fifth--not to take intoxicants--refers to any intake of drugs or
alcohol that alters consciousness and thereby diminishes good judgement. Those
who take this precept are allowed prescribed medications, even if those do
affect consciousness, assuming there is some overall benefit in taking them. It
precludes leisure drugs, especially habit-forming ones, including alcohol and tobacco.
The main point of not taking intoxicants is that the blurred judgement and
dependency they lead to can then cause a person to commit other harmful
actions. But there is also the fact that they harm the precious human existence
of the person taking them. In this respect, Tibetan lamas say that most people
severely underestimate the harm caused by smoking. Although Buddha Sakyamuni
never pronounced on smoking (it seems to have reached India after his time),
Guru Rinpoche speaks of it several times in the _terma<a href="#_ftn45">[45]</a>_ texts, written in
the 8th century CE and discovered at various moments of history since then. He
describes it as an agent, a vector, for bringing negative influences into the _prana_
systems of the body. When one considers the sacredness of breath in many
faiths, and its use in advanced yogas--both physical and mental--it is not
surprising that polluting the breath-system with smoke and poisons,
"blessed by demons", is seen as a horrible and damaging thing to do!</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Provided
that they have taken Refuge, lay people can take one or more of these _Five Precepts_, or all five, for a day, or
several days etc. up to the rest of one's life. To take all five for life makes
a person a "Lay Devotee", or _upā_ _saka<a href="#_ftn46">[46]</a>_ (_upā_ _sika_ for a woman). If they are taken with a commitment to
celibacy as the commitment to no sexual misconduct, it is called _brā_ _hmacarya upāsaka<a href="#_ftn47">[47]</a>_ --"pure conduct" upasaka.  These can be combined with three more, making _Eight Precepts_ whereby one promises:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>I undertake to abstain from taking life (both
     human and nonhuman).</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from taking what is not
     given (stealing).</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from all sexual activity.</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from telling lies.</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from using intoxicating
     drinks and drugs which lead to carelessness.</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from eating at the wrong
     time (the right time is eating  after sunrise and before noon).</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from singing, dancing,
     playing music, attending entertainment performances, wearing perfume, and
     using cosmetics and garlands (decorative accessories).</li>
               <li>I undertake to abstain from luxurious places for
     sitting or sleeping.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>If
the latter are taken with further ordination in mind, a person is known as an _anā_ _gārika_.
 </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Popular
ways for lay people to observe these _uposita_ ("for fasting") or
_nyennay_ (Tib.) precepts temporarily are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
To take them for
one day, on special days of the lunar month, i.e. New Moon, Full Moon, Eighth
Lunar Day, Tenth Lunar Day etc. or on the major Buddhist festivals,
commemorating the Buddha's enlightenment, passing into parinirvana, first
teaching, returning from the heavens where he liberated his mother, performing
miracles etc.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
To do the _Nyungynay_
practice<a href="#_ftn48">[48]</a>,
which involves a two-day retreat, including the evening before and the early
morning after the two days. The second day involves a complete
liquids-and-solids fast. These are practised after Tibetan New Year in Samye
Ling--eight successive pairs.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The great master Khyapjay Kalu Rinpoche,
among others, also recommended extending the eight precepts to ten, in the
tradition of Atisha, by adding two components of compassion:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)9.            Vegetarianism, as a token
of respect for life<a href="#_ftn49">[49]</a>.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)10.          Only drinking water after
midday meal.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
precepts need to be taken from an abbot-preceptor who has a pure lineage of
transmission of these vows and who has kept those vows purely. Lay people do
not wear the monastic robes and are not obliged to keep the head
shaved/nearly-shaved. Some people who have taken the celibate upasaka
commitment for life wear white robes or white clothes to indicate their choice.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Renunciate's or Monastic Precepts"
                     pagetitle="Renunciate's or Monastic Precepts"
                     tocentry="Renunciate's or Monastic Precepts">
            <paragraph>The
five groups of monastic precepts are a little more complicated and will be
explained in brief here. They developed at the time of the Buddha but, except
for the basics, he never laid them down as his own idea of an ideal set of
rules for the sangha to follow. Each rule arose out of an incident, due to
which the sangha members were not sure what to do--or not--in a certain situation
and so they requested his counsel. This accounts for the rather heterogeneous
nature of the rules and their great number. Had the Buddha lived another eighty
years, there would doubtless have been a good deal more, as different
situations arose. Thus there is the spirit and the letter of the monastic code.
Often these coincide but sometimes not. Taken as a whole, the rules exist
primarily to keep a monastic's life simple and to free up time for practice.
Thus begging for food avoids cooking, possessing and maintaining cooking gear
and so on and so forth. Not eating after lunch means than no time is lost in
the evening seeking nourishment. However, if following the rules to the letter
involves more complication and loss of time, then obviously the original
intention is lost. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>On
account of the above, the monastic code is observed differently in different
Buddhist countries. Tibet, with remote villages and a population of six million
in a country seven times the size of France and with a freezing climate, was
very different from India. It was simply not possible to go out on a begging
round every day. Thus the monks made a major alms-gathering in the autumn,
after harvest, and stored things for the winter. They tended to follow the
spirit rather than the letter of the rules. In Sri Lanka, Burma and Thailand,
the letter is followed more rigorously and it is necessary for bhikkhus (full
monks) to be accompanied by upasakas<a href="#_ftn50">[50]</a>
as they themselves are not allowed to carry money or do many things that modern
life makes necessary when travelling or staying in towns. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)All monasticism is based on the Four
Root Vows. To break radically any one of them is to lose one's
"ordination".  Depending upon the tradition and the circumstances,
once that is lost it is irreparable. As such it is compared to a clay pot,
shattered forever.  The four are:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.    
Not to kill a human
being.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.    
Not to take that
which is not offered.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.    
Not to lie
intentionally (in particular about dharma achievement).(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)4.    
To observe celibacy
and pure sexual conduct.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
full set of monks vows comprises 253 commitments arranged in five sets of
"downfalls" to avoid. The complete nuns' vows total 364. As these are
a formidable undertaking for someone entering the sangha, there evolved a _training_
or _novice_ ordination, in which the main rules are observed and in which
some of the rules which are downfalls for a full monk or nun become reparable
breakages for a trainee. The novice monk observes 33 basic rules and the novice
nun 22. Although those are their actual commitments, the very fact of being a
novice implies living as closely as possible by the rules of full renunciates
and making effort to learn and understand those rules. The five sets of monastic _pratimoksha_ are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.    
Monk,                            Skt: _bhikkhu_, Tib: _dge
slong_ ("gelong").</paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.    
Nun,                              Skt: _bhikkhuni_,
Tib: _dge slong ma_ ("gelongma").</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3.    
Nun in Training,          Skt: _siksamā_ _na_, Tib: _dge
slob ma_ ("gelopma").</paragraph>
            <paragraph>4.    
Novice Monk,              Skt:
_srā_ _manera_,
Tib: _dge tshul_ ("getsul").</paragraph>
            <paragraph>5.    
Novice Nun,                Skt: _srā_ _manerika_, Tib: _dge
tshul ma_ ("getsulma").</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Bhikkhuni transmission never went
to Tibet and there are moves today, involving some noted scholars and lineage
heads, to thoroughly check that the Bhikkhuni transmission that persisted in
China is an authentic, unbroken lineage, able to be integrated into the Tibetan
system. If so, nuns in the Tibetan tradition can take it and later reintroduce
it into their own system. Many have already taken the Chinese vows in
anticipation of this. Those vows have to be maintained properly for a certain
number of years by those who take them before a Tibetan sangha can be
constituted that can pass on the ordination.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These days, at Samye Ling, people
seriously considering taking renunciate's vows (the five groups just mentioned)
are often advised to take the eight main precepts, including celibacy, and to keep
them for a trial period, often six months or a year, so that they have the
experience of quite what it means to live under such liberating constraints.
This is very helpful, as many people's notion of being a monk or a nun is far
too idealised and little connected with the reality of such a life. Some people
over-estimate the renunciate's life as being a solution to their problems. It
will be, if pursued long enough and with enough diligence and faith, but the
simple fact of donning the robes and changing lifestyle cannot change
everything overnight. One must remember that these vows concern primarily body
and speech conduct and many people's problems are related to the way in which
their mind works. The latter takes time, meditation and insight to really
change. Renunciation and monasticism should create a favourable environment in
which that can happen.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Taking one of these five sets of
pratimoksha vows entitles a person to wear the monastic robes. The colour and
style of the robes has evolved over time and from country to country. Certain
colours (blue, orange and red) were permitted by the Buddha and the main idea
was to use the cheapest dye available. Chinese and Japanese monastic robes tend
to be black, blue or grey. In the Theravadin countries the robe is a saffron
brown. In Tibet they wear varying shades of maroon. The head is shaved
regularly and the hair not allowed to grow beyond a centimetre or so. This is a
token of following the Buddha, who cut off his magnificent hair when leaving
palace life: thus it is a symbol of renouncing the world. Hair was thought of
as a source of power in ancient India and the way the hair was worn was a
symbol of social status. The Prince Siddharta would have had and ornate pile of
hair, set with jewels to show his royal status. Hair is also of course part of
what is seen as beautiful and sexually attractive. Furthermore, hair grows
back, as do the mind poisons and bad habits, so the regular cutting off of hair
symbolises constant attentiveness to cutting back harmful karma and the
defilements.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </chapter>
</book>