<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book">
   <chapter index="2"
            title="The Rare and Sublime Dharma, An Introduction to the Three&#xA;Turnings of the Dharma Wheel, Wheel One: The Four Great Truths - Truth One:&#xA;Beings, Worlds and Suffering"
            pagetitle="Module 2"
            tocentry="The Rare and Sublime Dharma, An Introduction to the Three&#xA;Turnings of the Dharma Wheel, Wheel One: The Four Great Truths - Truth One:&#xA;Beings, Worlds and Suffering">
      <section index="1" title="" pagetitle="" tocentry=""/>
      <section index="2" title="The Dharma" pagetitle="The Dharma" tocentry="The Dharma">
         <subsection title="The Dharma" pagetitle="The Dharma" tocentry="The Dharma">
            <image width="458"/>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Preamble_" pagetitle="_Preamble_" tocentry="_Preamble_">
            <paragraph>The
_dharma<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>_
is the name given to the Buddha's teachings. Dharma is not a religion<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>, neither is it a philosophy<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>. It is usually described as *a way*, i.e. a way of living, a way to attain
liberation and a path to a certain end (Nirvana). As such, it is famous as the:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*Middle
Way*,
through its avoidance of extremes, or as the </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*Path
of Peace*,
through its profound care for life in all its forms and its teachings which
tame the agitated, harmful mind. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Another
way in which dharma could be described is as the *Way of Truth*. The word _dharma_
actually means, "Things as they truly are". Two of dharma's main topics are the
*Two Truths* and the *Four Truths*. However, as religious claims to
being possessors of truth have poisoned the world's history, one must be very
careful always to remember the genuine universality of the Buddha's message and
not to get lost in dogma, in sectarianism or the "_ism_" of Buddhism
itself. Paraphrasing what many of our great masters say,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>If you are a good person, caring, kind
and compassionate and devoted to awakening your mind to truth, you are what
could be called "a natural Buddhist", whichever belief you subscribe to
officially, as you are in accord with what is the true nature of things. Even
if you ardently wear a Buddhist badge but are not those things, then there is
nothing Buddhist about you.<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
Dr Saddhatissa said, in Samye Ling:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Enlightened One did not come to
this world to found a religion, but to help everyone, however he could.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>And
as many masters say,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_Whatever proves itself to be true, that
+is+ the Buddist teaching._</paragraph>
            <paragraph>And
the Buddha himself is famous for having invited his disciples again and again
never to believe something simply because he had declared it, but to put it to
the test themselves, whenever that was practicable.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>"There are two types of teacher and
    student. The _old-brains_ are content to learn by heart and pass on
    that tradition. The _new brains_ think about what they are studying." the late Prof. Khenpo Troru Tsenam a master and physician of insatiable curiosity,
    who strove to bring Tibetan medicine and dharma to life and into the modern
    world</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Having
understood this *universality* of the
Buddha's teachings, which simply try to point out, or to help us discover,
things as they really are, one needs equally to appreciate the *living lineages* of masters down the ages who
have given these universal truths to the world and maintained their purity.
Without the tremendous compassionate activity of the enlightened beings of the
sangha, who have meticulously handed down the Buddha's insights from generation
to generation, the world would never know these truths--despite their
universality. Nor would it be able to savour their true meaning and value,
through the unique experience of being in the presence of great masters.
Supporting specific traditions and lineages is not antithetic to the notion of
seeking what is universal. *In this module, we will consider dharma generally,
in a sort of overview. Details from its vast and profound content form most of
the rest of the course.*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)<img width="455" src="module2_files/image003.png"/>(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)_a page of an
exceedingly rare text, handwritten in both Sanskrit and Tibetan, by Naropa and
Marpa_(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_What\the Buddha Originally Taught &amp; &#34;Buddhism&#34;_"
                     pagetitle="_What\the Buddha Originally Taught &amp; &#34;Buddhism&#34;_"
                     tocentry="_What\the Buddha Originally Taught &amp; &#34;Buddhism&#34;_">
            <paragraph>(eh)What has developed these past 2,500 years, upon the basis
of what the Buddha taught, is _Buddh+ism+_. Over the centuries, it
has incorporated many, many things, transforming them into skilful Buddhist
tools. Of particular mention are the enormous Greek influx, in art and other
areas, through <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gandhara">Gandhara</a> and
the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kushan">Kushan</a> dynasties, and
also the integration and transformation of ritualised prayer, as opposed to
simple chanting of the sutras.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)We live today in a unique moment in Buddhism as, in the
modern global village, Buddhist traditions that have existed in isolation for a
thousand years or more are now thrown together under the microscope of the
modern mind. They are being examined and confronted by the world, and they also
have to examine and confront themselves. Which teachings and practices
correspond to what the Buddha Sakyamuni really taught or intended for us? What
was truly inspired by the sambhogakaya aspect of the buddha mind, after
Sakyamuni's passing, and what, if at all, is merely one or another tradition's
own propaganda: their words put into the Buddha's mouth? What is of use in the
world today and what is disposable cultural ballast? Many such questions are
being asked and many are questions without absolute answers. Opinions differ.
In the end, each of us has to make up his or her mind, using good sense and
good judgement. In that respect, "the proof of the pudding is in the eating"
and we are fortunate to have some great Buddhist masters alive and accessible
in this world. Their own achievement and example is an inspiring testimony to
the beliefs and practices they follow. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)But caution! The sharpest of intellects and a "modern"
sense of values are maybe not enough to guarantee good judgement. They could
even mislead. For example, if the story of Milarepa took place in the modern
day, his guru Marpa's treatment of him would be a terrible scandal; totally
unacceptable. Yet it is one of the most inspiring examples of what faith can do
and what tough, uncompromising, enlightened guidance can bring forth from a
person. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Now, after these reflections, let us enter into a more
traditional overview:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*_There are two main aspects
to dharma:*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)·     
*_Conventional
dharma_*--consisting
of the concepts, words and scriptures of Buddhist theory along with all the
detailed practice instructions that enable a person to evolve. These are
well-structured and clearly-explained and they are there to help us give rise
to ...(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)·     
*_Real
dharma_*--which is
the totally-personal, _experiential_ journey of awakening as the mind
frees its shackles and burdens and enters into ever-deeper insight into truth
about existence, while opening up the loving, compassionate heart. These
ever-changing experiences are there to give birth progressively to a deep _wisdom_,
known as _realisation_. That is the "ultimate real dharma".  (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Of
these two, the first is more _outer_ and the second more _inner_. The
first is _describable_ and can be passed from one person to another. The
second is _indescribable_ and very intimate and personal. The first is a _cause_,
giving rise to the second, a _result_. We will consider these two aspects
in the traditional Mahayana way, as taught at Samye Ling by Khenchen Thrangu Rinpoche
and reproduced in "Maitreya on Buddha Nature".</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Explanation\of the Two Aspects of Dharma from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;_"
                     pagetitle="_Explanation\of the Two Aspects of Dharma from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;_"
                     tocentry="_Explanation\of the Two Aspects of Dharma from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;_">
            <paragraph>10._                  The dharma is that
imbued with _</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_                       the intrinsic
characteristics of the two truths: _</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_                       that which is and
that which causes freedom from bondage.^19^_</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_                       Inconceivable, not
two and concept-free,_</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_                       purity, clarity and
remedy._</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Buddhadharma--the
famous Buddhist Path of Peace--is the second Refuge. The Refuges exist as cause
Refuges and result Refuges. Cause _dharma_ consists of all the concepts
which together make the Buddhist teaching. These concepts have been perpetuated
through the spoken word and through writings, primarily those of the original
canon received from the Buddha, consisting of _sūtra, vinaya,_ _abhidharma_
(the Triple Collection<a href="#_ftn5">^1^</a>)
and _tantra. _To this must be added the principal treatises(_shastra_),
written by Buddhist teachers over the past 2,500 years, explaining this canon.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The Triple Collection (_tripitaka_) represents
remedies for the three main mind poisons:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)The *_sūtras_* are discourses on
     taming the mind, seen as the main antidote to anger. (eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)The ethical guidance of the  *_vinaya_*
     is the antidote to desire and (eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)The precise analysis of mind and matter in the *_abhidharmais the antidote to ignorance. (eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)Taken together, the three collections discuss
eighty-four thousand key types of experience. But, for all that knowledge and
for all their precious value to the world, the Threefold Collection remains
only concepts ... along with the sounds and letters which convey those concepts
from one human being to another. Their great value is in enabling communication
between those who have understanding and those who do not. Through their use--in
teachings, personal advice, study and sincere reflection--attitudes and values
can evolve and that will impact significantly on someone's life. In particular,
one learns to discern what ennobles life from that which poisons it. All these
aspects of dharma are calleddharma as representations_* or _relative
dharma_ or _conventional dharma_.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Guided by these teachings and one's own growing
discernment, one lives the life of a bodhisattva and meditates. This opens many
doors of experience: those of overcoming desire and anger and of feeling
universal love, compassion, impartiality, sympathy, tranquillity in meditation
and so forth. With time, the meaning of the words of dharma comes vividly to
life. From a wide range of _experiences_ emerges first-hand wisdom, known
as *_realisation_ (in the sense of 'made real').
Whereas experiences come and go, realisation develops. In fact, although one
can use the word _realisation_ in this broader sense of a growing
awareness of the Four Truths, its use in the scriptures is often confined to
the end result: direct recognition of the void nature of things. The
development of realisation is the result aspect of dharma, known as *_dharma
as realisation_. *(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Dharma as direct
realisation is true dharma whereas dharma as representation is its pale
reflection in the waters of the intellect. The _Uttara Tantra_ is almost
solely concerned with dharma as realisation, which has two functions: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>It has the
     power to eliminate all defilements and </li>
               <li>The power to
     bring about the full fruition of primordial wisdom.  </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>Intellectual
knowledge--reason in any of its forms--cannot do this, just as the mere word
'candle' cannot illuminate a dark room. Words may tell us where the candle is
and how to light it, but only the lit candle itself can shed light and dispel
darkness. Only the +practice+ of dharma can enable us to face up to our
imperfections and overcome them with the strength of peace and wisdom. Only
such work on oneself will enable the light of wisdom to shine.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The dharma journey of personal experience and
realisation is in fact a journey of liberation from that which binds us to a
life spoilt by physical and mental suffering. There are *three main types of
bondage*:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.   
the *_defilements_*:
desire, anger, ignorance, pride, doubt and distorted views of reality, along
with all their hybrid forms such as narcissism, jealousy, hypocrisy,
frustration etc.<a href="#_ftn6">^2^</a>  (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.   
A deluded
understanding, built of dualistic concepts, because one has not recognised the
true nature of one's mind. This is called the *_cognitive obscuration_*.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.   
Limitations and *blockages
in meditation*. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These three are
intimately related. Through inability in meditation, one is unable to rest
easily and continuously in non-dual ultimate truth. In a darkness of ignorance,
all sorts of confused dualistic perceptions and ideas occur. It is through them
that desires, aversions and all the other grosser pollutions develop.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>[End of passage from "Maitreya
on Buddha Nature"]</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="An analogy for the relation between conventional and real\dharma"
                           pagetitle="An analogy for the relation between conventional and real\dharma"
                           tocentry="An analogy for the relation between conventional and real\dharma">
               <paragraph>The
_real dharma_ is the actual awakening of the mind. _Conventional dharma_
is what enables this to happen. The whole process is called "transforming
consciousness into wisdom". The superficial +consciousness+ of the mind,
generated by karma and habit, changes every split second and is hypnotically self-preoccupying.
It acts as a veil. As it becomes progressively weakened and removed--by
conventional dharma--then the timeless, unchanging, perfect +wisdom+ and
purity of mind can at last shine through: a little at first and then more and
more until habitual consciousness has been _totally_ replaced by wisdom.  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>We
could compare conventional dharma to the instructions about why and how to draw
back the curtains in a dark room, lit by a dim bulb (ordinary thinking). The
first entry of brilliant sunlight and its subsequent increase, revealing the
room's contents clearly, is like the actual experience of wisdom insight--real
dharma.   </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)We should never underestimate the value
of "real dharma". The Perfection of Wisdom teachings insist, at great length,
on how mere instants of real dharma are worth ages of conventional dharma.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)Although this is so, with the exception
of one person in a billion, a thorough development of conventional dharma is
the condition _sine qua non_ for real dharma to manifest.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)In the Kagyu tradition, +faith and
devotion+ are highly-valued as a prime catalyst of real dharma. Our greatest
contemporary scholar, Khenchen Thrangu Rinpoche, has said, (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)"All the formal teachings
and practices are there for one thing alone: (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)to give us faith."(eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Main\Categories of Dharma_" pagetitle="_Main\Categories of Dharma_"
                     tocentry="_Main\Categories of Dharma_">
            <paragraph>(eh)All the conventional teachings of
dharma fall into two categories, known as _sutra_ and _tantra_.
Please note that when this is the case the word "sutra" has a much broader
meaning than we just saw above:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>"*Sutra*" is a term covering sutra, vinaya
     and abhidharma, i.e. all the Triple Collection. It includes all the
     various teachings and practices of Hinayana and Mahayana Buddhism. One
     could say, simply, "Any Buddhism that could be described through words or
     thought about". Sutra teachings all form part of a graduated +path+
     of practice, leading to enlightenment.</li>
               <li>"*Tantra*<a href="#_ftn7">[5]</a>" is a term
     used to describe something more immediate. It is a direct experience,
     induced by practices which are secret by their very nature, i.e. they only
     make sense to someone whose mind is ready for them. Strictly speaking,
     they are indescribable. Any words which discuss tantra are known as "the
     sutra aspect of tantra'. As tantric (i.e. vajrayana) practices are all
     based upon the idea of awakening to the perfect buddha mind +in the very
     moment+, the idea of following a "path" is actually seen as an obstacle
     to their development.  They form a special aspect of Mahayana, suited to
     only a few and relying absolutely on a powerful working commitment between
     a qualified guru, holding authentic lineage, and a devoted, diligent
     disciple.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)Dharma is often presented as having *three
main components* related to the Threefold Collection:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.     *Right conduct*, of which the Vinaya
teachings on ethics form the basis.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.     *Meditation*, as taught in the
discourses of the Sutra.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.     *Wisdom*, of which the Abhidharma
texts form an important part, as they give us the terminology and definitions
needed for clear intellectual understanding and communication. However, one
must never forget that _deep_ wisdom, as expressed sometimes through the
Sanskrit terms _prajna_ and at any time through _jnana_, is not at
all related to the thinking mind. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Furthermore,
dharma is often described as "profound and vast". This is not just poetic
appreciation:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*_deepdharma refers to the
teachings on voidness: voidness of ego in the Hinayana and voidness of every
thing in the Mahayana. It is also often a codeword for teachings coming through
Nagajuna's tradition. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*_vast_* dharma refers to all the
teachings about cause-and-effect, interdependence etc. They are vast because
they describe all the different worlds of beings and all the stages of the
spiritual path. This is also a codeword for teachings coming through Asanga's
tradition.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="3" title="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching"
               pagetitle="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching"
               tocentry="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching">
         <subsection title="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching"
                     pagetitle="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching"
                     tocentry="The Three Major Phases of the Buddha's Teaching">
            <image width="479"/>
            <paragraph>Having
attained enlightenment, the Buddha did not rush into teaching but remained
silent for weeks<a href="#_ftn8">[6]</a>,
in meditation. That in itself was his first--and a very great--teaching. He did
it to show the profundity of what he had realised; something so deep and
far-reaching that words cannot even begin to convey it. Furthermore, in general
a teaching needs to be given when the time is right, when the listener's mind
is ready, receptive and respectful. When that time comes, the person will be
drawn to the teacher, will relate to the teaching as something really appreciated
and will assume proper responsibility for carrying it through to fruition. The
Buddha needed to test the world's readiness.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>On
behalf of our world, the gods Brahma and Indra are said to have come, made
prostrations and offerings, and requested the Buddha to share his understanding
with the world and to launch it into a major cycle of truth and awakening.
(This cycle is said to last for five thousand years, according to some Buddhist
predictions. We find ourselves living at a truly pivotal time for the planet,
just over halfway through this period, in the sixth of ten 500-year periods.
This is known as the _Time for Virtue_.)  </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
Buddha then went on to teach for some forty-five years, addressing remarkably
varied and sophisticated audiences. India in the 6th century BCE was a land of civilisation
and cultural richness. It was also a place of spiritual intensity, with many
meditative traditions and a sharp intellectual interest in the nature of
reality. Very early on (hard to date this), there were notions comparable to
differential calculus, or perhaps to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mereological_nihilism">mereological nihilism</a>,
speculating upon the nature of the smallest building-blocks composing the universe.
Element theory postulated five universal components being present in all
material things: mass, attraction, energy, motion and space<a href="#_ftn9">[7]</a>. It makes one think of the
physics of this century<a href="#_ftn10">[8]</a>.
Besides teaching great meditators and intellectuals, the Buddha also taught
everyday people and, most importantly, as time went by, the massive community
of thousands of monks, then nuns, who were his followers. In the Mahayana
scriptures, we read of him also teaching beings invisible to us, some of them
from worldly dimensions, such as _devas_ (gods), spirits and the like, and
others from sublime levels as reality, such as the bodhisattvas and
pratyekabuddhas. The latter had already started their journey long ago as
disciples of the previous Buddha: they appeared to Sakyamuni in subtle bodies
of light imperceptible to ordinary humans. Thus his more clairvoyant followers
saw him not just as a human teaching a crowd of disciples but as the living
presence of absolute truth teaching a vast array of beings stretching
throughout space and existing in superposed, parallel worlds.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
retrospect, and based on Asanga's teachings, the Tibetans distinguish *three
major phases in his teachings*. These are known to Buddhists as the _Three
Turning of the Wheel of Dharma_.  "Dharma", the word generally used to
denote the Buddha's teachings, simply means "the way things are"<a href="#_ftn11">[9]</a>. This massive delivery of
universal truths to our world is compared to the turning of a wheel, since
worlds and individuals come round, again and again, time after time, to a recognition
of these truths, in golden ages when great spiritual teachers manifest. This
wheel is the counterpart to another wheel: that of existence. Time and time
again, like a wheel returning to the same point, one finds oneself angry, in
love, crying, fighting, laughing, born, dying. Fortunately, from time to time,
a light pierces through the fabric of worldliness to connect one to the truth
behind its illusions.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
original Sanskrit phrase "turn the wheel of dharma" loses a lot in translation
and had incredibly powerful overtones, giving the impression of a mighty thing
of cosmic significance happening. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\First Turning_" pagetitle="_The\First Turning_"
                     tocentry="_The\First Turning_">
            <paragraph>The
first phase of the Buddha's teachings established the common ground of the
universal truths he had to impart. It is something accessible to almost anyone
who makes enough effort. It reveals much about the nature of worldly existence,
in a way which makes sense to the common perception of reality. Its statements
do not rely on faith and can be confirmed by investigation. The teachings of
this First Turning set out almost all the Buddha's teachings on relative truth<a href="#_ftn12">[10]</a>. Its discussion of absolute
truth is mainly focused on non-ego: the voidness of fixed ideas of personality.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
absolute priority of the First Turning is to eliminate, or at least reduce, suffering--the
bugbear of the universe. Suffering is not viewed as a virtue by Buddhists.
Although it can be turned into one, it has no intrinsic spiritual value in
itself. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Dharma
speaks first and foremost about suffering not because it is a pessimistic, gloomy,
faith but because a tiny amount of suffering can mar a great deal of happiness.
Just as tiny microbes can bring down a whole body, so is suffering spoiling
happiness everywhere. It is through a longing to bring happiness to people that
dharma starts by targeting suffering. Spirituality which does not address
life's chaos and pain can be likened to bringing delicious grapes to somebody
sick but not providing them with the medicine to cure the sickness.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The essence of the First
Turning is contained in the famous *Four Truths*.
The first two truths are a cause-and-result pair dealing with suffering. The
final two truths are a cause-and-result pair dealing with freedom from
suffering. We will explore them in more detail later in this module. Here is
just a summary: (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.     *The first truth concerns
suffering. It explores impermanence, suffering, voidness and no-self and
outlines the Buddhist description of the cosmos* and of the various life forms which
inhabit it, describing in detail their suffering and happiness. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.     *The second truth points to
the causes of the sufferings in the worlds*. Put simply, it says that by not
recognising the true nature of mind, an illusion of persona develops. This
leads to personal needs and desires, aversions, jealousy, pride etc. and these
poison the mind and cause one to act in a way which harms others. Such actions
(_karma_) generate suffering (_samsara_) later for their doer.
 (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.     *The third truth describes nirvana:
the state wherein suffering is no more*. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*4.     **The fourth truth examines* the causes of nirvana--*the
famous "path" of Buddhism, founded in right ethics and conduct, right
meditation and right understanding.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
this First Turning, we encounter the famous *Middle Way* as a description
of the dharma path. At this stage, it is mainly presented as a way of life and
of spiritual practice that avoids the extremes of over-indulgence and
asceticism. This Middle Way was practised by the Buddha, after his earlier
years spent first in utmost luxury and then in asceticism. The Middle Way also
avoids the extremes of projections of soul *(permanence) and negation* (of
karmic consequences).</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\Second Turning_" pagetitle="_The\Second Turning_"
                     tocentry="_The\Second Turning_">
            <paragraph>For
many years, Buddha Sakyamuni taught the way out of suffering and to freedom
from suffering. This involved a host of teachings, methods and the development
of a precise language to analyse and describe the mind and the world. He next introduced
the second phase of his teaching--to many (but not all) disciples; those who had
sufficiently freed their minds and who were ripe for the next step. This phase
is often associated with the caves of Vulture Peak in Rajgir<a href="#_ftn13">[11]</a>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*The first phase emphasised the voidness
of ego* but
described the world in a way that corresponded to the general perception of it
as something existing in its own right. This *second phase unveiled the
voidness of absolutely everything* inner _and_ outer: people _and_
their environment.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Over
the years of the First Turning, the Buddha had established a very complete
scientific and psychological language, enabling all things material and mental
to be clearly defined and distinguished. The extremely fine analysis of mind,
in particular, was the key factor enabling illusions of personal reality to be
understood and evaporated. The eighteen elements of consciousness, the five
aggregates, the twelve gates of perception, the twelve links of
interdependence, the fifty-one mental events, the thirty-seven factors of
enlightenment: these and many other notions became the everyday language and
working reality the Buddha's followers. These later became formalised as _abhidharma_.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the Second Turning, the Buddha revealed all of those key components of mind and
consciousness to be devoid_ of any ultimate reality. Having previously
shown his disciples how to dismantle the ego-illusion machine into its thousand
cogs, he now showed them how even the cogs are illusions, being merely ideas.
The second phase of his teachings is embodied in the _prajnaparamita_ or
Transcendent Perfection of Wisdom. Whereas the first phase spoke to everyone,
the second phase only made sense to those capable of considerable spiritual
maturity.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)In this second phase, the Buddha made
the omnipresence of voidness perfectly clear. Its teachings dismantle all conceptual
illusions of reality and even those of non-reality. However, they do not
elucidate the actual nature of ultimate reality--the buddha mind--beyond the
illusions--other than to point out what was absent. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the Second Turning, the *Middle Way* takes on a second and very profound
meaning, as expounded by Nagarjuna in his Perfection of Wisdom texts: that of
avoiding the four limits and the eight extremes. This will be explained in a
later module. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
the deconstruction of all illusions is a powerful and delicate process, it
requires outstanding compassion. This is needed for the work on oneself and for
the way in which one regards other sentient beings. The keynote of the Second
Phase is the omnipresence of compassion and the absolute need for compassion if
one wishes to attain the Buddha's enlightenment. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\Third Turning_" pagetitle="_The\Third Turning_"
                     tocentry="_The\Third Turning_">
            <paragraph>(eh)Once the meaning of voidness, as
expounded in the second phase, was well comprehended, the third phase of the
Buddha's teaching revealed the actual nature of ultimate voidness. This is not
simply an _absence_ of illusion. It is not _merely an emptiness_. It
is not vast, virgin space. On the contrary, it is the total, perfect _presence_
of the love, compassion, wisdom, powers and all the other qualities of
enlightenment. It is an _affirmation_, as opposed to the _negations_
of the other two "turnings". Most importantly, the Buddha taught that
every single sentient being has this ultimate voidness as his, her or its true
nature. Thus the Third Turning of the Wheel of Dharma teaches _buddha nature_,
the fact that the wisdom and perfection of enlightenment is profoundly present
in everyone, all the time.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Following
this, over the centuries, various learned and enlightened teachers wrote treaties--_shastra_--on
_buddha nature_. Maitreya's work--_the mahayana uttara tantra shastra_,
translated in English with commentary as "Maitreya on Buddha Nature" (see
bibliography at end)--is the greatest of these classics. It is the reference for
all the Tibetan traditions, as well as for Mahayana traditions in China, Korea
and Japan.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="A simple but effective introduction to the term &#34;voidness&#34;"
                           pagetitle="A simple but effective introduction to the term &#34;voidness&#34;"
                           tocentry="A simple but effective introduction to the term &#34;voidness&#34;">
               <paragraph>The
Sanskrit term _shunyata_ translates as _voidness_ or _emptiness_.
Both English words, and particularly the latter, conjure up visions of hollow,
empty space. To hear of someone "meditating in voidness" conjures up images of
absorption in vast, silent, cosmic spaces. However, such notions do not at all
convey the real meaning of the term _shunyata,_ which describe a clarity,
a wisdom, an awareness that pierces through mind's illusions. It is called _voidness_
because it sees the illusions as being "null-and-void"; devoid of the reality
they seem to have had.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Let
us take, for example, the phrase _the voidness of ego--_something taught in
all traditions of Buddhism. This is not talking about some quality of ego, in
the same way one might speak about _the sweetness of this cake_. It is not
saying that ego _exists_ but that somehow it is spacious and open. The
teachings show us that ego only exists as an illusion: some thing imagined.
That illusion does not correspond to reality. We can imagine Mount Fujiyama in
the centre of Paris but when we check it out, no Mount Fuji is found there.
Hence, investigation shows mind's imaginary projections of "I" and "me" to be
null-and-void. Realising the voidness our projections, illusions, delusions
etc. is the heart of Buddhist wisdom. We could say, "Realisation of voidness is
wisdom" but this is usually shortened to _voidness is wisdom_. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*_Voidness_** means _wisdom_*: very profound wisdom that
sees through the habitual illusions. It sees them to be devoid_ of<a href="#_ftn14">[12]</a> the reality they seem to
have. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>To
look at a mirage but +know+ that there is no water really present on the
horizon is a simple form of voidness-wisdom. Wisdom understands the movements
of light and knows what is happening. It informs us that there is no water,
even though the eyes tell us otherwise. The "voidness" of what seems to be a
distant shimmering lake is the wisdom in the mind of the watcher, no longer
tricked by delusion. But note, this wisdom does not in any way make the mirage
disappear. The optical effect continues exactly as before but now that it is
accompanied by wisdom, one's appreciation of what is there is different. It
saves an awful lot of useless trudging across the sand, to assuage a thirst!</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)In another way, voidness is very much
to do with limitlessness. It is the wisdom of an unlimited, free mind that is
not deluded by one or another limited view. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Once
the limiting illusion goes, there is usually a limitlessness. For instance, the
idea of a single, lasting self--some monolithic identity that lasts a
lifetime--is dissolved in Buddhism by a fine analysis of what a human being
really is--an infinitely complex, stream of components, the consciousness of
which changes every split-second.  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Furthermore,
any person's experience of a specific thing is necessarily +dependent+
upon many +limiting+ factors.  Humans see what humans see and hear what
humans hear. Dogs or bats hear things we cannot. Our senses are very limited.
The messages conveyed to the brain by the senses are severely filtered and then
immediately linked with memories which colour the perception. And so on and so
forth. Each of us has a unique and +highly subjective+ appreciation of
reality. Yet in each person's mind,* that appreciation seems to be reality
itself and is taken as such*.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>This
perception of reality is heavily coloured by past karma. Three people in the
same place can find it heaven, hell or indifferent respectively, depending upon
the state of their mind. The state of mind is the consequence of past karma. A
man with rare and expensive fish in his pond may look at them with great pride
and see them primarily as a beautiful possession. A passing heron may view them
as food. Another species of fish may jealously consider it as ugly; not
beautiful at all. The fish will feel like itself, neither a possession nor a
meal. A worm in the fish's stomach may just experience it as warmth and a
certain smell. A passing deva may see the fish as a n~ga. A neurotic spirit may see it as a
vicious sea-serpent. Which one is the real fish?</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Any
thing is infinitely more than simply the limited impression of it which a
sentient being perceive. Its infinite possibilities, and actualities, render
void our feeling that the thing _is only _what we at first perceive it to
be. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)Voidness means the wisdom that
recognises the difference between what _seems to be_ and what _really is_.
That "really is" cannot be just a different limited impression, an alternative
mental definition, another finite idea. It has to be infinite. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>It
is by applying the wisdom of voidness--as the piercing of illusions--that:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·     
The
First Turning teachings destroy delusions (projections) of self.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·     
The
Second Turning destroys projections of concrete reality and thereby stimulates
great compassion for those still deluded and (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)·     
The
Third Turning removes delusions about voidness itself and reveals authentic
reality as the changeless, eternal awakened (buddha) mind(eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="4" title="The Dharma After&#xA;the Buddha's Passing"
               pagetitle="The Dharma After&#xA;the Buddha's Passing"
               tocentry="The Dharma After&#xA;the Buddha's Passing">
         <subsection title="The Dharma After\the Buddha's Passing"
                     pagetitle="The Dharma After\the Buddha's Passing"
                     tocentry="The Dharma After\the Buddha's Passing">
            <image width="479"/>
            <paragraph>In
a later module, we will look in more detail into the development of dharma in
India and Tibet. There are some things however that it is good to know from the
start and which will be mentioned briefly here. <a href="#timeline">Annexe 1</a>
gives a simple timeline.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\Councils_" pagetitle="_The\Councils_" tocentry="_The\Councils_">
            <paragraph>We
saw in the first module that the custom at the time of the Buddha was to learn
the teachings by heart and that the Buddhist community spent its summer rainy
retreat in part repeating and learning the teachings. There were several major
meetings of the sangha to discuss and determine the exact content of the
Buddha's teachings. They are known as _Councils_:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The
     First Council, held three months after the Buddha's passing, i.e. 544 BCE<a href="#_ftn15">[13]</a>
               </li>
               <li>The
     Second Council, held approximately a century after the Buddha's passing.</li>
               <li>The
     Third Council in 250 BCE.</li>
               <li>The
     Fourth Councils, one (recognised by Theravadins) in Sri Lanka around 30
     BCE and another (recognised by Mahayanists) in North-West India around 100
     CE.</li>
            </list>
            <subsubsection title="The First Council" pagetitle="The First Council"
                           tocentry="The First Council">
               <image width="212"/>
               <paragraph>This
was convened by the elder Mahakasyapa and sponsored by the king Ajatashatru,
who erected a building in front of the Sattapanni cave in Rajgir (right, Bihar
state, India). It took place three months after the Buddha's passing, due to
Mahakasyapa's concerns about the monastic discipline (_vinaya_) crumbling
if it were not properly codified. It was attended by 500 fully-liberated monks
(_Arhants_). Under the guidance of the greatest expert on vinaya at the
time--Upali, who received the direct transmission of vinaya from the Buddha--the
rules for lay and monastic Buddhists were established.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Under
the Buddha's cousin, Ananda--who of all the sangha had accompanied and served
the Buddha the longest and who had the gift of total recall--the general
teachings the dharma were established. Nothing was written down but the _vinaya_
and _dharma_ were learnt by heart. Together they took seven months to be
recited, beginning to end.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Second Council" pagetitle="The Second Council"
                           tocentry="The Second Council">
               <paragraph>This
took place in Vesali, also in Bihar. It was to settle a hot dispute which grew
up concerning the minor rules for monastics. It was also to do with flexibility
and the question of which minor rules the Buddha had considered dispensable, in
certain circumstances. The main question was about whether monks or nuns could
carry money. The outcome was a decision to stick strictly to all the minor
rules.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Third Council" pagetitle="The Third Council"
                           tocentry="The Third Council">
               <paragraph>This
Council is only mentioned in the Theravadin tradition. It was convened in 250
BCE under the great emperor Ashoka, the first king to unite much of India. He
had converted to Buddhism and his brother had attained arhantship. His
extraordinary generosity to Buddhism (he is said to have constructed 84,000
Buddhist temples and monastic dwellings) led to corrupt people donning robes
and exploiting the system. This council was convened to deal with corruption
issues arising from this. One of the great outcomes of Ashoka's reign, and
arguably of this council, was the sending forth of great Buddhist masters
(those who knew the dharma thoroughly by heart) to foreign countries, including
Greece<a href="#_ftn16">[14]</a>,
many Himalayan kingdoms and what are now Sri Lanka and Myanmar. The Theravadins
hold that some things were written down at this time, in a text called the _Katthavattu_,
in twenty-three chapters discussing issues raised during the Council.  </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Sri Lankan Fourth Council" pagetitle="The Sri Lankan Fourth Council"
                           tocentry="The Sri Lankan Fourth Council">
               <paragraph>This
was held in  Tambapanni, Sri Lanka, in 29 BCE under the patronage of King
Vattagamani and lasted for three years. Severe loss of life, due to drought in
Sri Lanka, had threatened the continuity of the oral tradition by which the
Buddha's teachings had been remembered and passed down for some five centuries.
It was decided to commit the teachings to writing and this gave the world the
famous Pali<a href="#_ftn17">[15]</a>
Canon, the earliest Buddhist scriptures, written on palm leaves, held together
by string to make books. Copies of these were taken to other Buddhist
countries, such as Myanmar, Laos and Thailand.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Indian Fourth Council" pagetitle="The Indian Fourth Council"
                           tocentry="The Indian Fourth Council">
               <paragraph>This
was convened by the Kushan emperor Kanishka, either in Jallandar<a href="#_ftn18">[16]</a> or in nearby Kashmir.
Although various abhidharma lineages had appeared by this time, it was during
this council that ideas<a href="#_ftn19">[17]</a>
concerning _abhidharma_ (the Buddhist science of mind and matter) were
codified by a team of five hundred scholars under the guidance of a certain
Vasumitra. This is recounted in early Mahayana texts, describing the
Sarvastivadin refutations of abhidharma as codified in the Great Discourse (_Mahavibasha_).
Sarvastivadin does not exist today as an indepndent school but its ideas on
abhidharma were taken up by Mahayana schools. The codification is said to have
taken twelve years, covering three hundred thousand verses and some nine
million statements. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>It
also seems that this was a defining moment in language, as the early Prakrit
(vernacular) texts were rendered into Sanskrit from then on. Sanskrit had been
a "high" language reserved for Brahmins at the time of the Buddha, who had
insisted that teachings be given in local, common, dialects so as to be
accessible to all. Now, some six centuries later and in a much-changed society,
Sanskrit was seen by Mahayanists to be the best vehicle for writing down the
ancient instructions. Theravadins stuck by the original ruling from the Buddha
and maintained their scriptures in the commoners' Pali.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\Development of Mahayana_" pagetitle="_The\Development of Mahayana_"
                     tocentry="_The\Development of Mahayana_">
            <paragraph>The
truth is that little is known for sure of the history of this. We will consider
Indian Buddhist history and its main teachers in a later module. Here are some
key points:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>Mahayanists
     themselves see their teachings as going right back to the historical
     Buddha and believe in the Three Turnings, as explained above. Theravadins
     do not agree. They only accept the First Turning and see Mahayanists as
     breakaway groups wanting to add their own interpretations and developments
     to the original teachings.</li>
               <li>The
     earliest Mahayana writings appeared between the 1st century BCE and the
     2nd century CE. These include such famous works as the Perfection of
     Wisdom (_prajnaparamita_), Lotus Sutra, Nirvana Sutra etc.
     Mahayanists believe that the Buddha gave these teachings during his lifetime,
     in places such as the Vulture Peak at Rajgir, and that many of the
     Buddha's followers were either not ready for them--and so were led
     elsewhere by their karma when the teachings were given--or else thought
     they had already heard everything to be heard from the Buddha and so
     excused themselves when he started to teach them.<a href="#_ftn20">[18]</a> Until they
     were written down, they were either preserved as an oral tradition or else
     secreted away, in writing, in other realms, such as the Perfection of
     Wisdom texts, guarded for some six centuries by _naga_ serpent
     spirits and recovered by Nagarjuna.</li>
               <li>Mahayana
     became dominant in India from the 5th to the 10th centuries CE.</li>
               <li>The
     two immensely-important Buddhist masters whose own writings and whose
     disciples' writings give us the main content of Mahayana were Nagarjuna
     and Asanga.</li>
               <li>Nagarjuna
     was born in either the 1st or 2nd century CE. The Mahayana tradition
     stemming from him is known as "the deep one" and he is famous for his
     extensive explanations of the Perfection of Wisdom.</li>
               <li>Asanga
     was born around 300 CE. The tradition stemming from him is known as "the
     vast one", as his five great _shastra_ give much detailed information
     about the path. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>**</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Vajrayana\Buddhism_" pagetitle="_Vajrayana\Buddhism_"
                     tocentry="_Vajrayana\Buddhism_">
            <paragraph>We
will explore Vajrayana Buddhism in much more detail in the third study year.
For now, here are some key points:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>It
     means the way, or vehicle, (_yana_) of that which is indestructible (_vajra_).
     This refers to the timeless, perfect, indestructible buddha mind, or
     buddha nature. The vajrayana teachings help one connect with that in the
     present moment. It is also called _tantra_, which means "thread" in
     Sanskrit. This refers to the continuous, unbroken, thread of buddha mind
     which accompanies the deluded mind every second, throughout the illusion
     of samsara, yet remains unrecognised. The point of these teachings is to
     recognise it.</li>
               <li>Tibetan
     masters say that some vajrayana lineages started at the time of Sakyamuni
     Buddha, principally the instructions he gave to King Indrabhuti.</li>
               <li>The
     first vajrayana _texts_ appeared around the 5th century CE but
     vajrayana had doubtless existed as a highly-secret, oral tradition,
     practised in forests and mountains by small groups of yogis for many
     centuries before it entered the monasteries, where its teachings became
     "tamer" and integrated with the monastic round, giving rise to the texts.
     It is likely that there was already a thriving vajrayana at the time of
     Asanga, since we know that his epoch was a time of opening for the
     monasteries. It seems to have become more common for the studious monks to
     go off to the jungles and for great siddhas<a href="#_ftn21">[19]</a> to be
     invited to teach in monasteries.</li>
               <li>The
     vajrayana flourished in India from the 7th through to 12th centuries in
     India. After that time, most Buddhist traditions disappeared, due to a
     violent rise of foreign Islamic invasions and local Hinduism.</li>
               <li>Vajrayana
     went to Tibet in two great waves: the _ancient transmission_
     (Nyingma) in the 8th century, with Guru Rinpoche (Padmasambhava) and the
     other during the 11th and early 12th centuries with the founders of the
     "new traditions" (Sarma). Eight great traditions were transported to Tibet
     by both Indian and Tibetan masters. They are known as the Eight Great
     Chariots.</li>
            </list>
            <subsubsection title="&#34;Tibetan Buddhism&#34;" pagetitle="&#34;Tibetan Buddhism&#34;"
                           tocentry="&#34;Tibetan Buddhism&#34;">
               <paragraph>This
term makes a lot of superficial sense--as we compare it with Japanese or Thai
Buddhism-- but it also makes it sound as though Tibet developed its own
Buddhism, which is not really the case. From the 8th through to 12th centuries
CE, both Tibetan and Indian masters transplanted the +Indian Buddhism+ of
that period across the Himalaya to Tibet, in a very complete way. Tibet
received the broadest, most comprehensive "package" of Buddhism--more than any
other country. In the wealth of its literature and techniques, one finds the
overall picture of what otherwise is found only in parts other countries. It was
the only country to preserve  a living wealth of vajrayana.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Conclusion" pagetitle="Conclusion" tocentry="Conclusion">
               <paragraph>The
way in which our lamas tend to view the development of dharma in India, from
the time of _nirmanakaya _Buddha Sakyamuni until its disappearance in the
13th century, 1800 years later, is as follows. The Buddha Sakyamuni taught all
levels during his lifetime: Hinayana, Mahayana and Vajrayana. The Mahayana and
Vajrayana continued as secret traditions until this world was ready for them to
be spread at large. As that happened, the _sambhogakaya_  buddha-mind
either emanated as great teachers or else directly inspired great teachers, who
composed the various Mahayana shastras and the tantras.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>If
we consider this cosmically, rather than historically, the universe is vast and
multi-dimensional. The pure buddha mind is the constant backdrop to its
ever-changing fabric. Whenever someone is truly ready, for whichever level of
teaching it be, that buddha mind will appear in their existence, guiding and
teaching them.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>**</paragraph>
               <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Sutra and Shastra" pagetitle="Sutra and Shastra"
                           tocentry="Sutra and Shastra">
               <paragraph>During
his forty-five years of teaching, the Buddha gave many detailed explanations
about all sorts of topics. These were mostly taught in response to questions,
in this place or that place, sometimes simply and sometimes profoundly.
Everything recorded of the Buddha's own teachings fills over one hundred thick
volumes of Tibetan scripture, in a collection known as the *_Kanjur_*(_bka 'gyur_), which means "Sacred Instruction Translated". If we take
a typical topic--such as karma--we will find various teachings on it scattered
throughout the hundred volumes. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Therefore
we can understand the value of the tremendous work accomplished by the greatest
Buddhist masters, such as Nagarjuna, Asanga and their disciples, in compiling
information on key topics and presenting it to us as a coherent whole. They
themselves had encyclopaedic understanding of the Kanjur and had clear,
enlightened minds. The works they composed were not commentaries
properly-speaking, on the Buddha's teachings, as a commentary usually takes original
verses and elaborates on them, word by word, meaning by meaning. They were
brilliant analytical presentations. We call them _shastra_ and call the
Buddha's own teachings _sutra_. The traditional collection of the great _shastra_
in Tibetan translation is known as the *_Tenjur_* (_bstan 'gyur_),
meaning "shastras translated". It has more than two hundred volumes.</paragraph>
               <table class="MsoNormalTable">
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*_Buddhas in Buddhist ArtIt
  is interesting to note that the historical Buddha Sakyamuni was not
  represented by statues or paintings until at least four centuries after his
  passing, when the influence of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greco-Buddhist_art">Greco-Buddhist art</a>
  and the Gandhara style swept across Buddhist Asia, bringing a whole new
  iconography. During those first centuries, the undefinable presence of the
  Buddha was represented as footprints, an empty seat, a stupa, a bodhi tree or
  a wheel.</td>
                        <td>
                           <img width="227" align="left" src="module2_files/image007.png"/>_Jataka
  story fresco, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ajanta">Ajanta caves</a>_</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <img width="202" align="left" src="module2_files/image008.png"/>_The
  Ajanta caves, Maharashtra State, India_</td>
                        <td>The
  earliest images found in caves, just centuries after the Buddha, depict him
  anthropomorphically only in his former lives, as a bodhisattva, but not in
  his life as Prince Gautama.  This
  is indeed a token of the inconceivable presence of the Buddha. The people in
  those first centuries of Buddhism did not have stereotype images of a Buddha
  in their mind but instead a notion of formless presence of love and wisdom,
  appearing differently to each person, as needed; something beyond the
  imagination. </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="5" title="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised"
               pagetitle="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised"
               tocentry="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised">
         <subsection title="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised"
                     pagetitle="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised"
                     tocentry="The First Turning &amp; The Four Truths of the Realised">
            <image width="479"/>
            <paragraph>Before
we enter into the details of this topic, there are a few odd points to clear
up.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_&#34;Noble&#34;\Truths &amp; &#34;Noble&#34; Eightfold Path_"
                     pagetitle="_&#34;Noble&#34;\Truths &amp; &#34;Noble&#34; Eightfold Path_"
                     tocentry="_&#34;Noble&#34;\Truths &amp; &#34;Noble&#34; Eightfold Path_">
            <paragraph>This
way of translating the Truths and the Path is found almost everywhere in
Buddhist texts. It sounds dignified but, according to Tibetans, is not quite true
to the original meaning of the _noble_ in those ideas. The original
Sanskrit _arya_, and later the Tibetan _'phags pa_, are not adjectives
describing the Truths or the Path as "noble" but words telling us that the Four
Truths are understood clearly only by "noble beings",  _aryas_,  meaning
those who have transcended worldly rebirth forever. Likewise it is the
eightfold path followed by such saintly beings. Noble beings means: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>Arhats
     (those who have attained nirvana), in the Hinayana systems, and </li>
               <li>Great
     bodhisattvas (who have constant realisation of voidness), in the Mahayana
     system. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)*The Eightfold Path of the Realised
consists of:*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*Right view (i.e. wisdom)*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right thought.*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right speech.*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right action.*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right livelihood.*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right effort.*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right mindfulness and*(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Right meditative absorption.*(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>When
we study in detail the various stages of the path to liberation, it becomes
clear that the full penetration of those Four Truths is the defining moment
when one leaves worldliness for saintliness. From that time onwards _only_,
until total enlightenment, one treads "the eightfold path of the noble ones'.
Its eight aspects all depend upon the first of the eight--right view--and this is
_only_ acquired at that exalted stage of development, because there is then
authentic insight into true reality.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>For
this reason, you will find in this course that we say _Four Truths of the
Realised_ and _Eightfold Path of the Realised_. The Theravadin
tradition places tremendous emphasis on a version of the Eightfold Path adapted
for everyone and not dependent upon the person practising it having authentic
insight into reality. The "eightfold" formulation in Mahayana Buddhism is
reserved for the saintly stages of the path.    </paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The famous &#34;First Teaching&#34;[20] of the\Buddha"
                           pagetitle="The famous &#34;First Teaching&#34;[20] of the\Buddha"
                           tocentry="The famous &#34;First Teaching&#34;[20] of the\Buddha">
               <paragraph>Many
Buddhists will say that the very first teaching that the Buddha gave was that
of the Four Noble Truths, as preserved in the _Dharmachakra Sutra_ (Pali
translation in <a href="#wheel">Annexe II</a> at end of this Module) and that
he gave it to the five former ascetics, who were his first five disciples. He
actually taught two other people--the laymen merchants Tapussu and Bhalluka--before
meeting up again with the group of five, so the latter were not technically the
first disciples but they were the first to become monks. The earliest texts do
not mention the Dharmachakra Sutra as such but say that the Buddha would teach
some of the five disciples while the others went off to beg for food for the six
of them. The five learned in a sort of rota. It seems that the essence of what
the Buddha taught them during this period was later summed up apocryphally as
the Dharmachakra Sutra.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\Role of the Four Truths of the Realised_"
                     pagetitle="_The\Role of the Four Truths of the Realised_"
                     tocentry="_The\Role of the Four Truths of the Realised_">
            <paragraph>The
Truths were much more than merely the first of a series of teachings:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
They
cover all the teachings, as everything else can be considered as a development
of the details of the Truths.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
They
give us the main "message" of the Buddha and show us how its very fibre differs
from that of most religions.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The All-Embracing Nature of the Four Truths"
                           pagetitle="The All-Embracing Nature of the Four Truths"
                           tocentry="The All-Embracing Nature of the Four Truths">
               <paragraph>(eh)*Anything, anywhere can be assigned to
one of two areas of reality: _samsara_ or _nirvana_:*(eeh)</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)*_samsara_* is the name we give to
     the worldly mind and to all the "outer" experiences of the worldly mind,
     i.e. the environment, other beings of the six realms (described later in
     this module). It is deluded and it suffers. The Tibetan, _'khor ba_,
     means "what goes round and round", referring to the repetitive
     and self-perpetuating nature of anger, passion and the like.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)*_nirvana_* is the name given to
     freedom from the worldly mind. +This is not a specific "state" with its
     own definite characteristics+: simply freedom from samsara--freedom from
     delusion and suffering. That's all! There are many sorts of nirvana, depending
     upon the qualities present in that freedom. (eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>(eh)For Buddhists, +there is nothing in
heaven, on Earth or elsewhere that it not included somewhere in these two+.
The Four Truths are all-embracing because they are a vivid and complete
description of samsara and nirvana (Truths 1 and 3), explaining the causes of
each (Truths 2 and 4):(eeh)</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)The *Truth of Suffering*
     describes samsara, explaining its six main states (humans, animals etc.),
     their world-systems, life-spans, joys, sufferings, its beings' faculties
     and so forth. In particular, it pinpoints three main levels of suffering
     innate to these existences. (eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)The *Truth of the Cause of
     Suffering* explains how the experiences of samsara come about. The
     immediate cause is _karma_. Karma is caused by a _defiled mind_.
     Defilement is caused by _deluded thinking_. Such thinking comes from _ignorance_.
     The way all these fit together is described through _interdependence_.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)The *Truth of Cessation*
     describes nirvana, i.e. the _peace_ and _liberation_ achieved
     when samsara is annihilated.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)The *Truth of the Path*
     explains the interdependence of liberation: how an ethical life,
     meditation practice and wisdom development lead first to liberation and
     then to the perfect qualities of a Buddha.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>(eh)Thus the first two truths are the
effect-and-cause of samsara and the last two truths are the effect-and-cause of
nirvana. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Four Truths as the Defining Message of Dharma"
                           pagetitle="The Four Truths as the Defining Message of Dharma"
                           tocentry="The Four Truths as the Defining Message of Dharma">
               <paragraph>Humankind
has developed many religions and philosophies. They each have their own
explanations of life's meaning, purpose and possibilities. Some believe their
teachings came directly from a divine creator and that our purpose is to serve
that creator. Some believe in an after-life whereas others insist that
consciousness ceases totally at physical death. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)Buddhism differs from most faiths. It
has neither God nor abstract ideals as its central focus but a very real
emancipation of suffering. All the teachings are there for that purpose: not to
help us serve the Buddha or to follow his teachings simply because he said we
should; not for personal ecstasy or for power or even to satiate our intellect's
curiosity about existence but to help us understand, confront and relieve
suffering. This means dealing _in very real terms_ with the suffering both
in oneself and in others and to work positively to bring happiness to the
world. More than that, dharma is seen as the way to plant the seeds of
long-term future happiness in the world and to create a wiser and more
harmonious society. It is the way to find the highest happiness "beyond the
world": that of an enlightened mind. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Four Seals of Dharma" pagetitle="The Four Seals of Dharma"
                           tocentry="The Four Seals of Dharma">
               <paragraph>(eh)There is such a vast wealth of wisdom
and technique in dharma that it would be easy to misunderstand it or to misuse
it to selfish or harmful ends. To be sure that a teaching has the true "seal"
of dharma, we have four traditional guidelines known as the 'four seals of
dharma". They are:(eeh)</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)*All composite things are
     impermanent.*
     A "composite thing" (also known as a "compound" or "compounded
     phenomenon") is something which comes into being through various causes
     and conditions. (eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)*All that is tainted involves
     suffering*.
     "Tainted" generally means tainted by self-centredness and the pride,
     anger, sense of territory etc. linked to ego. In Mahayana Buddhism, it has
     a finer definition of taint through taking dualistic perceptions as
     reality.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)*Nirvana is peace.* "Peace" in this sense
     means the true end of all delusions of self and their associated
     defilements. (eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)*All things are devoid of
     self-entity*.
     In the Hinayana teachings this is mainly applied to sentient beings, whose
     projections of themselves do not tally with what they really are. In the
     Mahayana it refers to any thing and everything, demonstrating how nothing
     truly is what it at first appears to be. (eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>This
means that if in our own minds, or in something we read or hear taught, there
seems to be a Buddhist teaching denying voidness of self-entity, or explaining
the total happiness of what is tainted etc., we should be very suspicious
indeed!</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Some General Comments about the First Turning of the\Dharma-Wheel"
                     pagetitle="Some General Comments about the First Turning of the\Dharma-Wheel"
                     tocentry="Some General Comments about the First Turning of the\Dharma-Wheel">
            <paragraph>It is
the common ground of all Buddhism. It was taught at length and in detail by the
Enlightened One to a general public. Its teachings are recognised and practised
by almost all schools of Buddhism. They deal practically with tangible things:
life at it is, the mind as we can observe it and they expound a set of "natural
ethics" based upon respect for life and non-violence, generosity of spirit and
self-mastery. The main focus is on the reduction and eventually the total
elimination of suffering. This first turning addresses two sorts of audience
through its two aspects of truth:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The
     *relative truth* aspect of its teachings outlines the processes of
     cause-and-effect which weave the very fabric of existence. They show how a
     person's actions (_karma_) will determine their happiness or
     suffering in future lives. The wholesome acts, known as "virtue", generate
     happiness. "Non-virtue" generates suffering. By avoiding
     non-virtue and practising virtue, anyone can expect his or her future
     lives to be better and hence this aspect of the teachings can readily and
     willingly be put into practice by anyone, according to their capacity. </li>
            </list>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The
     *ultimate truth* aspect of its teachings points to the total illusion
     of notions of self or personality and the fact that any worldly existence
     is a prison-like suffering compared with nirvana. This aspect of the
     teachings can only really be applied by renunciates, willing to abandon a
     personal, worldly existence and able to practice meditation. Within the
     peaceful stability of meditation, their thoughts and feelings can be
     worked with in the light of wisdom.    </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>Thus,
throughout the Buddhist world, there are monasteries and nunneries peopled by
renunciates and towns and villages with lay populations dedicated to pure
ethics, especially those of generosity and respect for life.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Some
other brief points about the teachings of the Buddha's First Turning:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>It
     taught the equality of all beings and was revolutionary in India, which at
     the time was a land of many kingdoms nearly all practising a caste system
     with therefore enormous gaps in social and religious privilege.</li>
               <li>It
     allowed women into its religious order. This did not happen in the other
     faiths of the time.</li>
               <li>It
     was revolutionary inasmuch as it had no gods or godhead to be worshipped
     or served and neither did it attribute divine purpose to "creation".</li>
               <li>It
     gave the world one of its earliest and most complete systems of analysing
     and understanding the human mind.  </li>
            </list>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="6" title="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering"
               pagetitle="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering"
               tocentry="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering">
         <subsection title="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering"
                     pagetitle="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering"
                     tocentry="The First Truth of the Realised: The Truth of Suffering">
            <image width="470"/>
            <paragraph>We
shall examine this in six ways:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The
     essential point: samsara is suffering.</li>
               <li>A
     classical approach through the four key points of this truth.</li>
               <li>An
     analysis of the three types of suffering.</li>
               <li>A
     survey of the cosmos, according to Buddhism.</li>
               <li>The
     six categories of beings.</li>
               <li>A
     brief look at what a sentient being is: the five _skandha_.</li>
            </list>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\essential point: samsara is suffering_"
                     pagetitle="_The\essential point: samsara is suffering_"
                     tocentry="_The\essential point: samsara is suffering_">
            <paragraph>The Tibetan word<a href="#_ftn23">[21]</a> for _samsara_ means, "what goes
on and on and on..." or else "what goes round and round and round ..." In fact, it means what will
go on endlessly, as a sort of self-perpetuating mechanism, unless something is
done to stop it. It refers to the ignorance, confusion, illusions and other
harmful things in the mind, which lead into ego-centred realities. There is the
struggle for affection, recognition and companionship; the sexual drive; the
wish for power and there is also a habitual self-centredness and fear which
stifles altruism. All of those things (and many others which we will look at in
next month's module) cause us to +act+. Action, in Sanskrit, is _karma_.
</paragraph>
            <paragraph>According to the Buddha's teachings, what we do now--the
_karma_ we create now--determines what will become of us in the future and
in future lives. What we are now, and the world as we experience it, each
uniquely, is the result of what we did in the past. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The crucial point is this: no one _wants_ to
suffer, people want happiness. The problem is ignorance, because in trying to
find happiness, people create sufferings they never intended. They create suffering for
others, in the short term, and for themselves in the long term, through the
play of karma. They simply do not know enough about life's immutable causal
mechanisms or about the nature of change: impermanence. There is a further
level to add to this: each person's samsara is a very sorry sate of affairs
compared with how their mind could be, if only they knew what was possible. The
price of fleeting happiness in this world is disproportional and almost always
entails considerable suffering. All the Buddha's life and teachings are about
reducing and getting rid of this unnecessary suffering forever.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Of
course, there are many wholesome, useful things in the mind too: a sense of
ethics, selfless generosity, love of truth etc. These are not a problem. The
guideline is this: +whatever has the "I" thought at its heart leads to a
perpetuation of samsara and hence to suffering+.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_A\classical approach to the truth of suffering_"
                     pagetitle="_A\classical approach to the truth of suffering_"
                     tocentry="_A\classical approach to the truth of suffering_">
            <paragraph>In
the more technical treatises on the Four Truths, each truth is developed
through four key topics, making sixteen in all<a href="#_ftn24">[22]</a>.
These are especially important in Theravada Buddhism, as it is realisation of
these which constitutes the insight aspect of their enlightenment. The key
topics for this First Truth are:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>Impermanence.</li>
               <li>Suffering
     itself.</li>
               <li>Voidness.</li>
               <li>No-self.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>*_Impermanence_*, explained briefly here,will be developed in
detail in Module 9. It is defined as being the instability that is the very
nature of any _composite phenomenon_, i.e. +anything+ that arises due
to the coming-together of prime causes and secondary conditions. Based on the famous
saying found in the _Collection of Aphorisms,_ Gampopa sums it up:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>What
is accumulated will eventually dwindle, what is built up will eventually
disintegrate, what comes together eventually will part and what lives
eventually will die.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Suffering_*-- _in
its three aspects and in terms of its manifestation in the six realms--will be
developed immediately below in considerable detail. The suffering of
samsara is defined as an inability to satisfy and an unexpected sting<a href="#_ftn25">[23]</a>. Here, we will connect it
with the previous point, impermanence. Everything changes. Nothing lasts. Thus,
whenever someone clings--to health, youth, beauty, their parents, children,
status, reputation, lovers or whatever impermanent thing gives them
happiness--there will be suffering when that person or thing changes or
disappears. The more one clings, the more there is suffering through the pain
of loss. Furthermore, much harmful karma is created in trying to resist
inevitable change.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Voidness_*
is defined as the actual true nature of the illusory things through which one
suffers. In its simplest and most universal explanation of this point, the
people and things through which one suffers are demonstrated to be, on an
absolute level, no more than a momentary concatenation of atoms. What we perceive
is a gross, very partial, frozen image based on the dance of those atoms.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_No-selfis
defined similarly to the above but is related to the perceiving mind; the
illusory, suffering mind. On a level of absolute truth, there is no sufferer
but merely a sequence of separate moments of consciousness. The frames of a
cinema film are each an individual image yet when they run one after another
they give an impression of a single, lasting reality. Likewise, the
split-second moments of minds consciousness, cognition and so forth give the
impression of a lasting self, of a "person" who suffers. No such self can ever
be found. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>These
two topics of voidness and no-self will be developed Module 4.   </paragraph>
            <paragraph>**</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Three\levels of suffering_" pagetitle="_Three\levels of suffering_"
                     tocentry="_Three\levels of suffering_">
            <paragraph>(eh)This topic is very important, as it reveals
why suffering is at the heart of Buddhist teaching. In dharma, "suffering" is
not restricted to the physical and mental difficulties that the word at first
suggests.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*Suffering as suffering*: this is when mind or
     body or both feel pain. It is the obvious suffering and usually the only
     sort of suffering people think of when they hear the word "suffering". (eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Suffering through change*: besides the suffering
     through impermanence described in the previous section, there is a major
     aspect of suffering through change that is related to karma and ignorance.
     To the uninformed eye, it does not look like suffering. In fact, it often
     appears like someone having a good time. However, the very things that are
     being done, to have that "good time", are setting in motion mechanisms of
     suffering. An extreme example would be someone enjoying hurting another
     being, like a hunter enjoying a day in the forest shooting deer. In that
     particular case, it may be the highlight of the person's week: their
     greatest happiness and something to really look forward to. Yet, through
     the inevitable cosmic laws of cause-and-effect, taught by the Buddha, we
     know that the hunter will be reborn to suffer tremendously, physically, on
     account of such acts. The sufferings will be immeasurably greater than the
     fleeting moments of pleasure enjoyed while shooting. 
     Many everyday actions that people perform--from spraying the bugs on their
     roses to cheating the taxman--fall into this category, which can be defined
     as creating the karma of suffering through actions intended to bring
     pleasure or to combat the unpleasant.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Suffering of the Composite*. This third stage of
     suffering is only known to very pure beings. From the beauty, liberation,
     wisdom, peace and innate, selfless love of their state of mind, the whole
     of regular existence--even when it is at its best--is a dark, limited state
     of affairs. Such noble beings, _arya_, see that to ignore the
     liberated state is in itself a tremendous suffering.(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>These
three are linked. Through _the suffering of the composite_, we ignore how
happy, free and wise the mind is in its natural, uncontrived state. We get
involved in all sorts of ventures and situations, in an attempt to find
happiness for ourselves, but due to the _suffering through change_, our
ignorance of cause-and-effect means that often our attempts to find happiness
are triggering unhappiness for the future. When that future comes, there is _suffering
as suffering_. Therefore the scriptures compare samsara to poisoned rice. By
its very nature, it is poisoned. Not knowing this, one eats it and finds it
delicious and nourishing. But because of the poison, one later falls ill and
writhes in agony.    </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_A\Buddhist survey of the cosmos_"
                     pagetitle="_A\Buddhist survey of the cosmos_"
                     tocentry="_A\Buddhist survey of the cosmos_">
            <paragraph>The
way in which the Truth of Suffering is presented is as a survey of the
different worlds of existence and a sort of balance-sheet describing the
life-conditions, joys, sufferings, faculties and life-spans of the various
beings. The Buddha taught about the cosmos itself differently according to the
audience. In general, we have three versions<a href="#_ftn26">[24]</a>:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The
     common-people's version, based on the way in which the people at the time
     of the Buddha believed the world to be<a href="#_ftn27">[25]</a>.  This was
     a widespread Indo-European world view which had probably reached India in
     the second millennium BCE. It was a _world-centred view_ of the
     cosmos, based upon a central mountain, with the realms of the gods stacked
     one above another in the sky above and with the infernal realms in the
     volcanic lava beneath the earth. The stars and planets revolved around the
     world in the sky above.</li>
               <li>The
     _universal view_ often found in Mahayana texts. It consists of
     inhabited universes, each made of a billion world-systems similar to the
     one mentioned above. In fact, it is a thousand sets of worlds made of a
     thousand sets of worlds each made of a thousand sets of such worlds. You
     will find such a universe described as a _gigacosmos_ or _trichiliocosm_
     in translations.</li>
               <li>A
     _mind-based view_ of the cosmos, in which there are as many "worlds"
     as there are sentient beings and these worlds could be absolutely anything,
     as could their beings. One finds this in the tantras, such as the
     Kalachakra Tantra, where it says that how other beings may possibly be
     defies our imagination.</li>
            </list>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_The\six categories, or &#34;Six Realms&#34;, of beings_"
                     pagetitle="_The\six categories, or &#34;Six Realms&#34;, of beings_"
                     tocentry="_The\six categories, or &#34;Six Realms&#34;, of beings_">
            <paragraph>We
only have to look around here on Earth, on land or in the oceans or through a
microscope, to appreciate the almost limitless and breath-taking variety of
living beings, not to mention those which might exist elsewhere. Mahayana
Buddhism, while recognising an endless number of types of being, discerns six
major categories, known as the "six realms of samsara". There is a tendency
these days among certain Buddhist teachers to take these solely as a metaphor
for the range of different experiences of the human psyche. Although that is
very useful, as a tool for understanding our human minds and human karma, our
greatest contemporary masters say beyond any doubt that the Buddha taught these
as actual states of being into which one can be reborn. Of the six, most humans
only experience two; those of other humans and animals. The existence of the
remaining four has to be taken on trust: trust of the Buddha's own teachings
and trust of the experience of other realms which arises in the clear
meditations of accomplished Buddhist masters.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
Hinayana Buddhism, mind and matter are different and the various realms have
"geographical" existence. The locations are mentioned in each section below. In
Mahayana Buddhism, everything is mind and hence the question as to whether
hells exist as real places or not becomes redundant. In this respect, please
note Gampopa's comments about the hells, at the end of that section.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The six realms fall into two groups:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.     The *upper realms*--of
gods, demi-gods and humans--where there is a relatively good rebirth and some
degree of happiness, albeit transient.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.     The *lower realms*--of
animals, spirits and hell-beings--which are generally unfortunate rebirths and
where suffering dominates.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>All
is not clear-cut. There are many borderline cases and stories of mixed karma.
For instance, a pampered pet dog may be materially much better-off than a human
living in a place of extreme famine and war. These are general categories only,
established with a particular view to help us understand the major results of
karma. For a fairly full description of these states, you are recommended to
read the "suffering" chapter in Gampopa's "Gems of Dharma, Jewels of Freedom".
What follows is a resumé.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The Upper Realms" pagetitle="The Upper Realms"
                           tocentry="The Upper Realms">
               <paragraph>The
upper realms are characterised by the relative ease of their circumstances *yet*
there is always some suffering present and none of these states lasts
indefinitely: a human life, for instance, is not that long. There is also the
suffering of change. The upper realms all belong to samsara, and hence there is
always the suffering of the composite. These relatively fortunate states
represent good rebirth resulting from previous virtuous karma. Their
duration--or the number of times one may be reborn in them--depends upon the
quality and quantity of virtuous karma.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
god realms are as good--in material terms--as samsara gets. Gods' bodies (some
have bodies of light) and the realms in which they live, not to mention the joy
and harmony between them, are for the most part delightful, although some gods
have a wicked side. These godly--of if we use the Sanskrit word _deva_--
existences occur as a result of strong and virtuous karma in previous lives.
There are three main categories of gods:</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*Sense-dimension
     gods*.
     As the name suggests, their worlds are sensorial, filled with visual
     beauty, pleasant sounds, pleasant companions and consorts etc. These
     result from former powerful practice of generosity, pure conduct and
     forbearance. These actions, accomplished in what appears to the realms of
     the senses, bring joyful sensorial results. There are six main levels of
     these gods<a href="#_ftn28">[26]</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>*Form-dimension
     gods.* 
     These are rebirth-states in which the experience is not of sensorial
     beauty but of meditative absorption. It is very long-lasting and
     uninterrupted and produced by virtue and prowess in similar meditations
     when human. There are four main categories with seventeen sub-categories, +of
     which only the first twelve belong to samsara+. The others are only
     accessible to beings who have gone beyond individuality and rebirth.</li>
                  <li>*Formless
     gods.*
     These are rebirths into a state on ongoing formless meditation, produced
     by the impetus of mastery of formless meditation whilst human. There are
     four levels.</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>Thus,
altogether, there are twenty-seven levels of gods of which twenty-two fall
within samsara.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
*sufferings* of the gods are those of having to protect their vast
possessions and to fend off the attacks of the jealous demi-gods (see below),
of dissatisfaction due to unsatiated desires but principally those of decline
and fall, when their karma to remain in the god realms eventually runs out.
They have become so accustomed to the beauty or the purity of their realms, and
to all the power and possibilities associated with their state, that the pain
of losing it all is unbearable. They have considerable clairvoyance and foresee
their coming rebirth long before it happens. This prospect is overwhelmingly
sad and unbelievable, as their pride, which in this context means "taking for
granted" (see below) finds it so hard to accept that there can be no other
outcome but a fall into a much, much worse state, often, as it happens, the
lower realms.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
*defining characteristic* of the god realms is *pride*. This can be
taken to mean arrogance and haughtiness but it often has a much broader meaning
of "identifying with being on top"<a href="#_ftn29">[27]</a>.
The gods are where they are through their good karma but rather than
understanding their condition to be a transient moment of good fortune, they
feel that it is "their place", "their right", forever. We could take the
example of a person born a billionaire in our world, who would find it
completely natural to be flown around in a private jet, to have a home filled
afresh with expensive flowers every day and so on and so forth, even though
others are penniless. It feels natural - to him! Thus, there is presumption and
complacency.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>   
It was the combination of pride with good karma which caused gods to be reborn
as they are and that is why it is important for us, as we create virtue, to
remain humble and to dedicate it to a useful rebirth, preferably as a human.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>   
Another defining characteristic of the gods is *spiritual laziness*. This
is a direct consequence of their pride and the feeling that things will always
be that good. There is not the stimulation of experiencing suffering, either in
themselves or the world around them, to trigger the compassion which is the
keynote of spirituality. When they do start to suffer, as they see their
forthcoming nemesis, they are too filled with fear and self-pity to give space
to spirituality.      </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Compared
to humans, gods live for extremely long periods of time, although their own
perception of time is different from ours.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>These
have a fair degree of good karma and are reborn in proximity to the deva realms
and in states of relative ease. However, their states are not as rich, or
resplendent, as those of the true gods. Their possible pleasure is marred by
their *jealousy*, which is their *defining characteristic*.  Jealous
of their neighbour gods, they set out in battle to appropriate the gods'
riches. However, they themselves lack the karma to possess those riches and as
the gods have greater strength, they inevitably lose their struggles. Thus the
sufferings of the demi-gods are principally those of the inner torment of not
being able to accept their limited good fortune and of being burnt by jealousy,
along with the outer torment of undergoing humiliating injury and defeats.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>They
share a similar perception of time to that of the gods.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>A
human birth is considered the finest, as far as spiritual potential goes. It
has just enough suffering to stimulate compassion. It is relatively short, so
there is an impetus to prioritise spirituality. It has enough freedom--in terms
of time, resources and so on--for someone to actually be dedicated to dharma.
The *defining characteristic* of humans is *desire* and hence *busyness*
in order to fulfil the desires.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)All human life is subject to the
following four sufferings:(eeh)</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)Birth.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)Ageing.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)Sickness.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)Death.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>(eh)And nearly all human life has the
following four other sufferings:(eeh)</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)Separation from the people and
     things one loves.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)Encountering what is unpleasant.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)Striving to get what one needs and
     (eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)<img width="427" align="left" src="module2_files/image011.png"/>Striving to maintain
     what one has.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>As
this realm is of direct concern to us, as humans, let us examine the first four
in more detail.</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*"Birth"* covers the whole
     period from the experiences of the "in-between-lives" state<a href="#_ftn30">[28]</a>, through
     conception, time in the womb and the helpless period when one is a
     dependant baby. The latter could arguably be extended into teenage years
     or to whichever time one can actually take control of one's own existence.
     
         This whole period of "birth" is governed by helplessness and
     unavoidable experience. The _bardo_ is like a wild dream in which one
     is flung here and there, from one crazy experience to another. It ends
     with a series of powerful experiences, heralding conception and the future
     life. These experiences and the various stages of experience in the dark
     confines of the womb, once conception has taken place, are vividly
     described in Gampopa. 
        Once born, one is unable to speak, take care of oneself and so forth
     and is dependent upon others for everything. Without any choice in the
     matter, for better or for worse, one acquires the habits and attitudes of
     the family and culture into which one has been born.</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*Ageing* is not simply old-age,
     although that is the most vivid stage of the process. It is the loss of
     abilities and faculties which starts already in one's twenties (the
     ancient vajrayana texts recognised this and talk of a gradual decline from
     very early on). Some of the things affected, mentioned in Gampopa, are:
     strength, hair, skin, complexion, physical ability, sense faculties,
     prestige, quality of life, health and mental ability.</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*Sickness* is vividly depicted by
     Milarepa, who describes it as being "like a tiny bird smitten by slingshot
     in mid flight". Most of us are aware of the suffering of physical or
     mental sickness. Gampopa highlights: being actually hit by the disease,
     having to undergo medical procedures and examinations, having to take strong
     medicines, being prevented from eating and drinking what one likes or
     doing things one likes to do, having to follow doctor's orders, fear of
     death and the effect it has on one's work and fortune.</li>
               </list>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>*Death* is described vividly
     in the following extract from a sutra taught to a monarch. "Great King! 
     When, like this, one has been tormented on the torture spike of death, one
     is no longer so arrogant. One is without protectors, allies or friend.
     Stricken by disease, the mouth is thirsty, one's face changes, the limbs
     give way, one is unable to work and filthies one's body with saliva, snot,
     urine and disgusting vomit and wheezes noisily. The doctors abandon hope,
     one sleeps on one's bed for the last time, sinks into the stream of
     samsara and becomes frightened of the Lord of Death's emissaries. The
     breathing stops, the mouth and nostrils gape. One leaves behind this world
     and heads for the next. It is the great departure, the entrance into
     deepest darkness, the fall over the greatest precipice and the mighty
     ocean sweeping one away. Borne away by the wind of karma, one goes to the
     place of no settling and this without being able to take one iota of one's
     possessions. Though one cries out _Oh, mother! Oh father! Oh my
     children!,_ there is, at that time, great king, no other protector, no
     other refuge, no other ally, than dharma."   </li>
               </list>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Three Lower Realms" pagetitle="The Three Lower Realms"
                           tocentry="The Three Lower Realms">
               <paragraph>The
lower realms are the more painful end of samsara, in general representing
unfortunate rebirth due to past non-virtuous karma. Besides the specific
sufferings of each state, there is also the fact that the mind of a being in
those states is so preoccupied with its own condition, often pain, that there
is not the "space" for dharma.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>These
are defined either by their habitat (land, sea or air), or by the numbers of
their legs<a href="#_ftn31">[29]</a>
or else by their servitude (domestic animals, wild animals). Today we take for
granted our vast knowledge of the animal world brought about by technological
advance. It is quite extraordinary that thousands of years ago, the texts
already clearly stated that by far and away the greatest majority of animals
live in the oceans, in endless variety, eating one another ... and how so many
were too small to be seen with the naked eye. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
main physical sufferings of the animals are those connected to survival itself:
finding food, coping with the elements and avoiding predators. It is said that
many of them live in constant fear for their lives. Domesticated animals have
to suffer what humans impose upon them. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
*defining characteristic* of animals is ignorance, in the form of *stupidity*,
in a life dominated by concern for food and reproduction. Although within their
own realms of action, animals can show remarkable intelligence and skill, they
cannot, in general, understand dharma and could not follow a path of spiritual
evolution, as we humans can. As always, there are exceptions but these only
serve to confirm the rule.</paragraph>
               <paragraph> Their
Sanskrit name sounds like _préta_. These beings are generally invisible to
humans, when they live in the same lands. Many are said to live in sand or ice
deserts and lonely places. Their rebirth is a result of *avarice,* their *defining
characteristic*, and their lives are like an avaricious person's worst
nightmare: that of never getting what one most longs for or of losing it just
as it seems to be assured. Some of these spirits are powerful ghosts or demons
and, through the complexity of their karma, have considerable powers in certain
areas, yet this gigantic, hollow, unsatisfied yearning in others. The _préta_
"aristocrats" are the lieutenants of the Lord of Death and have abodes in
cavernous spaces deep beneath the earth. The rest are pitiable, isolated
creatures, sometimes living in tiny groups of families<a href="#_ftn32">[30]</a> . </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
deprived spirits have three major types of suffering, mainly related to eating
or drinking:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>1.    
An
external impediment, whereby they can never find something to eat or drink, not
even a scrap, despite roaming and searching for months on end. Sometimes they
do find something but often only to see it snatched from under their eyes or to
find other beings barring them from eating it. Or else it turns to pus and
blood in their perception.  In our human world, we have those unfortunate
people in places of famine and poverty whose lives are a wretched search for
food. The humans often die quickly. The deprived spirits do not have the
"escape route" of death but a seemingly-unending frustrating and desperate
search for food or water lasting for centuries.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>2.    
An
internal impediment, whereby they have "bellies the size of a mountain but a
mouth the size of a needle".</paragraph>
               <paragraph>3.    
A
general impediment, whereby when at last food or drink is found, its ingestion
causes unimaginable pain, being like fire-garlands or molten copper or else
tasting like filth. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>These
spirits live for around five hundred or their own years, which are said to be
the equivalent of fifteen thousand of our years. Many of these spirits have
clear recall of their previous lives, as humans, and of the avaricious acts
which caused their sorry lot. We find accounts of them in the likes of the
stories told by Million In The Ear<a href="#_ftn33">[31]</a>.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Their
*defining characteristic* is *anger*. They fall into four main
categories:</paragraph>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>Those
     in *eight hot hells*, undergoing all sorts of torture from heat and
     physical pain. The various degrees of agony are due to being crushed, or
     cut up, or being burnt by coals, molten metal etc., with no relief through
     "death" but mini-revivals, only to start the agony all over again. </li>
                  <li>Those
     in *eight cold hells*, undergoing severe cold and physical pain.
     These tend to be desolate, grim, arctic landscapes.</li>
                  <li>Those
     in the four *"neighbouring" hells*, each with its specific plight,
     such as swamps of filth or trees with razor-sharp leaves.</li>
                  <li>Those
     in *occasional hells*, which, unlike the above, produced by
     commonplace anger, violence and harm to others, are produced by very
     unusual karma in past lives. These could be almost anything, anywhere.</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>These
hells are mainly spoken of as being located kilometres beneath the earth. Their
duration is complicated and very long indeed, comparable to the gods'
life-spans. The details can be found in Gampopa, who concludes:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>One may wonder whether or
not the guardians of the hells--who appear to be humans or ravens with iron
beaks--are actual sentient beings. The Particularist<a href="#_ftn34">[32]</a> schools hold them to be sentient
beings whereas the Sutra Follower<a href="#_ftn35">[33]</a>
schools say they are not. The Practisers of Union<a href="#_ftn36">[34]</a> schools and the patriarchal
transmission of Marpa and Mila *hold them to be manifestations of one's own
mind*, due to evils one has enacted. The Guide to the Bodhisattva Life
accords with this interpretation:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Who could have created the
beings there and their hellish weapons for such purposes?  Who made the burning
iron ground and from what are the fires generated. The Great Sage has said that
all these sorts of things are due to the existence of an unwholesome mind.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Many people have
a tough time or strong reaction when they discover that Buddhism, like some
other faiths, has notions of hell, with description not dissimilar to those of
Catholicism etc. As explained above, by Gampopa, these hells are not places but
states of mind. Angry or evil people carry the imprints of their conditioning
and past deeds in their consciousness. At death, this consciousness experiences
hell, just as a dreamer has a nightmare in which the horrible circumstances
seem completely real, all-encompassing and unending. Human dreamers are awoken
by their physical body. Without a body, those who die and enter into these ghastly
hallucinations have no biology to stop the repetitive nightmare. The realities
experienced make a lot of sense: an angry person's dream is to blame and defeat
the enemy and worst nightmare is to be beaten and humiliated themselves. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>    Anyone who
has experienced the horrors of war zones or locked psychiatric wards will
understand that if such things are possible for humans, worse is possible for a
mind let loose by death to plunge into its worst phantasms.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="7" title="The Five Aggregates  (Skandha)"
               pagetitle="The Five Aggregates  (Skandha)"
               tocentry="The Five Aggregates  (Skandha)">
         <subsection title="The Five Aggregates (Skandha)" pagetitle="The Five Aggregates (Skandha)"
                     tocentry="The Five Aggregates (Skandha)">
            <image width="461"/>
            <paragraph>As
the First Truth is about beings and their worlds, we shall consider briefly the
five _skandha_, as it is through them that a sentient being is defined.
The Buddha taught the Five Aggregates to help us get away from the illusion of
a sentient being as a single, indivisible entity. We will come back to this
topic several times over the study programme, especially as we explore
consciousness in more depth.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="_Why\they are so-called_" pagetitle="_Why\they are so-called_"
                     tocentry="_Why\they are so-called_">
            <paragraph>They
are "aggregates" (Skt: skandha, Tib: phung po) or "heaps" because a heap is a
pile of many small things. Each of the five is a major, distinct, area of our
being, itself constituted of many smaller, short-lived components. These five come
together, in all sorts of different ways, instant after instant, to create the
illusion of life as we experience it, and especially the experience of being
"someone". </paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*The five
aggregates are: *(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*form     
feelings      cognition      mental events      consciousness.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.  *Form*.
</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Although
this has a specific definition, as "visual form", i.e. the raw shapes and
colours which are the field of visual consciousness, it usually has a more
general definition of all the forms present in the mind. We can sum these up as
being:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.    
_Primary
Forms_: the *primal
elements*: matter, bonding, energy and movement, referred to poetically as
earth, water, fire and wind. The remaining ones are _secondary forms_. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.    
The *Five
Sense Organs &amp; Faculties*: giving the power to see, hear, smell, taste
and touch.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3.    
Their *Five
Fields*: sights, sounds, odours, flavours and tactile sensations.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>4.    
*Other
forms*,
including abstract forms, such as maintaining precepts, "making a prostration",
where the mind relates to a series of actions through its knowledge of the
intention behind them etc.  Also "unrecognisable forms", such as a meditation
experience of colour, in one person's mind, imperceptible to another's. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.  *Feelings.* This term has a quite specific and limited meaning in
dharma. It simply refers to the initial reaction to something as being:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*1.    
**Pleasant.*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*2.    
**Unpleasant
or*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*3.    
**Neutral.*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Hence
there are three feelings only. If we sub-categorise the first two into physical
or mental, this gives a maximum of five feelings.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3.  *Cognition* is the recognising of things: the "apprehension of
characteristics". It is of two sorts:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.    
*Object-related*, whereby grass can be distinguished
from rock, a wolf's howl can be distinguished from the sound of wind etc. This
is something directly and immediately perceived and _does not require thought_.
Therefore animals and all other beings have this.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.    
*Idea-Related*, where the thinking mind _labels_
its object-related perceptions and even goes on to refine that recognition
through elaborating thoughts and describing things to itself, in thought-words,
at length. This is highly-developed in humans.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>4.  *Mental Events*, Mental Factors, also called Conditioning Factors. This
category includes some of the other four aggregates, extracted and given their
own categories because they play such an important role in the quality of life.
There are 51 main headings in this section, including the 11 main virtues of
mind, the 6 and 21 non-virtues and various mechanisms of the mind.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>5.  *Consciousness*. This word too has a very tightly-defined
meaning in dharma. It is "that which links the perceiving mind with what
is perceived". Thus we have five sense consciousnesses and mental
consciousness:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>_Visual
     Consciousness_,
     linking the power to see with visible forms.</li>
               <li>_Hearing
     Consciousness_,
     linking the power to hear with sounds.</li>
               <li>_Smelling_ or _OlfactoryConsciousness_,
     linking the power to smell with odours.</li>
               <li>_Tasting_ or _GustativeConsciousness_,
     linking the power to taste with flavours.</li>
               <li>_Tactile
     Consciousness_,
     linking the body's ability to feel with sensations, such as heat, cold,
     hunger, texture, pain etc.</li>
               <li>_Mental
     Consciousness_,
     linking the perceiving mind with whatever it is thinking about or
     experiencing. The sphere of mind's objects is known as _dharma_.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>To
these six, found throughout Buddhism, the Mind-Only school very usefully adds
two more:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>_Distorting
     Consciousness_,
     which "warps" the experience of the six consciousnesses by adding duality.
     It also triggers the next moment of consciousness.</li>
               <li>_Universal
     Basis Consciousness_,
     which is like the neutral ground, or storehouse of consciousness,
     retaining karmic and memory imprints.</li>
            </list>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="8" title="" pagetitle="" tocentry=""/>
   </chapter>
</book>