<book>
    <appendix index="6" title="The Sixty Qualities of the Buddha's Melodious Speech">
        <list>
            <item>It is _distinguished and subtle_ inasmuch as hearing it causes sentient beings to plant roots of virtue.</item>
            <item>It is _smooth and soothing_, bringing immediate physical well-being to its listeners.&#xA;&#xA;_*These two are qualities which are results.*_</item>
            <item>It seems _beautiful_ to the listener's mind since it teaches the meaning of what needs to be established and what needs to be eliminated.&#xA;&#xA;_*This is the quality of what is being expressed.*_</item>
            <item>To the listener it seems so _suitable_, by its choice of words used to express those meanings.&#xA;&#xA;_*These first four could also be called the essence-qualities of their speech.*_</item>
            <item>It is _pure in its virtuous motivation_ inasmuch as it is achieved subsequent to the supramundane.</item>
            <item>It is _unpolluted_ since it has a motivation free of any negative affect because dormant negative affects have been eliminated.&#xA;&#xA;_*These two qualities are related to motivation; they might also be described as relating to the faultless character of their speech.*_</item>
            <item>It is _clear_ i.e. there is clarity of terms and letters. This is in terms of application.</item>
            <item>It is _harmonious to listen_ to since it dispels unhealthy views.</item>
            <item>It is _worthy of attentive listening_ because it teaches the means of true transcendance.</item>
            <item>It is _unharmful_ since it does not criticise others and dispels aberrant speech.</item>
            <item>It is _sweet-sounding_, making the listener's mind fill with joy.</item>
            <item>it is _taming_ since it teaches remedies for the negative affects such as attachment etc. &#xA;&#xA;_*These five are qualities in terms of ability: qualities of its euphony and understandability through might, whichever be the case (as above and below).*_</item>
            <item>It is _not coarse_ because it does not apply what would be fatiguing.</item>
            <item>It is _not difficult to practise or corruptible_ since it teaches how to regenerate what has been broken.&#xA;&#xA;_*These two relate to it inspiring right conduct.*_</item>
            <item>It _most-excellently disciplines_ because it establishes paths for the three sorts of capacity.</item>
            <item>It is _pleasing to the ear_ because it removes the impediment of powerful distraction.</item>
            <item>It _physically satisfies_ disciples, through proficiency and deep insight.</item>
            <item>It _mentally satisfies_ disciples, through proficiency and deep insight.&#xA;&#xA;_*These four relate to it applying others to profound absorption.*_</item>
            <item>It _soothes the mind_ by removing doubts.</item>
            <item>It _inspires well-being_ by removing aberrant thinking and uncertainty.&#xA;&#xA;_*These two relate to it engendering wisdom. Thus qualities 13-20 describe the way it helps others apply themselves to the three trainings.*_</item>
            <item>It _anihilates grief_ by anihilating regret.</item>
            <item>It is _universally enlightening_ because listening to it instills the finest wisdom.</item>
            <item>It is the _work of total intelligence_ by establishing the foundation of the very best wisdom of contemplation.&#xA;&#xA;_*These three concern its refreshing, satisfying quality.*_</item>
            <item>It is _utterly clear_ because it teaches without favouritism or holding-back.&#xA;&#xA;_*This is its quality of absence of avarice concerning dharma.*_</item>
            <item>It _makes joyful_: as disciples delight in the increase in qualities already attained.</item>
            <item>It _brings manifest joy_: delight, since what was not attained is generated.</item>
            <item>It _makes omniscience_ by pointing out the profound.</item>
            <item>It _makes total intelligence_ by teaching the vast.&#xA;&#xA;_*These four are its qualities of sustenance for sentient life.*_</item>
            <item>It is _reason_ because it expresses that which is valid.</item>
            <item>It _relates to others subjective conditions_ since it teaches in a way which accords with individual disciple's
            existences.</item>
            <item>It is _not inarticulate_, being without confused expression, stuttering etc.&#xA;&#xA;_*These three are qualities of aware application.*_</item>
            <item>It is _like a lion's roar_, so awe-inspiring that it excludes debate.</item>
            <item>It is _like an elephant's trumpeting_, so far-reaching that it pervades any entourage.</item>
            <item>It is _like the rumbling of thunder_, being deep in tone.</item>
            <item>It is _like the naga-king's melody_, worthy of being heard and enrapturing.</item>
            <item>It is _like the gandharvas' melodies_: to hear it steals away the mind.</item>
            <item>It is _like the song of a kalavinka bird_: awe-inspiring for all, uninterruptedly bring understanding and never overpowered by other sounds.</item>
            <item>It is _like Brahma's melody_, famed far and zide.</item>
            <item>It is _like the cry of the mythical shang-shang-tiu bird_, inasmuch as to hear it is an auspicious indication of the accomplishment of any task.</item>
            <item>It is _like Indra's melody_, employing noble terms.</item>
            <item>It is _like the sound of the mighty divine drum_, victorious over negative forces.&#xA;&#xA;_*The above ten qualities are examples of its greatness.*_</item>
            <item>It is _not arrogant_ even though it is praised for its lack of defilement.</item>
            <item>It is _unperturbed_ by criticism.</item>
            <item>It _properly employs the significance of terms_---not transforming whatever is said into some other meaning and staying within the defined meanings of conventional terminology.</item>
            <item>It is _unstumbling_, because of faultless recollection.</item>
            <item>It is _not incomplete in its effectiveness_ since it is centred on and pervades all areas of disciples' meaningful benefit, both in terms of time and situation.</item>
            <item>It is _uncompromising_ because there is no involvement with honours or respect.</item>
            <item>It is _confident_, being beyond anxiety about audience reaction.</item>
            <item>It is _extremely joyful_ since there is neither fatigue nor regret in teaching dharma.</item>
            <item>It _encompasses every significance_ through erudition in all that can be known.</item>
            <item>It is _faultless_ because it makes its meaning be comprehended by everyone, through its love, supporting even those without roots of virtue.</item>
            <item>It is _continuous_, expressing itself uninterruptedly, i.e. teaching permanently.</item>
            <item>It is _explicative_ or _brilliant_, because it brings understanding and explains thoroughly various facets of the meanings expressed.</item>
            <item>It _encompasses all terms_ by being located in various means of expression, using terms of various divine or other languages, even when employing just one term.</item>
            <item>It _satiates according to capacity_---by illuminating all the various meanings that individuals seek to understand.</item>
            <item>It is _uncriticisable_ since it never makes statements subject to refutation and hence regret.</item>
            <item>It is _never other than altruistic_ since its advice is ever timely and never misplaced.</item>
            <item>It is _unrushed_ since they do not speak over-hurriedly with jumbled or mumbled words.</item>
            <item>It _resounds throughout its audience_, being heard equally by those close or distant.</item>
            <item>It is _the finest of all things_ through its ability to thoroughly teach any meaning and use anything as an example.&#xA;&#xA;_*These last nineteen are qualities related to Buddhas benefiting their disciples.*_</item>
        </list>
        <paragraph>To the above are sometimes added a further four - the conquest of attachment, aversion, stupidity and the maras, making sixty-four qualities in all.</paragraph>
    </appendix>
</book>