<book>
    <appendix index="0" title="Stories Illustrating Buddha's Skill &amp; Compassion">
        <section title="Kisagotami &amp; The Mustard Seed">
            <paragraph>
            The starting point of Gautama's own search for Nirvana was the realisation that sorrow is a condition of life, that one cannot avoid it, only rise above it, and this theme occurs frequently in the story of his career. One of the best-known episodes on this theme is that of the bereaved mother and the mustard seed.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Kisagotami was a young woman from a well-to-do family who was married to a wealthy merchant in Savatthi. When their first-born child was about a year old it fell ill and died before a physician could be summoned. Kisagotami was beside herself with grief and began roaming the streets of Savatthi asking people if they knew of a medicine that would restore her child to life. Some people merely ignored her, others thought she had gone out of her mind and laughed at her, but no one could offer her any help. Finally she met a wise man who told her: `There is only one person in the world who can perform the miracle you ask. He is the Buddha, and at the moment he is staying at the Jetavana monastery. Go and ask him to help you.' Kisagotami went to the Buddha and, placing the body of her child at his feet, told him her sad story.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            The Buddha listened to her with patience and kindness and then said: `My sister, there is only one way to heal your affliction. Go down to the city and bring me back a mustard seed from any house in which there has never been a death.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Kisagotami felt a great elation and immediately set off for the city. She stopped at the first house she saw and said: `I have been told by the Buddha to fetch a mustard seed from a house which has never known death.' `Alas,' she was told, `many people have died in this house.' She went to the next house and was told : `There have been countless deaths in our family.' And so to a third house and a fourth until she had been right through the city without being able to fulfil the Buddha's condition. Now she realised what the Buddha had intended her to discover-that death comes to all. Reconciled to this sad reality she took the body of her child to the charnel ground for disposal and returned to the monastery.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Have you brought the mustard seed?' asked the Buddha.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `No,' she said, `nor shall I try to find it any longer. Now I understand the lesson you were trying to teach me. My grief had made me blind, and I thought that only I had suffered at the hands of death.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `So why have you come back here?' asked the Buddha.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `To ask you to teach me the truth,' she replied.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Whereupon the Buddha began to instruct her, saying: `In all the world of men, and of the gods too, there is only one lawthat all things are impermanent.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Kisagotami joined the Sangha and, we are told, eventually achieved Nirvana.
        </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section title="Patachara">
            <paragraph>
            An even more poignant story, rivalling the trials of Job as a catalogue of misfortunes, is told about a girl called Patachara. Patachara was the daughter of a rich man of Savatthi. Her parents were so possessive and protective towards her that they kept her confined in a room high up in their mansion. So, lacking companionship, she secretly fell in love with her page boy.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            When she reached the age of sixteen Patachara's parents made arrangements for her to be married to the son of another rich man. Greatly distressed, she and her lover decided to elope and on the morning of the wedding day she disguised herself as a servant going to fetch water and slipped unnoticed out of the house. They met at the edge of the city and went to a far place, where they got married.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            In due course she became pregnant and as her time approached she recalled the custom whereby a woman should give birth to her child in her parents' house. She mentioned this to her husband, who was naturally horrified at the idea, but now her desire was so strong that she set out in spite of his objections. He followed, begging her to turn back, until in the middle of their journey she went into labour and gave birth. There was no point in going on and they returned home.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            A second time she became pregnant and as before she set out for her parents' home, followed by her reluctant husband. But this time tragedy was to strike. Along the way a violent storm arose and at the same time Patachara began to feel birth pains. She settled down as well as she could, while her husband went off into the woods to get some branches and make a shelter for her. As he was cutting down a bush he was bitten by a snake and fell down dead. Troubles now came thick and fast. She bore her child and the three of them-she herself, her elder child and the baby-spent the night exposed to the tempest and rain. The next day they came across the dead body of her husband. There was nothing to do but continue her journey, so carrying her baby on her hip and leading the other child by the hand Patachara walked on until she reached a river swollen in flood. Not feeling strong enough to carry both children across at one time, Patachara left the older one on the bank while she took the baby across to the other side. No sooner had she put it down than a bird of prey swooped towards it. She shouted at the bird to scare it off, whereupon the boy on the other bank, thinking his mother was calling him, jumped into the river to join her. Horrified, Patachara herself plunged into the water to try and save him; but too late, he was swept away by the current and drowned. Meanwhile, before she could regain the bank the bird returned and made off with the baby.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            As if this was not sufficient calamity, a further shock awaited Patachara when she eventually reached Savatthi. Anxious for news of her parents she stopped a man on the outskirts of the city and asked him if he knew them. `Ask me about any other family,' he replied, and went on to tell how, the previous night, their house was destroyed by heavy rain-the same storm which Patachara and her children had endured-and they had died in its collapse. The man pointed to a fire nearby which, he explained, was their funeral pyre.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            It is worth remarking that, if such a tale of misery strains the credulity of the modern Western reader, disasters on this scale are still not uncommon in a part of the world regularly ravaged by floods or else parched by drought and always beset by natural dangers of one kind or another. Even so, it is difficult to imagine a sadder tale and it serves as a graphic and memorable parable to illustrate the Buddha's message.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            On hearing that she had lost everything Patachara collapsed helpless with grief. While she lay weeping and writhing on the ground some people came by and took her to the Jetavana monastery where the Buddha was preaching. The Buddha asked some of the women present to wash and clothe her, and give her food, and then he began to talk to her about her misfortune. Taking refuge in his teaching she too joined the Sangha and eventually, we are told, gained Enlightenment.
        </paragraph>
        </section>
            <section title="Compassion for All Living Things">
                <paragraph>
            From his childhood, when he had disputed with his cousin Devadatta over the wounded swan, Gautama is. depicted as showing concern for all living things. Such compassion is perhaps the reverse side of the coin which bears on its face the motto `Sorrow is universal'; certainly in the course of the Buddha's teaching there are various examples of this charitable feeling in action.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            On one occasion, while visiting a monastery with his attendant Ananda, the Buddha entered a room where a monk lay sick. He was suffering from diarrhoea and besides being in great pain was in a filthy condition. No one, however, showed the least concern about him.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            `Why are the other monks not attending on you?' asked the Buddha.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Because I do not attend on them,' he answered.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            The Buddha called Ananda and together they began to minister to the sick monk. They boiled water and washed him, and then they moved him from his bed to a clean resting place. When they had finished the Buddha summoned the other monks and exhorted them to look after the sick and suffering.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Whoever attends on the sick attends on me,' he said.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            On another occasion a monk at the Jetavana monastery developed a skin ailment which brought his body out in boils. As the boils burst they caused terrible sores which stained his garments. His condition became so unpleasant that his fellow monks in desperation carried him out of the monastery and abandoned him on some open ground. Hearing of this the Buddha, again accompanied by Ananda, went out to tend him. This time the other monks rallied to the Buddha's example and between them they prepared hot water, washed the monk's clothes and made him comfortable.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                Stories are told, too, where the Buddha admonished children for being cruel to animals. In one instance he came across some boys amusing themselves at the expense of some fish trapped in an almost dry reservoir. Another time he found some boys attacking a snake with a stick.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            According to the texts the Buddha used these opportunities to explain the law of moral causation-that one is morally responsible for the consequences of one's acts, good or evil. But at the same time, being a practical man with an understanding of human psychology, he seems to have appealed to the better instincts of these children in much the same way as parents and teachers have always done when trying to restrain the unthinking brutality of youth. He asked them in effect : `How would you like somebody to do that to you?'
        </paragraph>
        </section>
<section title="The Middle Way">
    <paragraph>
            Practicality and common sense are fundamental to the teaching of the Buddha. They are what perhaps most obviously distinguishes Buddhism from the practice of others both then and now who renounce the worldly life-the ascetics, hermits, yogis and so on who had adopted `sanyas', or rigorous self-denial and withdrawal from ordinary human activity-and which Gautama had himself repudiated after following it for six years. Common sense is the foundation of the Middle Way, which essentially means avoiding such fanatical adherence to a particular course of action or attitude of mind that it can itself become an imprisonment, another kind of `clinging'. Yet, because it is so difficult to define, the moderation taught by the Buddha has created difficulties for many of his followers, since those who adopt the religious life tend to do so with the zeal of total commitment and have little patience with half-measures.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            This common sense of the Buddha-and, incidentally, his ordinary, straightforward kindness-is illustrated in a touching little story that echoes his own experiment with asceticism. One day the Buddha and his entourage were the guests of the inhabitants of a place called Alavi. One of those who had determined to go and hear him was a poor farmer, but on the morning of the visit one of his oxen was discovered to be missing. Torn between his desire to hear the Buddha and his concern for his ox, the farmer set out early to look for the animal, intending to join the meeting later. But by the time he had found the ox and returned it to the herd it was approaching evening. He had eaten nothing all day, but it was now so late that he could not delay further, so he went straight to the meeting. Meanwhile the Buddha and his companions had been entertained to a meal by the people of Alavi and the Buddha was about to `give thanks' in the customary way by preaching a sermon. At this point the farmer arrived. Seeing this poor man, looking so tired and weak, standing in front of him, the Buddha asked one of the stewards to find him a place to sit and give him food. Only when the farmer had finished eating did the Buddha begin his discourse, to which the farmer listened with rapt attention.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Some of the monks with the Buddha raised their eyebrows at such concern for one man, especially a poor farmer who had arrived late, and after the meeting they began to grumble at what seemed to them the unorthodox behaviour of their leader. Hearing these complaints, the Buddha explained: `If I had preached to this man while he was suffering the pangs of hunger he would not have been able to follow me. "There is no affliction like the affliction of hunger.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            But the Buddha also made it clear that in urging moderation he was not by any means condoning indulgence. On the contrary, moderation implied restraint--restraint of all appetites, including that for self-punishment.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            King Pasenadi of Kosala was a man who liked his food. A good meal for him meant boiled rice by the bucketful, with curries and sauces in corresponding measure. One day after breakfasting in his usual style he began to feel drowsy, but not wishing to fall asleep so early in the day he went for a walk to the Jetavana monastery where the Buddha was staying. With a weary iook he flopped down near the Buddha, barely able to keep his eyes open.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `What is the matter, great King?' asked the Buddha. `Did you not sleep well?'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Oh no, your reverence,' he replied courteously. `I always have this trouble after eating.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Great King,' said the Buddha, `your trouble is eating too much. Anyone who lives indolently, sleeping all the time and over-eating, so that he rolls about like a hog fed on grain, is a fool, because that is bound to mean suffering.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Then the Buddha went on: `Great King, it is wise to observe moderation in food, because that way lies contentment. A man who is abstemious in eating will grow old slowly and will not have a lot of physical trouble and discomfort.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Poor Pasenadí, however, could not discipline himself, so the Buddha called the King's nephew, Prince Sudassana, and requested him to help. He told the prince the advice he had given to Pasenadí and asked him to watch the King whenever he had a meal. Whenever the King was about to seize the last handful of rice in his dish the prince should stop him and remind him of the Buddha's advice. Then for the King's next meal Sudassana should prepare only as much rice as had been left at the previous one. The King co-operated enthusiastically in this training-indeed, he even penalised his gluttony by giving away a thousand pieces of money in alms each time be had to be reminded of the Buddha's words-and soon he had reduced his consumption of rice to a modest potful a day. Transformed by this regime into a lean and energetic figure of a man, the King went to thank the Buddha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            `Now I am happy again,' he said. `Once more I am able to go hunting and catch wild animals and horses. In the past I used to quarrel with my nephew, but now we are on such good terms that I have given him my own daughter in marriage. Then the other day a precious stone belonging to my household was lost; this has now been found and returned, to my great joy. Moreover, in order to create closer friendship with your community I have given the daughter of one of your kinsmen a place in my household, and that has caused me much pleasure.' Such an extravagant testimonial to the advantages of a starch-reduced diet could hardly be improved on by the devotees of today's slimming cult.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            King Pasenadí, the champion of the balanced diet, also figures in a story meant to illustrate balanced judgement. This serves to show, if nothing else, that moderation, common serve, restraint, these characteristics of the spiritually mature outlook, apply to all a man's activities and should underlie his whole personality; they are not merely a code of discipline. One day when visiting the Buddha, King Pasenadí saw a group of ascetics walking along the road. With proper reverence, the King got up and saluted them respectfully. Then when they had gone he turned to the Buddha and asked him : `Do you think there were among those ascetics any that could be considered saints?' To this somewhat naive question the Buddha first pointed out that such a judgement would be difficult for a man of the world to make, caught up as he is in the life of the passions and preoccupied with matters like property. Then he went on:
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `It is only by dealing thoroughly with a man, and over a long period, that you can know about his virtue. It is not something to be discovered by a moment's thought, nor can a fool learn it, only a wise man.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `It is by long association with a man that his integrity can be judged. It is in times of trouble that a man's fortitude becomes apparent. And it is in dealing with a man, conversing with him extensively, that one is able to tell how wise he is.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            The Buddha claimed no supernatural ability in evaluating his fellow men; his judgement was the fruit of experience, maturity and, above all, self-knowledge. The same balance characterised his attitude to praise and criticism, even wljen he himself was the subject.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Once the Buddha was on a journey with a company of monks. Travelling along the same road a little way behind were two ascetics, Suppiya and his pupil Brahmadatta, who belonged to a different school. As they walked, Suppiya and Brahmadatta were arguing about the Buddha, his doctrine and his Order. Suppiya was inclined to be critical, but Brahmadatta, with the enthusiasm of youth, was all praise. They stopped for the night at the same rest house as the Buddha and his followers, but their dispute continued, and some of the monks overheard it. Upset that they should be the subject of such comment these monks the following morning began to talk among themselves. Eventually the argument came to the Buddha's notice.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `My brothers,' he said to them, `why are you unhappy and angry to hear people criticise me, or my doctrine or the Order? Such anger and unhappiness will only come in the way of your own self-conquest. If you get annoyed when others speak against you, how can you properly weigh the validity of what they say? When people talk critically about us you should examine what they say to find out what is not valid and then point it out, giving the reasons. Similarly, if anyone speaks approvingly of me, of my doctrine or of the Order, there is no cause to feel overjoyed. You should simply acknowledge whatever is correctly said and say why it is correct. After all, when people offer me praise, it is usually in respect of inessential matters, trivial aspects of behaviour, not the things that are really important.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            A tale with a similar theme is told about a zealous lay disciple called Atula. Atula, who had many friends, lived at Savatthi, and one day he suggested to his friends that they go to the monastery to listen to a discourse. They first encountered a monk called Revata and, saluting hirrl respectfully, sat down near him expecting he would address them. Revata, however, was a solitary, contemplative type, and had nothing to say to them.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Disappointed, they got up and went to see Sariputta, the famous exponent of the doctrine. Sariputta was only too glad to oblige them and launched into a lengthy and detailed discourse on philosophy. But this did not satisfy Atula and his friends either, for they found it abstruse and tedious.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            They decided to try once more, and found themselves in the company of Ananda. They explained why they had come, and how they had not got what they wanted from either Revata or Sariputta. So Ananda attempted a compromise and gave them a brief discourse expressed in simple language. But still they were not content, and finally they went to complain to the Buddha. This is what he had to say:
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Throughout history it has been the practice of men to criticise other men. A man who says nothing is liable to be criticised, as is a man who says a great deal or a man who says neither too little nor too much. Everyone comes in for blame, as well as praise; even kings do. The great earth, the sun, the moon. I myself sitting and speaking in the assembly, are criticised by some and praised by others. But praise and blame bestowed idly are of no account. It is the praise or blame of the truly discerning man that matters.'</paragraph>
            </section>

<section title="Intellectual Prowess">
    <paragraph>
            The Buddha was certainly not averse to philosophic speculation and, as his career amply demonstrates, even allowing for legendary embellishment, he possessed a mind as agile as any of his time. Also, some sort of philosophical structure was necessary for his teaching, if only to relate it to contemporary doctrines. But it emerges clearly from the accounts of his life that he regarded the value of such speculation as strictly limited and that he mistrusted it in general as potentially a distraction from the pursuit of the spiritual life. The core of his teaching is that, as everyone can see for himself, the human condition is rooted in suffering, but that with appropriate discipline and effort it is possible to achieve release from this suffering and discover a fulfilment beyond description in terms of ordinary human experience. When he speaks, as he often does, about the “Truth”, he means this fulfilment, not a description or explanation of objective reality; indeed, implicit in the whole effort of seeking that experience is the conviction that, on its achievement, objective reality as it is generally understood will become irrelevant. This, it may well be argued, is begging the question, for how can one be confident about a method of procedure before putting the method to the test? Such an objection would itself be condemned as irrelevant by the Buddha, since he would regard every minute or hour spent on pondering alongsuch lines as so much delay in the process of gaining spiritual insight. We are here concerned with faith.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            There are many stories and parables to illustrate the Buddha's impatience with philosophical argument. One concerns the monk Malunkyaputta. Malunkyaputta had a restless mind and his meditation was constantly disturbed by universal questions to which he felt he was entitled to have an answer from the Buddha. But every time he raised them, the Buddha shrugged them off without a satisfactory explanation. Finally he could stand the uncertainty no longer and went to the Buddha with an ultimatum : either he received a proper reply or he left the Order and returned to lay life. He then pedantically spelt out the problems that were troubling him. Is the universe eternal or not? Is the universe finite or infinite? Is the soul identical with the body or are they separate? And so on.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `You have failed to give me answers to these questions, and this upsets me,' he said. `If the Blessed One will explain these matters to me I shall continue to follow the holy life under him, but if not I shall leave the Order and go away. After all, if the Blessed One knows that the universe is eternal, why not say so: if he does not know, well then it is quite in order to admit it straightforwardly and say "I don't know".'
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            The Buddha first admonished Malunkyaputta for attempting to blackmail him. `Did I ever say to you: "Come, Malunkyaputta, lead the holy life under me and I will make plain such matters to you"?' he asked. He then went on to tell Malunkyaputta a parable.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Imagine a man who is struck by a poisoned arrow. His friends and relatives rush him to a surgeon, but before they do anything the man says: "I will not let this arrow be removed until I know who was the man who shot me; whether he belongs to the Kshatriya or Brahmin or Vaishya or Sudra caste; what are his name and clan; whether he is tall, short or of medium height; whether he is dark in complexion or brown or yellowish; from which village or town he comes. And I must know what kind of bow was used to shoot the arrow; what sort of bowstring was used; the type of arrow; the kind of feather that was used on the arrow and with what the arrow was tipped."</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            `Malunkyaputta, that man would die before he could know any of these things. The same is the case of anyone who says he will not devote himself to the holy life until he knows the answer to such questions as whether the universe is eternal and finite.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            The Buddha went on to explain that the holy life does not depend on such questions. Whatever conclusion one may reach about them, the essential facts of life remain-birth, old age, decay, death, sorrow, pain, lamentation and `the cessation of these things which I declare to be possible in this life'.
           </paragraph>
           <paragraph> `Therefore, Malunkyaputta, accept whatever I have explained and do not concern yourself with what I have not explained. Those questions which you raise, why have I not attempted to give you an answer? Because they are not of any use or relevance to the spiritual life. They do not help you to achieve detachment, tranquillity, deep realisation and ultimately Nirvana. What have I told you about? I have told you about unhappiness, the cessation of unhappiness and the way to bring about that cessation. And I have told you about these because they are fundamental to the spiritual life.'
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>In similar vein the Buddha once began talking to some of his monks while they were sitting in a grove of simsapa trees. Gathering up a few simsapa leaves in his hand the Buddha said to the monks : `Which are more numerous, the leaves in my hand or those in the trees overhead?'
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            `There are far more in the trees,' replied the monks.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            `Such is the comparison between the truths I have realised and revealed to you ,pd those which I have not revealed,' said the Buddha. `Those things which I have not revealed are not useful to the pure life and do not assist your spiritual progress. What I have revealed is the nature of unhappiness and how to overcome it, for these are truths that lead to Nirvana.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Not surprisingly, the Buddha also had little patience with dogmatism. If philosophical speculation is essentially futile, how much more so is preoccupation with theological dogma. This attitude is amusingly demonstrated in one of the bestknown stories relating to the Buddha, a story that has probably been heard by many people in one form or another even if they do not connect it with Buddhism.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            On one occasion a number of ascetics and learned men were gathered at Savatthi, while the Buddha was residing there., They began to discuss philosophical matters and soon they were busily debating the same sort of questions as those that had so agitated Malunkyaputta-whether the world is eternal and infinite, whether body and soul are separate, whether perfection is attainable during life, and so on. The argument became so heated that it moved from the academic level to one of personal abuse. Eventually the Buddha was summoned to intervene, and he dealt with the situation by telling the following parable.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            “There was once a king who, seeking some entertainment for himself, had a number of people who had been blind since birth brought together in front of him. An elephant was then led in and made to stand in the midst of them, and they were instructed to reach out so as to feel the part of the animal nearest them. Accordingly some felt its head, some an ear, some a tusk, while others felt its trunk or its foot or its tail, and one felt the tuft on the end of its tail. The king then asked the blind men in turn to say what they thought an elephant resembled. Those who had felt its ample, hard head said: `An elephant is like a cooking pot.' Those who had felt an ear said: `Like a basket for winnowing grain.' A tusk suggested a ploughshare, the trunk the shaft of a plough, a leg a pillar, the tail a pestle, while the man who had felt only the tuft of the tail said: `An elephant is like a broom.' A great argument developed among the holders of these varying opinions and before long they came to blows, to the huge amusement of the king. Such, explained the Buddha, is the case of people who have seen one aspect of reality and then dogmatically suppose that they have seen the whole reality.”</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            An elephant simile is used by the Buddha in another parable in which patience and humility are recommended in the pursuit of truth. An ordinary, unskilled man goes into a forest and sees a large footprint. That, he says to himself, must be the footprint of the great royal elephant. But the skilled tracker who sees the print is more cautious. Such a footprint could have been made by a stunted cow elephant treading heavily. The tracker looks around for other evidence. He sees that branches high up have been broken off by the elephant's shoulders. He still does not assume, however, that the great royal elephant was responsible until he has found enough further evidence to satisfy all his doubts. Only then does he say: `Yes, this is the footprint of the great royal elephant itself.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Similarly, said the Buddha, spiritual progress is achieved in stages and one should not allow oneself to think that perfection has been achieved at any stage while it is possible to persevere further.</paragraph>
        </section>
<section title="Self-Reliance &amp; Questioning Attitude">
                <paragraph>
            Buddhism is not for those who like to be told how to order their lives, who look constantly for guidance to an outside authority, whether in the form of priest, scripture or ritual. Throughout the Buddha's teaching, along with his insistence on balance and common sense, there is an implied obligation on each individual to think things out for himself, to make up his own mind and take his own moral decisions. Naturally there has to be a framework, and this the Buddha provides with the eight-fold path. But the doctrine of karma requires each man ultimately to be responsible for his own salvation; it is no use looking for an insurance policy either in observance of safe formulas or in total inactivity.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            On one occasion the Buddha visited a town called Kesaputta which seems to have been a popular spot for ascetics and religious teachers. The local people, known as Kalamas, were perplexed because each teacher who came to talk to them expounded his own particular doctrine and tore to shreds the doctrines of everybody else. When the Buddha arrived they approached him with the challenging question: `How are we to tell which of all these learned men who address us is telling us the truth?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            The Buddha replied : `You are quite right to feel doubts and uncertainty. In making up your minds about the validity of a doctrine do not rely only on what you have heard said about it, upon reputation or upon rumours; nor should you depend on scriptures, or axioms or specious reasoning; nor upon the seeming cleverness of the teacher, nor should you simply assume that because a man is an ascetic he is a worthy teacher. You have to know inside yourselves what things are bad, what things would be censured by a wise man and which, if pursued, would lead to harm and ill.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Some will object that this again is begging the question and, like the Kalamas, demand some absolute standard of judgement. Certainly the extent of sectarianism and intolerance in the world does not seem to have diminished in the two and a half millennia since the Buddha answered the Kalamas. But the Buddha's reply to such an objection would be to direct attention inward, to the human factors of desire, anger, delusion and so on which impede the exercise of sound judgement, and this was indeed what he did with the Kalamas, reportedly to their eventual satisfaction.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            It goes without saying that for the Buddha to allow any kind of personality cult to develop around him would have been quite inconsistent with the spirit of his teaching. Nevertheless, since respect and reverence, particularly in the religious context, can easily lead to hero-worship and even deification, the Buddha is at pains on a number of occasions to stress that what matters is his teaching, not himself as an individual.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            While travelling near Rajagaha at what must have been an early stage in his missionary career, the Buddha stopped for overnight shelter in a potter's shed. Also spending the night there was a young recluse, and the Buddha began talking to him. `Of which teacher are you a follower?' he began, since those who took up the holy life generally identified themselves with one school or another.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            Not knowing who the other man was, the young man, by name Pukkusati, replied: `There is a recluse called Gautama, a scion of the Sakya royal family who left his home for the religious life. He is very well spoken of and it is said he is a saint, a fully enlightened one. It is in his name that I have decided to become a recluse, and I regard him as my master and his doctrine as the one I wish to follow.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            `Have you ever seen him, this Enlightened One? Would you recognise him if you saw him?' asked the Buddha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            `No, I have never seen him, and I should not recognise him if I saw him,' said Pukkusati.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Thereupon the Buddha, without revealing who he was, offered to explain his doctrine, and the young man readily agreed. Only towards the end of the discourse did Pukkusati begin to realise that it was being delivered by the Buddha himself and when it was over he bowed down to his master, apologising for not knowing him and asking to be ordained into the Sangha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            In order to be ordained, Pukkusati needed to have an alms bowl and robes, but while he was out trying to obtain these he was attacked by a cow and killed. When the Buddha heard this he praised Pukkusati as a wise man who had grasped the truth and who had been sincerely concerned with the doctrine rather than the teacher.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            A story with a similar moral is told about a young man of Savatthi called Vakkali. The Buddha spent much of his time in Savatthi and seeing him coming and going in the town Vakkali developed what can only be described as an infatuation for him. Whenever he saw the Buddha he was overcome with admiration. One day Vakkali said to himself: `As long as I remain living at home I cannot see the Buddha as often as I should like, so I had better go to the monastery and become a monk. Then I can see him every day.' Duly he went to the monastery and was ordained.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Vakkali was now able to admire the Buddha as much as he wanted and followed him like a shadow, gazing at him with unvarying adulation. The Buddha was aware of this but said nothing, preferring to wait until Vakkali was a little older. After a few years, when he thought he had matured sufficiently, the Buddha said to Vakkali: `Vakkali, what is the use of gazing all the time at my body, which is something transient and impermanent? If you really want to see me, look at my teaching.' N
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            However, this had no effect, so the Buddha decided to be firm. One day he was invited to go for three months to Rajagaha, and when Vakkali got up to go with him he told him: `No, Vakkali, you cannot come with me. I have to go alone.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Deeply disappointed, Vakkali returned to his cell and began to wonder how he could pass three months without seeing his hero. He decided he could not, and climbed to the top of a mountain with the intention of throwing himself to his death. At this point the Buddha miraculously appeared to him to explain that only through his teaching could happiness be achieved, and Vakkali at last realised the folly of his ways.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            There is nothing academic about the Buddha's moral teaching; it is firmly rooted in experience of human nature and it was regularly put to the test during his leadership of the Sangha. Monks, it would seem, are no less liable to jealousy, quarrelling and petty-mindedness than anyone else. Dealing with the tensions that arose within the Sangha must have been one of the Buddha's more common tasks, and on at least one occasion it appears he became thoroughly disgusted by the behaviour of his followers.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            A dispute over a small matter concerning the rules of hygiene broke out at a monastery in Kosambi between two senior members of the Order, one a leading exponent of the Doctrine, the other a specialist in the Discipline. The issue was taken up by the respective pupils of these two men and soon it grew into an open quarrel involving other monks, nuns, lay supporters and even some people who were not followers of the Buddha at all. At one stage the Discipline man pronounced excommunication against the Doctrine man for allegedly refusing to acknowledge his original breach of the hygiene rules. The Buddha sent a message to the Kosambi monastery asking the monks to stop quarrelling, and when that did not work he went there in person. But still they would not listen, so, disheartened, the Buddha went away. He wandered off alone, and settled down for the rainy season in a forest called Parileyya, where he was befriended by an elephant.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Hearing that the Buddha had abandoned the monks to their squabbling the lay Buddhists of Kosambi withdrew their support from the monks. This brought the monks to their senses and they hastily apologised to the lay supporters. The latter, however, refused to accept any apology until the monks had made their peace with the Buddha, and as it was now the rainy season they could not go in search of him. They thus spent the next few weeks in some misery.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            The description of the Buddha's stay in Parileyya forest contrasts sharply with the discord experienced by his followers in Kosambi. The elephant not only protected the Buddha from the danger of wild animals but went with him to beg for alms, carrying his bowl and robe on his head. One day a monkey added his services to that of the elephant by collecting some wild honey and giving it to the Buddha to eat. This was an idyllic period showing the Buddha in harmony with nature.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Meanwhile, it became known that the Buddha was staying in the forest, attended by a noble elephant, and in the city of Savatthi some of the leading figures, including Anathapindaka, approached Ananda and asked him to persuade the Buddha to return so that the trouble with the monks at Kosambi could be resolved. Accompanied by a large number of monks, Ananda went to the forest. The Buddha greeted them with the somewhat bitter words : `When one has intelligent companions worth associating with, who lead a good life, then one should live with them happily and co-operatively. Otherwise live alone like a king who has abandoned his kingdom, or an elephant in the forest. There is no companionship with a fool; it is better to be alone.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Nevertheless, he agreed to return with them to Savatthi. The parting with the elephant, incidentally, is portrayed as a poignant scene, with the animal weeping bitterly. When the Buddha was back in the Jetavana monastery, at Savatthi, the Kosambi monks came to beg his pardon. By this time, however, they were thoroughly unpopular. The King of Kosala threatened not to allow them into his territory, and Anathapindaka was reluctant to let them enter the Jetavana monastery. When the monks finally did arrive they were given separate lodgings, and were treated with overt contempt by the other monks. But the Buddha himself showed no vindictiveness. `These monks are good people,' he told the King of Kosala and Anathapindaka. `It is only because of a dispute among themselves that they paid no attention to my words.' When they came before him, ashamed and contrite, and threw themselves at his feet, the Buddha admonished them and then gave them a simple lesson: `Some people do not realise that quarrels will fade away by themselves. If you know this you will cease to have dissension.'
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            Perhaps the most dramatic example of the Buddha's principles coming face to face with human reality is the occasion when he prevented a war. The Sakyans and the Koliyans were neighbours separated by the river Rohini, and jointly they dammed the river in order to irrigate their fields on each side. In the month of June, however, at the hottest time of the year, the river was running low and the crops began to droop. The Koliyans began to talk of diverting the water to their exclusive use, since there would not be enough for both of them, but the Sakyans would have none of this. Tempers rose and abuse was exchanged. One or two people came to blows, and eventually the two parties brought out their armies.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            At this stage the Buddha came to know about the argument. It was a particularly delicate situation for him to become involved in since he was related to both clans-being the son of a Sakyan king and a Koliyan princess-but he saw it as his duty to intervene. There is an ironical comment on the nature of warmongering, how it comes to take on its own momentum regardless of the original reason, in the story of how he approached the site of the dispute and asked his kinsmen what all the trouble was about; no one of any rank was able to tell him what the quarrel was really about until he asked some of the slave labourers-the people lowest in the hierarchy-who told him `Water'. The Buddha then went to the King and asked: `How much is water worth, great King?' `Very little,' replied the King. `And how much are the lives of your people worth,' the Buddha continued. `Oh, they are beyond price,' said the King. `Well,' said the Buddha, `is it right that for the sake of a little water you should destroy so many lives that are beyond price?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>

            The Buddha then went on to address both sides as follows `Great Kings, why do you act in this way? Were I not here today you would have started a river of blood flowing. You live in enmity and hatred. I live free from hatred. You live afflicted with the sickness of evil passions. I live free from such disease. You spend your lives in eager pursuit of sensual pleasures, whereas I do not. If we want to live happily, let us live without hate among men who hate. Let us live in good health among those who are sick. Let us live free from care among those who are careworn.'</paragraph>
            </section>
    </appendix>
</book>