<book>
    <appendix index="2" title="Khentin Tai Situpa's song: The Twelve Deeds of the Buddha">
        <verse title="The Twelve Deed%s% &#xA; o%f% the Bu%d%d%ha%" linenumberfrequency="0" font="poeticaFour" author="@(person)Khentin Tai Situpa@">
            <stanza index="1" flagtext="1">
                <line indent="0" line-length="yes">Because you could hear the saddening cries of suffering</line>
                <line indent="0">And the calling of your children from a ripening world,</line>
                <line indent="0">To fulfil the hopes and wishes of those beings,</line>
                <line indent="0">To bring them to happiness and show virtue's worth,</line>
                <line indent="0">With limitless love and fearless resolution</line>
                <line indent="0">From the highest of pure lands, you emanated to Earth.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="2" flagtext="2">
                <line indent="0">Seeing Jambudvipa, our planet, in extraordinary vision,</line>
                <line indent="0">A mother who could bear you, a father a great king,</line>
                <line indent="0">With courage that was born of the deepest conviction</line>
                <line indent="0">In the benefit that your life as a human would bring,</line>
                <line indent="0">Amidst miracles and wonders, you entered the womb</line>
                <line indent="0">Of noble Mahamaya, King Suddhodhana's Queen.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="3" flagtext="3">
                <line indent="0">Born painlessly from her right side in the grove of Lumbini,</line>
                <line indent="0">With the special signs of a Buddha your body was marked.</line>
                <line indent="0">You took seven steps in each of the principal directions</line>
                <line indent="0">And at each step a lotus-flower sprang up from the earth,</line>
                <line indent="0">The King of Gods came to make his humble prostration</line>
                <line indent="0">As you declared yourself most high in the whole universe.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="4" flagtext="4">
                <line indent="0">Understanding with precision the qualities of all things,</line>
                <line indent="0">The play of phenomena, with insight so deep,</line>
                <line indent="0">That your prowess transcended all human expectation</line>
                <line indent="0">Whilst in all of the arts you were always supreme,</line>
                <line indent="0">Also brilliant in each of the sciences you became</line>
                <line indent="0">The most wise and gifted, youth that man has ever seen.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="5" flagtext="5">
                <line indent="0">To fulfil the dreams of your father and your people</line>
                <line indent="0">In the city of Kapila you took as your bride</line>
                <line indent="0">King Suppa's daughter, Yasodhara, Princess of the Sakyas,</line>
                <line indent="0">A jewel amongst maidens, fit to stand at your side.</line>
                <line indent="0">Tasting life's riches with not the slightest involvement —</line>
                <line indent="0">A perfect prince with all the joys that the world could provide.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="6" flagtext="6">
                <line indent="0">Seeing all that appears in Samsara's three dimensions</line>
                <line indent="0">As just the sadness of sickness, birth, old-age and death,</line>
                <line indent="0">Knowing how worthless is all comfort and royalty,</line>
                <line indent="0">Preferring the calm of the forest in its stead,</line>
                <line indent="0">Without an instant of clinging, you mounted Kantaka</line>
                <line indent="0">And with heartfelt renunciation from the palace you sped.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="7" flagtext="7">
                <line indent="0">The river Neranjara is cool and slow-running</line>
                <line indent="0">By its banks all majestic ease was cast aside.</line>
                <line indent="0">With rock for a cushion, in the utmost simplicity,</line>
                <line indent="0">You practised absorption of body, speech and mind,</line>
                <line indent="0">Sitting without moving in the shade of a tall tree,</line>
                <line indent="0">For six years, enduring hardship, the highest truth to find.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="8" flagtext="8">
                <line indent="0">In the absolute sense, you were always the Buddha,</line>
                <line indent="0">With nothing to purify, from all obscuration free,</line>
                <line indent="0">The perfection and union of all the finest qualities,</line>
                <line indent="0">But to show, in the relative, the great necessity</line>
                <line indent="0">Of developing virtue and wisdom, you went to</line>
                <line indent="0">The Noble Seat of Achievement, beneath the Bodhi Tree.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="9" flagtext="9">
                <line indent="0">Being jealous of your power and your all-embracing wisdom,</line>
                <line indent="0">Of your matchlessly-peaceful harmonious state,</line>
                <line indent="0">Of the way you would lead us to all forms of happiness,</line>
                <line indent="0">The forces of darkness boiled with anger and hate</line>
                <line indent="0">Subduing without malice their nightmarish onslaught,</line>
                <line indent="0">In one instant of your love, all evil was tamed.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="10" flagtext="10">
                <line indent="0">On the full moon of Vesak beneath the tree at Bodh Gaya,</line>
                <line indent="0">The very heart of our planet, of all places holiest,</line>
                <line indent="0">In the splendour of the sunrise of that glorious morning,</line>
                <line indent="0">The ultimate of everything you saw, just as it is,</line>
                <line indent="0">Through your perfect awakening and total realisation,</line>
                <line indent="0">You became the peerless guide for all that lives.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="11" flagtext="11">
                <line indent="0">In the natural wild beauty of the forest near Benares</line>
                <line indent="0">And in other worldly places, worldly beings heard you preach</line>
                <line indent="0">The path you had travelled - eighty-four thousand dharmas,</line>
                <line indent="0">Whilst in exceptional places the gifted heard you teach</line>
                <line indent="0">The extraordinary truth of the transcendent meaning:</line>
                <line indent="0">Thus you revealed to mankind the profound path of peace.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDHA+</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="12" flagtext="12">
                <line indent="0">Though far beyond any notion of 'staying' or 'going',</line>
                <line indent="0">To clarify the wrong views of those who believd</line>
                <line indent="0">In the eternal or in 'nothing' you passed from the sight f</line>
                <line indent="0">Those humans whose good fortune to see you had cease.</line>
                <line indent="0">Laying your right side to the earth of Kushinaa</line>
                <line indent="0">You dissolved into the vastness of universal peace.</line>
                <line indent="0">+GREAT IS THE BUDDA+</line>
            </stanza>
        </verse>
    </appendix>
</book>