<book>
    <appendix index="4" title="The Thirty-Two Special Marks of a Buddha">
        <paragraph>
# The feet are perfectly even and marked with dharma-wheels of a thousand 'spokes'. This is the outcome of the bodhisattva's proper taking, and keeping, of commitments, as well as his or her respect for teachers and the gathering of much virtue.
# The feet are broad and the ankles do not protrude. This is the outcome of enacting innumerable virtuous deeds.
# The fingers and toes are long. This is the outcome of giving protection to beings who would otherwise have been killed.
# The digits of hands and feet are slightly webbed. This is the outcome of former peace-making.
# His skin is soft and his flesh fine and youthful. This is the outcome of former generosity to the poor and hungry.
# His body has seven elevated parts, i.e. the backs of the hands, feet and shoulders and the nape of the neck are all nicely full and rounded. This is the outcome of giving food and drink to the needy.
# His calves are like those of an antelope, i.e. strong, solid and muscular. This is the outcome of a thorough mastery of all five branches of Buddhist learning.
# His private parts are recessed, like those of an elephant. This is the outcome of always maintaining confidentiality.
# His torso is like that of a lion, i.e. broad and majestic. This is the outcome of looking after other beings with great ethical care.
# His clavicles are not hollow but well-filled with flesh. This is another outcome of former generosity, especially that of giving medicines to the sick.
# The tops of the shoulders have elegant curves. This is the outcome of right speech, which eased the fears and worries of others, and only used kind and appropriate words.
# The arms are soft, round and even. This is the outcome of always being a friend for beings.
# The arms are long, the hands reaching down to the knees. This is the outcome of always striving to fulfil others' expectations.
# His perfectly pure body is surrounded by an aura of light. This is the outcome of relentless efforts to practice the ten virtues.
# His neck is as immaculate as a perfect conch. This analogy refers to the resemblance between the three fine lines on the Buddha's throat to those of the spirals on a conch. They are a sign of the Buddha's perfect ability to teach all 84,000 aspects of dharma. They are also a specific outcome of serving the sick and providing them with medicines.
# His cheeks are as magnificent as those of a lion. This is the outcome of never wasting the power of speech, through useless chatter, but instead using it to guide people into what is good and wholesome, and particularly into Buddhist practice.
# He has forty teeth, twenty on each jaw. This is the outcome of  treating everyone with equal kindness, as they have all been former parents. It is also the result of overcoming harsh speech.
# His teeth are very white and beautifully aligned. This is the outcome of always speaking truthfully and so as to create harmony.
# The teeth are immaculate and evenly aligned, i.e. they are without mark or defect and harmoniously aligned as far as their length is concerned. This is the outcome of giving away possessions and gaining a livelihood honestly.
# The eye-teeth are perfect and brilliantly white. This is the outcome of former physical, verbal and mental actions being perfectly honest and straightforward.
# His tongue is long, unending and inconceivable. The tongue, like the head-mound, gives the impression of endlessness to those who see it.[1] This is because the Buddha can declare the profound meaning of voidness, and it is the outcome of speaking sweetly and softly.
# There is the most perfect faculty of taste. Everything that the Buddha eats has the most exquisite taste. This is the outcome of always providing solutions which were agreeable to beings and finding effective answers to their problems.
# The Spontaneously Born has a voice as sweet as that of the kalavinka bird or as Brahmä. This is the outcome of always speaking in a pleasing, peaceful voice that proclaimed the truth, in a way which was relevant and meaningful to beings.
# The Supreme Being has beautiful eyes, like blue lotuses. This is the outcome of always looking upon other beings with the loving concern of a mother for her only child.
# The eyelashes are as handsome as those of an ox, i.e. long and beautiful and neatly separated (not glued in little bunches).  This is the outcome of overcoming anger and hypocrisy in dealings with others.
# With its immaculate white 'treasure-hair', his face is handsome to behold. The Buddha's face is very clear and radiant. Those who see it are deeply moved by its great beauty. It has the treasure hair, which is very long (more than one metre), white and curled into a tight swirl in the brow. This is often represented by a simple dot on the Buddha's forehead in paintings and statues. These signs are the outcome of always treating special beings, such as other bodhisattvas, with respect.
# His head is adorned with a mound. In fact, those who look at the Buddha's head can never see where its upper part ends. It goes up and up, beyond the deva realms and out of sight. This is the outcome of devotion and service to gurus and other teachers and bodhisattvas, while himself a bodhisattva.
# His skin is pure and fine. This is the outcome of always striving to do good and to make the mind flexible and manageable.
# His skin is golden-hued. This is the outcome of always serving the Buddhas and making offerings to them.
# The hairs on his body are exceedingly fine and soft, one in each pore, spiralling to the right and upwards. This is the outcome of always meditating to make the mind manageable and applicable to all tasks, as well as of diligent effort in bringing the tasks to a proper conclusion.
# His hair is impeccable and like a deep blue gem. This could have originally meant that his dark hair had a beautiful blue sheen, like dark sapphire, although it is sometimes taken literally and Buddha statues often have the hair painted blue. This is the outcome of always acting with loving kindness.
# As well-rounded as a perfect nyagrodha tree, the Ever-Good, the incomparable Great Sage, has the strength of Narayana in his firm body. This last mark applies to the whole body. The nyagrodha tree is well known for its harmonious proportions and straightness. Narayana is another name for Vishnu, renowned for his strength.

fn1. As it is impossible to portray an infinite head mound, artists usually depict it as a large bump on the Buddha's head, but this is not how it appears to those who see the Buddha.

      </paragraph>
      <paragraph>All these marks shine with their own radiance and steal away the mind of the beholder with their beauty and sense of profundity, making one know that one is in the presence of the Supreme of Beings; in the presence of something beyond the grasp of one's mind. They were taught by the Buddha himself as beings the signs of an Enlightened One. Although some other great beings have several signs similar to these, at least in description, they are not the same. Nor are they complete.
      </paragraph>
  </appendix>
</book>