<book>
    <appendix index="3" title="The Special Marks of a Buddha">
        <verse title="The Thirt%y%-Tw%o% Mark%s% &#xA; o%f% a Per%f%ect Bein%g%" linenumberfrequency="0" font="poeticaNine" author="@(person)Maitreya@ on @(sutra:Thirty-Two Marks of a Perfect Being)Buddha Nature@">
            <stanza index="1" flagtext="257">
                <line indent="0">Perfectly level and marked with wheels,</line>
                <line indent="1">his feet are broad and his ankles not protruding.</line>
                <line indent="0">Long are his fingers and his toes, webbed.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="2" flagtext="258">
                <line indent="0">Soft is his skin and fine his youthful flesh,</line>
                <line indent="1">his body having seven elevated parts.</line>
                <line indent="0">Like an antelope's are his calves</line>
                <line indent="1">and like an elephant's are his private parts recessed.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="3" flagtext="259">
                <line indent="0" line-length="yes">His torso is like a lion's and his clavicles not hollow but well-filled.</line>
                <line indent="0">His shoulders are elegantly rounded;</line>
                <line indent="1">rounded, soft and even are his arms.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="4" flagtext="260">
                <line indent="0">His arms are long and his perfectly pure body</line>
                <line indent="1">is surrounded by an aura of light.</line>
                <line indent="0">His neck, like a conch, is rounded and without blemish</line>
                <line indent="1">and his cheeks are like those of a king of beasts.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="5" flagtext="261">
                <line indent="0">Equal are his forty teeth. They are very pure, closely set,</line>
                <line indent="1">immaculate and evenly aligned;</line>
                <line indent="2">the eye-teeth are perfect and excellently white.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="6" flagtext="262">
                <line indent="0">His tongue is long, unending and inconceivable,</line>
                <line indent="1">possessing the most perfect faculty of taste.</line>
                <line indent="0">The spontaneously born has a voice</line>
                <line indent="1">like the song of the kalavinka bird or like Brähma's melody.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="7" flagtext="263">
                <line indent="0">The supreme of beings has beautiful eyes, like blue lotuses,</line>
                <line indent="1">and like an ox's are his eyelashes.</line>
                <line indent="0">With its immaculate white treasure-hair,</line>
                <line indent="1">his face is handsome to behold.</line>
                <line indent="0">His head bears a mound and his skin is pure, fine and golden.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="8" flagtext="264">
                <line indent="0">The hairs on his body are exceeding fine and soft,</line>
                <line indent="1">one from each (pore) and curling to the right and to the top.</line>
                <line indent="0">His hair is impeccable and like a deep-blue gem.</line>
                <line indent="0">As well-rounded as a perfect nyagrodha tree.</line>
            </stanza>
            <stanza index="9" flagtext="265">
                <line indent="0">The ever-good and incomparable great sage has the strength</line>
                <line indent="1">of Narayana in his firm body. These two and thirty marks,</line>
                <line indent="2">vividly brilliant and beyond any concept's grasp,</line>
                <line indent="3">are taught by our Teacher as those of a lord of men.</line>
            </stanza>
        </verse>
    </appendix>
</book>