<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<book>
    <chapter index="9" title="Essential Contemplations - Impermanence, The Dharma arrives in Tibet &amp; The Eight Chariots">
        <section index="1" title="Preamble: Study, Meditation &amp; Life Experience">
            <paragraph>Jojo: 'What's the point of sitting meditating on something for months and years when the answer is already in the scriptures and you can learn it in minutes?'
Sammy: 'Yes, but what's the point of having all that good information when it doesn't actually seem to change us? Only meditation can do that by working directly and deeply with the mind.'
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Sometimes there is an unnecessary tug‐of‐war between *study* and *meditation*. Which is best? Which is best for me? The answer is that both are needed. They are often compared, in general, to the two wings of a bird, needed for flying (rather than getting into a flap and turning in circles!). However, as study and meditation cannot always be nurtured simultaneously, in actual practice there will be times and places for each.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It may be helpful to remember that lamas are human and that their levels of realisation vary enormously. Depending on their own lives, some may tend to over‐ privilege study while others only want to hear of meditation. They teach others through what they themselves have found a real benefit; the area in which they are most comfortable and can best guide followers. Practically, some great meditators are genuinely embarrassed by their lack of book learning and some great scholars are embarrassed by their lack of meditation attainment. They are understandably reluctant to teach what they don't know well. That is honourable. But a lama's preference can sometimes confuse the larger picture for followers, who will paint the whole dharma with their lama's brush. This is remedied by taking the great lineage holders as our models; then we can never go wrong. They are terrific exemplars of the benefits of *both* study and meditation and their life work is in promoting *both*.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The bottom line, in @(concept:vajrayana)Vajrayana Buddhism@, is that a good guru will counsel a person as to when it is time to put energy into study and when it is time to put it into meditating. This advice should be entirely based on what will help that person, at that time, and also what will help them help others, now or later.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The great @(person)Kalu Rinpoche@, who towards the end of the last century became the senior meditation guru for the @(concept:lineage!Kagyu!Karma)Karma Kagyu@ tradition, made it clear that meditation is the actual crux of the matter but that meditation without sufficient dharma knowledge was not only "no good" but potentially dangerous. This is because when difficult situations arise in meditation, the poorly‐informed meditator does not have sufficient dharma understanding to react intelligently and compassionately. (S)he can become very confused and things can go very wrong. This happens quite often.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Other than study and meditation, there is also a third dimension to be taken into account: *actual life experience*. This is a powerful @(concept:teacher)teacher@ but it takes time: time we do not always have.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In this chapter we shall be looking into impermanence. We'll _study_ it and have much information to hand afterwards. In the @(concept:meditation!mahamudra)Mahamudra@ training, many of us _meditate_ on it, as one of the @(concept:four contemplations)Four Ways of Changing the Mind@.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The main point of these @(concept:impermanence)impermanence@ teachings is to help us to cling less and to become more vividly aware of our mortality. However, many experienced Buddhists find that they have studied impermanence well and also devoted considerable time to meditating on it but it is only when someone close to them dies that the message of impermanence becomes lit up with a 500‐watt glow. It is only when their success or material wealth is suddenly lost, when the lover leaves or when the body loses its beauty or prowess that the utter truth of the Buddha's words resounds loudly.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>How many of us have not regretted what we have said or done to others, in the past? In retrospect, our vanity, self‐centredness, projections or @(concept:ignorance)ignorance@ all become so horribly clear—and we kick ourselves, thinking _If only, if only, I could have seen it like this at the time!_ The other people concerned are gone far away now, or are dead and buried, and nothing can be done except to learn the lesson. +That the lesson is learned is wonderful ...+ but life is so short and if we take life alone as our teacher, we may have to wait until our final days to gain some profound wisdom. Dharma is here to help us gain the insight as soon as possible, so that it informs the rest of our lives.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Nevertheless, nothing teaches as powerfully as real experience. Real experience cannot be faked ... but ... but ... we can meet it halfway, *by bringing our studies to life through meditation*. This involves taking the ideas we learn in our studies and using the imagination to the full to bring them to life—like going to the cinema and "living" the film—to explore their meaning and to try to penetrate what the Buddha and our lamas are trying to help us to understand, as quickly as is possible.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>@(concept:mindfulness)Mindful@, aware, intelligent observation of ourselves and the world around us feeds in powerful support for such reflections, as does the invaluable skill of being able to put ourselves in other's places. This is what the @(concept:four contemplations)Four Ways of Changing the Mind@ try to achieve: an awakening to reality that changes our lives. Its meditations on impermanence bring insights without having to wait for life to deal its various body‐blows. Profound contemplation of impermanence, of death, also prepares us for the actual events, when they happen. We will find a strength, in those times of chaos and sadness, that few humans have access to.</paragraph>
        </section>

        <section index="2" title="The Dharma Master's Instructions">
            <paragraph>Following the previous chapter's appreciation of our *precious human existence*, the next contemplation is that of @(concept:impermanence)*impermanence*@. This is one of the central topics of Buddhism. We shall study it by seeing impermanence as one of the four main components of a lama's instruction. Then we will look at the contemplations themselves, in detail.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Someone may piece together the teachings and realise that we all have buddha nature and that samsara has existed since time without beginning. Therefore it must have happened that, on various occasions, we had a precious human existence in which we met the dharma and good dharma masters. This poses the question, _What prevented me from becoming enlightened then?_ The answer that the Mahayana texts give is that the harmful mistakes of falling under the sway of four blockages prevented progress in those previous precious human lives. These four obstacles are what stand in everyone's way on the path to liberation.</paragraph>
            <paragraph style="highlight">*The @(concept:four impediments)four impediments@ that have prevented the attainment of budhahood are:*

# *Attachment to the experiences of this life.*
# *Attachment to worldly well‐being.*
# *Attachment to the well‐being of meditation's peace and stability.*
# *Sheer ignorance of the means by which buddhahood is achieved.*

These four impediments are eliminated by their remedies, and this involves taking to heart the appropriate instructions of dharma masters and putting those instructions into practice. The instruction comprises advice on:

# How to meditate on impermanence.
# How to meditate on the shortcomings of samsara and on actions and their consequences.
# How to cultivate love and compassion.
# How to cultivate bodhicitta.

            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>These will act as remedies in the following way:</paragraph>
            <table caption="Four Impediments &amp; Four Remedies">
                <tr>
                    <th>The Practice Of</th>
                    <th>Remedies</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Meditation on impermanence</td>
                    <td>attachment to the experiences of this life</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Meditation on the shortcomings of samsara</td>
                    <td>attachment to worldly well‐being (in general)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Meditation on love and compassion</td>
                    <td>attachment to the well‐being of (meditative) peace</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>The teaching on cultivating bodhicitta</td>
                    <td>ignorance of how to attain buddhahood</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <paragraph>@(person)Gampopa@ says of these four: "These cover every Mahayana teachings—from taking refuge up to the meaning of the two types of absence of self‐entity or from the five stages of the path and the ten levels down through all the teachings on bodhicitta."</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Some of these topics form the basis for @(concept:bodhicitta)bodhicitta@, some are its objective, some are the rituals connected with bodhicitta development, some are advice pertinent to bodhicitta, some concern its qualities and benefits and some represent its results. There is no Mahayana topic that is not included in the bodhicitta teachings. Those instructions stem from the dharma master: they depend on the dharma master. Thus the _Array of Trees Sutra_[1] says:

bq. The dharma master is the very source of all the teachings of virtue.

and

bq. Omniscience is dependent on the instruction given by dharma masters.

fn1. This is the _Gaṇḍavyūha sūtra_, part of the larger @(ref:Flower Ornament Sutra)_Flower Ornament Sutra_@ or _Buddhāvataṃsaka_.
            </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section title="Impermanence">
            <paragraph style="highlight">Without doubt, an enormous amount of human suffering is triggered by life's changes. Other people change; they come and go; their attitudes towards us change. The world around us changes. Our own bodies and minds change. Good fortune comes and goes, according to karma. In reality, the problem is not the change itself, because change is frequently inevitable, being the very nature of things. *Suffering happens because of an insufficient understanding of change and through not being emotionally mature in the face of change.* The Buddha, and hence our lamas, try to bring us to wisdom and maturity so that we become liberated from this huge area of unnecessary misery. The process can involve tackling life‐long attitudes.</paragraph>
            <paragraph style="highlight">Anything that comes into existence through the gathering of prime causes[2] and their supportive conditions[3] is known as a _composite phenomenon_. *In general, _every_ composite thing is impermanent*. Therefore the Buddha taught:

bq. Bhikkhus! All composites are impermanent.

How exactly are they impermanent? What is accumulated will eventually dwindle, what is built up will eventually disintegrate, whatever things or whichever people come together eventually will part and what lives eventually will die. Quoting the @(ref:Collection of Aphorisms)_Collection of Aphorisms_@:

bq.
The end of all accumulation is dispersal,
The end of construction is disintegration,
The end of meeting is parting and
The end of life is death.

fn2. Skt: hetu, Tib: rgyu, see Chapter Three, Page 9.
fn3. Skt: pratyaya, Tib: rkyen, see Module Three, Page 9.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph style="highlight">The teachings on impermanence are one of the foremost topics in Buddhist theory and one of the most important areas of its meditation. It is one of the _three marks of existence_[4].
fn4. Impermanence, suffering and no-self.</paragraph>
            <paragraph style="highlight">Meditation on impermanence is also the second of the Four Ways of Changing the Mind.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As mentioned in the previous chapter, each of these four contemplations needs to be worked on until there is a definite change of mind. And even that is just the beginning, like peeling back the first layer of the proverbial onion. There will be many more 'definite changes' as the implications of impermanence open the eyes of wisdom to the true nature of things and, by the same token, to the illusions with which the web of life and suffering has been woven by the diligent spider of confused mind.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
