<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book">
   <chapter index="1"
            title="The Life of the Illustrious One, The Totally&#xA;and Perfectly Enlightened Buddha; Guide and Protector for All Beings (Including&#xA;and Introduction toThe Three&#xA;Kayas)"
            pagetitle="Module 1"
            tocentry="The Life of the Illustrious One, The Totally&#xA;and Perfectly Enlightened Buddha; Guide and Protector for All Beings (Including&#xA;and Introduction toThe Three&#xA;Kayas)">
      <section index="1" title="The Buddha" pagetitle="The Buddha" tocentry="The Buddha">
         <paragraph>It
seems natural--obvious--in many ways, to begin our study of Buddhism by looking at
the life of the Buddha. In one way, we can say he was the wisest, kindest, most
liberated, most fulfilled and most beneficial human who ever existed. That is
why we follow his example and teachings. What "becoming a Buddha" really means is
something too deep for a regular biography, describing _external_ life
details of a person in the past. It would miss the point. Our whole Buddhist
path is one of discovering the true _inner_ meaning of what Sakyamuni
attained, because we too can attain it: a perfect mind.</paragraph>
         <subsection title="Etymology of Buddha" pagetitle="Etymology of Buddha"
                     tocentry="Etymology of Buddha">
            <paragraph>(eh)The Sanskrit root _budh_ has two
main meanings: *_to awaken_* and *_to flourish_*. A buddha
is someone (eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>(eh)*awakened* from the sleep of
     ignorance and(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)in whom enlightened qualities are *flourished*.
     (eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>Therefore,
when the Buddha's own disciples were speaking of _the Buddha_, they were
simply acknowledging their teacher as 'The Awakened One' and as 'The Complete
One'. The word _buddha_ had real meaning for them, whereas for us it is a
rather exotic, foreign word, evoking Indian imagery rather than a very real,
awakened, perfect state of mind. The same applies to the term _dharma_,
the word we use for the Buddha's teachings. That was simply the Sanskrit term
for _things, phenomena_. It sounds so exotic and mysterious to say _the
Buddha taught the dharma_ yet so down-to-earth to say _an awakened person
taught things as they really are_. The latter is precisely what people in
India were saying!</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Buddhas and Bodhisattvas" pagetitle="Buddhas and Bodhisattvas"
                     tocentry="Buddhas and Bodhisattvas">
            <paragraph>As
we will discover as this course develops, the terms_ buddha, enlightened one_
and so forth can be applied to *+all+* those who have an unfaltering
realisation of voidness<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>
(some say _emptiness_). In order to distinguish a totally-enlightened
being--such as the historical Buddha Shakyamuni--from the others, the Sanskrit
and Tibetan texts use strings of superlatives, meaning something like 'the
totally-pure, utterly-perfected enlightened one'. These are often dropped by
modern translators, in the interest of less laborious reading. They mainly use _Buddha_
for 'the totally-pure, utterly-perfected enlightened one' and _bodhisattva_
for other 'awakened ones' who have attained voidness yet not its fullness
extent and depth.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Different Versions of the Buddha's Life and Former Lives"
                     pagetitle="Different Versions of the Buddha's Life and Former Lives"
                     tocentry="Different Versions of the Buddha's Life and Former Lives">
            <paragraph>The Buddha's teachings flourished in India for some
seventeen centuries (5^th^ century BCE to 12^th^ century CE). Literacy was not nearly so
highly regarded in the first centuries of this period as it is in the West
today. In those days, anything of spiritual value was so greatly treasured that
had to be learnt by heart--and carried in the heart. Writing things down was
mainly a thing for merchants to do, to list their goods, and not for people of
religion. Thus Buddhism existed solely as
an oral tradition for centuries without being written down<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> and we
have no contemporary written accounts of the Buddha's life from either Buddhist
or non-Buddhist sources. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The earliest Buddhist writings were
those of the Pali Canon, set down in the 1^st^ century BCE because the
oral tradition of the Theravadins was becoming threatened at the time--there was
no more guarantee that all their teachings could be retained in the minds of
their communities. What was recorded then was the "original canon",+
as it was known by the Theravadins+. Research in Chinese and other sources
gives us certainty that other canons existed at the time, not identical to the
Pali one. These were set in writing later and +are not necessarily less
authentic because of that+.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
general; *we have two main ways of seeing the life of the Buddha: the
Theravadin<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>
way and the Mahayana<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a>
way*:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*The Theravadin way* sees the Buddha's life
     primarily as a human being's--Prince Gautama's--quest for truth. It is a
     dramatic, human story most people can relate to, without too much
     other-worldliness. The actual tale told comes from the scant information
     the Buddha gives us himself (in the sutras<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a>), spiced
     with many legends, some of them much older than others and perhaps
     therefore more likely to be true. The Theravadin tradition also has many
     stories of the Buddha's former lives, as _the bodhisattva _(the main,
     sometimes only, way they use this term), in the Jataka tales.(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*The Mahayana way* sees 'Buddha' in three
     ways:(eeh)</li>
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)*As the purity and perfection
      inside each and every one of us*--our *buddha nature*.
      Although already perfect, like a gemstone in its ore, it needs to be
      released and so exists for most people as only a _potential._(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)*As someone*--in this case, for our
      present world, Sakyamuni--*who has completely unfolded and realised that
      potential*. His journey from ordinariness to enlightenment, taking
      three cosmic aeons, was the "life" or "lives" of the Buddha.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)As a much deeper and more
      complete understanding of what the mind of Buddha actually was, for
      himself and for others:* the three_ kaya_.*(eeh)</li>
               </list>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)
Thus, concerning the life of Sakyamuni, we are learning about the final step of
a long spiritual journey which covered some three cosmic aeons, with him starting
out as a human, evolving from one worldly life to another worldly life. He then
transcends the world and matures through the bodhisattva levels as a mental
body of light in very pure dimensions of existence. The long evolution ends
with enlightenment being attained in the highest sphere of existence, from
which the Buddha spontaneously manifests the three _kaya<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a>_. One of these--the _nirmanakaya_--appears
in worlds such as our own, demonstrating the 'life of a buddha' in twelve major
deeds, each of which contributes to setting the stage perfectly for his
timeless, cosmic teachings to be well received and to endure for a long time. _The_
Buddha--Shakyamuni--was one of these 'supreme' nirmanakayas--the manifestation of
timeless, universal truth in our particular world of "Rose Apple Land"
(_Jambudvipa_), as it is called in the scriptures.(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="A general point: where to seek our Buddhist knowledge?"
                     pagetitle="A general point: where to seek our Buddhist knowledge?"
                     tocentry="A general point: where to seek our Buddhist knowledge?">
            <paragraph>(eh)In our Kagyu tradition, our greatest
contemporary teachers such as the Gyalwang Karmapa and the Kuangting Tai
Situpa, place great stress on the importance of _living lineage_ and of
adhering to traditional teachings which come directly from masters holding
authentic lineage. For that reason, as much as possible of the material
presented in this course will come from teachings given directly by the great
Kagyu masters at Kagyu Samye Ling in Scotland. There is tremendous blessing in
this and it is something totally different from just learning information from
books. *To apply a little of living teachings to one's life is far more
important than reading hundreds of pages of text*. There are so many books
these days and, as they say in France, "Paper doesn't refuse ink".  (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
order to present a non-Kagyu view of the Buddha's life--that of the Theravadin--I
have therefore used below information from the former senior Theravada bhikkhu
for all Europe, the late Ven. Dr. Saddhatissa, a true friend of Samye Ling.
There are so many versions of the Buddha's life published today. Some are very
moving but perhaps contain more folk legend and the author's imagination than actual
history. We can trust Dr Saddhatissa's version as being the best balance
between scripture and generally-accepted legend<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a>.
 This 'outer' story of Shakyamuni's life found in Theravadin Buddhism is also
used in Mahayana, for a general public ,with Mahayana's own 'inner' version
being reserved for those of its followers with some understanding of deeper
topics such as _buddha nature_, voidness and so forth.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>For
the Mahayana version of the life of the Buddha, we will use the teachings given
at Samye Ling by Kuangting Tai Situpa, the Goshir Gyaltsabpa and Khenchen
Thrangu Rinpoche. Most of those teachings are based upon Maitreya/Asanga's text
on buddha nature and, less directly, on Mahayana sutra sources such as the _Lalita
Vistara_. Apologies in advance! The Mahayana section in this module is
harder reading (mostly direct extracts from _Maitreya on Buddha Nature_)
because the subject-matter is profound and precise. We use Maitreya's speech
because it is _guaranteed accurate. _The Mahayana section starts with a
simple, more user-friendly presentation but any "easy" presentation
is always flawed in one way or another. Maitreya had good reason to be careful
with his words.  </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Anyone
deeply interested in the various accounts of the Buddha's life is also
encouraged to read Thomas's 'Life of the Buddha'. It is a fantastic piece of
research which shows the scriptural origins of different episodes in the
Buddha's story, comparing the various versions with great scholarity. This
fascinating and edifying book is currently out-of-print but may be found
through the library system or in second-hand book stores.    </paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="2" title="A THERAVADIN&#xA;Life of Buddha Shakyamuni"
               pagetitle="A THERAVADIN&#xA;Life of Buddha Shakyamuni"
               tocentry="A THERAVADIN&#xA;Life of Buddha Shakyamuni">
         <image width="434" src="module1_files.image001.png" align=""/>
         <paragraph>based
on the account by</paragraph>
         <paragraph>The
Very Venerable Dr Hammalawa Saddhatissa</paragraph>
         <image width="154" src="module1_files.image002.png" align="left"/>
         <subsection title="Birth" pagetitle="Birth" tocentry="Birth">
            <paragraph>In the sixth century BCE in the foothills
of the Hima­laya near the present-day border between India and Nepal there was
a small but prosperous kingdom ruled by a warrior people called Sakya. The
capital city of this kingdom was called Kapi­lavastu, and the land around was
thickly dotted with smaller towns and villages. To the south of this kingdom
lay the country of Kosala, and beyond that the kingdom of Magadha, in the area
of the modern Indian state of Bihar around Rajgir. To the east lay the land of
Koliya, from which came Queen Mahamaya, the wife of the Sakyan ruler, King
Suddhodana.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha teaching
his five companions</paragraph>
            <paragraph>in the 'Deer Park'
at Isipatana</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In the year
560 BCE there was great excitement in the land of the
Sakyans because Queen Mahamaya was to bear a child. According to the custom of
the time a woman expecting a baby would return to her parents' home for the
birth, and in due course it was arranged for Queen Mahamaya to make the jour­ney
to the neighbouring kingdom of her father. The King sent soldiers ahead to
prepare the way and the Queen set out, carried in a decorated palanquin and
attended by a large company of guards and retainers.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>On the way to Koliya the party passed by a
garden called Lumbini Park where,
attracted by the trees and flowers, the Queen ordered a halt. It was intended
to be only a rest, but while the Queen was lying in the leafy and fragrant
shade of a Sala tree in full blossom she went into labour and gave birth to a
son<a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a>.</paragraph>
            <image width="455" src="module1_files.image003.png" align=""/>
            <paragraph>There was no longer any reason to continue
the journey to Koliya and the party returned to Kapilavastu, where the new
prince was greeted with great rejoicing. He was named </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Sidd­hartha which means "wish fulfilled" by a proud and doting father.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Such, in outline, is the account given in
the Pali scriptures of how the man who was to become revered by millions
throughout most of recorded history as the Enlightened One, the Perfect Being,
the Buddha, made his entry into the world. The date of his birth-the full moon
day of the month of Vesak, corresponding to May in our calendar-is thrice
sacred, for in Buddhist tradition it is the date not only of the Buddha's birth
but also of his enlightenment and death. And, indeed, the account of this nativity, like so much else written down about
the Buddha's life, especially the early years, is full of legendary and
symbolic elements. +It would be impossible, should anyone wish to try, to
disentangle the purely historical events from their fantastic and miraculous
embroidery+, but it would in any case be an exercise of little value;
the essential features of the Buddha's life and teaching are quite clear, and
of the rest, if many incidents did not happen as reported, they might as well
have done, such is their symbolic quality.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="India at the Time" pagetitle="India at the Time"
                     tocentry="India at the Time">
            <paragraph>Before continuing with the account of the
Buddha's life, something must be said about the historical circumstances. At
this period, two and a half thousand years ago, the civilisation which had
grown up in northern India was already quite complex and sophisticated. The
term Hindu did not exist at that time-it was coined much later-but the chief
elements of what was to become known as Hindu society were well established.
The most obvious of these was the organisation of the community according to
caste. The variety of castes in India</paragraph>
            <paragraph>is bewildering, but traditionally they have
all fallen into one of four groups-at the top the Brahmins, who had the right
to act as priests and were the custodians of religious knowledge; next Kshatriyas,
or warriors, who generally provided the ruling class and were responsible for
governing and protecting the community; then the Vaishyas, or merchants, who
kept the eco­nomic life of the community going; and finally the Sudras, who did
most of the hard work as artisans, labourers and servants.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The family into which the Buddha was born
belonged to a Kshatriya clan called *Gautama*. But though the Kshatriyas formed
the nobility and governing class of society, the spiritual leadership was held
by the Brahmins, whence the name Brahminism for the religious system of the
time. Kings relied on Brahmins not only to perform religious functions but also
to give advice and guidance. So, not surprisingly, priests figured prominently
in the early life of the Buddha as the proud King Suddhodana thought about the
career of his son and sought clues to his destiny.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Predicitons" pagetitle="Predicitons" tocentry="Predicitons">
            <paragraph>One of the first visitors to the King after
the birth of his son, it is recounted, was a venerable sage named Kala Devala
(also called Asita). Kala Devala was renowned for his wisdom and his reputed
powers of clairvoyance, and it was he who first sug­gested, when he came to the
palace to pay his respects to the new prince, that King Suddhodana's son was to
be a man out of the ordinary. On seeing Siddhartha he first smiled and then
began to weep. Alarmed, Suddhodana said: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Why are you weeping? Is any misfortune
likely to come to the baby?' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'No,' replied Kala Devala. 'I smiled
because I have been privileged to see a being who, I perceive from certain
particular signs, is surely destined to become a fully enlightened one, a
Buddha. But when I look into my own future I see that I shall not live to hear
him deliver his teaching. That is why the tears came to my eyes. Rejoice, King,
for the son that is born to you will become the greatest being in the whole
world.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It should be explained that the concept of
enlightenment was well known among religious devotees of the time and as the
career of the Buddha shows many strove after it by way of the hermit's asceticism
or the monk's discipline. The term 'Buddha' itself, meaning 'wise one', was not
uncommonly applied to holy men of acknowledged spiritual stature. But the idea
of a royal prince abandoning his heritage in favour of a life of austerity was
not so easily accepted, especially among members of his family who would have
other ambitions for him. Suddhodana therefore began to be worried.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The method of fortune-telling by which Kala
Devala had arrived at his prediction was to 'read' a person's body for certain
marks or characteristics indicating the future course of his life - a kind of
whole-body palmistry. So to test Kala Devala's inter­pretation the King
summoned to him eight of the most learned Brahmins in the land who were also
adept in body-reading.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Seven of the
Brahmins, after studying the child, concluded that there were two possible
courses open to him. If he decided to remain in the world he would become a
great emperor. If, on the other hand, he decided to give up the world and seek
enlightenment he would become a Buddha. But the eighth Brahmin, who was called
Kondanna, was unequivocal. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'His markings
show that his future can go in only one way,' he told the King. 'A time will
come when he will witness four special signs and as a result he will renounce
the world and go out to seek enlightenment. Eventually he will achieve that
enligh­tenment and become a Buddha.' (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Indeed, say the texts, so impressed was
Kondannaby what he had read inthe child's appear­ance that he himself decided
there and then to renounce the world and, accompanied by four friends of like
mind, went away to wait for Siddhartha to grow up and attain Buddhahood. Kon­danna
and his group later featured prominently in the Buddha's career.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>King Suddhodana, it is related, was greatly
upset by this pre­diction, and it was to obsess him as his son grew up. But
mean­while the child was the focus of everyone's admiration. His skin, it is
said, had a golden hue and gleamed with a metallic glow. His eyes were blue
'like the flower of the flax plant', his hair was black with a bluish tinge<a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a> and his limbs were perfectly
moulded.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Early Life" pagetitle="Early Life" tocentry="Early Life">
            <paragraph>On the seventh day after his birth
Siddhartha's mother, Queen Mahamaya, died. He was not deprived of motherly
care, however, for the queen's sister, Prajapati, took responsibility for him.
Polygamy was common among the nobility of that society, and Prajapati was also
married to Suddhodana. Accord­ing to the texts, she herself gave birth to a
child on the day that Mahamaya died, but she put out her own son to be looked
after by a nurse and brought up Siddhartha as her own, with all the love of a
real mother.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>After a few years Siddhartha was sent to
school, where he joined the children of other noble families. His ability
quickly impressed his teachers and he rapidly learnt a wide range of subjects,
including languages and mathematics. He also became proficient in sports like
wrestling and archery. He excelled in all
things, surpassing his fellow pupils, and even going beyond what his teachers
could teach him. He was tall, strong and hand­some, and his good manners and
kindness endeared him to everyone.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="First Experience of Samadhi" pagetitle="First Experience of Samadhi"
                     tocentry="First Experience of Samadhi">
            <paragraph>Every year in the land of the Sakyans a
ploughing festival was held. It seems to have been a largely ceremonial affair,
sug­gesting a fertility ritual. The King himself drove the first pair of
bullocks, which wore golden trappings on their horns and pulled a golden
plough; other nobles of the kingdom drove bul­locks wearing silver harnessing
and drawing silver ploughs. When Siddhartha was seven the King took him to the
ploughing festival. During the proceedings
the boy was taken by his attendants to rest under a rose-apple tree on a
specially prepared couch. While seated there he forgot all about the ploughing
fes­tival and fell into meditation, breathing in the measured and controlled
way of skilled practitioners, until he entered a trance. It was the first
mystical experience recorded in his life. It was thus that his
attendants found him when they came back a little later, aloof from his
surroundings, in a state of rapture. Time had stood still for him, and as if to
make this point the accounts say that the shadow of the rose-apple tree under
which he was sitting had not moved from the time the attendants left him up to
their return. This event was reported to the King who came hurrying to witness
this latest evidence of his son's uniqueness.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Much is made in the accounts of
Siddhartha's early life of his compassion for living things. One day he was
walking in the woods with his cousin Devadatta, who later, when the Buddhist
community had become established, was to take on the role of a trouble-maker.
Devadatta was carrying a bow and arrows with him, and seeing a swan fly past
overhead he took aim and shot it. Both boys ran quickly to where the bird had
fallen, and Siddhartha arrived first. The swan was still alive, so Siddhartha
gently drew the arrow out of its wing. He then took some leaves and squeezed
the juice from them onto the wound to stop the bleeding and tried to calm the
frightened bird. When Devadatta arrived and wanted to claim the swan Siddhartha
refused. 'If you had killed it, it would have been yours,' he said. 'But it is
only wounded, and since it is I who have saved its life it belongs to me.' The
argument went on until Siddhartha suggested putting the case before the court of
wise men. After hearing all the evidence their verdict was: 'A life must belong
to him who tries to save it. A life cannot be claimed by one who is only trying
to destroy it. Siddhartha has the right to take the wounded swan.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Meanwhile,
King Suddhodana continued to ponder the pro­phecies made by the Brahmins at his
son's birth, and as the boy grew up he worried particularly about Kondanna's
predic­tion that Siddhartha would renounce the world after seeing four special
signs. So one day he sent again for his Brahmins--only seven this time, since
Kondanna had disappeared to await the transformation of Siddhartha into a
Buddha--and asked them to explain what was meant by the four signs. Unlike
Kondanna, the seven Brahmins had allowed two possible courses for Sidd­hartha's
life; he would become either a Buddha or a great emperor. He would opt for the former
if he were to be con­fronted in turn by four men of different conditions--an old
man, a sick man, a dead man and finally an ascetic, one who had renounced the
world to seek deliverance from suffering. Well, thought the King, I must ensure
that my son does not see any such signs. Immediately he ordered that no old or
sick people and no sign of death should be permitted near the prince. Guards
were specially posted to enforce this. No ascetic was allowed within a mile of
him. He was given young servants, and any mention of illness, old age, death or
monasticism was strictly forbidden. Even fading flowers and leaves were removed
from gardens and pleasure parks so that the prince should not see anything that
might suggest decay and death.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At the same time all possible luxuries and
delights were pro­vided for Siddhartha. Three palaces were built for him, one for
each season of the year in that tropical region-the hot sea­son, the rains and
the cool months of winter. Extensive parks and hunting grounds, decorated with
ponds full of fish, water lilies and swans, were prepared.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In this environment Siddhartha developed
into a young man of great strength and beauty, and also of outstanding
intellectual ability. He outstripped all his contemporaries in the martial
arts, while in knowledge and agility of mind he surpassed even the most
renowned pundits.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In due course,
King Suddhodana decided the time had come for him to marry, and one day he
summoned all the eligible girls in the kingdom to the palace for Siddhartha to
make his choice. Among them was his cousin Yasodhara, a beautiful and charming
girl. Siddhartha's choice fell on her, to the King's great pleasure, and they
were married with much ceremony and rejoicing. By the time that Siddhartha was
nearing his twenty-­ninth birthday Yasodhara was expecting a baby, and King
Suddhodana had begun to think that everything was, after all, turning out as he
wished.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>But though denied evidence of the human
condition, and provided with every possible comfort and diversion, Siddhartha
remained thoughtful and preoccupied. With the inevitability of a fairy-tale
plot, the elaborate defences erected by the King were soon to be eroded by
reality, by the discovery, which was to become the basis of the Buddha's
teaching, that life is suffering.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Life-Changing Experiences" pagetitle="Life-Changing Experiences"
                     tocentry="Life-Changing Experiences">
            <paragraph>(eh)*1.   *All the diversions provided by King Suddhodana did not prevent the
prince feeling bored and restless, and one day he summoned his charioteer and
personal attendant, Channa, to take him for a drive in the countryside. Channa
chose four fine horses of the famed Sindhi breed, white and spotless like lotus
blooms, and harnessed them to a magnificent chariot. Sidd­hartha took the
reins, majestic and resplendent as a god.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)They had not
gone far before they saw standing in the road­way a hunched-up, tired-looking
old man. At last the pre­cautions taken by the King had failed. Siddhartha was
astonished. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'What is that?' he asked Channa, bringing the horses to a stop. 'It
looks like a man, but his hair is all white, he has no teeth, his cheeks are
sunken, his skin is dry and wrinkled, and his eyes are bleary. Look at his bent
back, his ribs protruding, his thin crooked arms and legs that seem as if they
can hardly support his wretched frame, so that he has to lean on a stick. What
kind of man is that?'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'That,' replied Channa, apparently making little effort to sus­tain
the elaborate structure of pretence that had shielded Sidd­hartha from reality
up till then, 'is an old man. It is someone who has been living for a long
time, perhaps sixty, seventy or even eighty and more years, so that his body is
worn out and decaying. It is nothing to be dismayed at, since it is a common
thing. We all get old.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Do you mean to say that we all of us become like that, that we all
get old?' said Siddhartha. 'That Yasodhara, and you, and all my youthful
companions, and even I myself, must one day look like that?'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Yes, my lord,' answered Channa. 'It is everyone's lot.' (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Siddhartha was
so upset that he could not go on with his drive. Instead, he turned the horses
around and went back to the palace, deep in thought, too troubled to speak.
When the King saw his son returning so soon after setting out he asked Channa
the reason; and when he heard it he cried out in despair: 'Now you have
destroyed me.' But the King was not one to give up so easily. In an effort to
remove from Sidd­hartha's mind the memory of his meeting with the old man he
ordered special dramas and amusements to be provided. He also doubled the guard
around the palace grounds and reminded everyone of the strict instructions he
had issued.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*2.   *But once again Siddhartha decided to go for a chariot ride with
Channa, and on this occasion they encountered a man who was ill. He was so weak
he could not stand up, but rolled and writhed on the ground. His eyes were
bloodshot, his mouth was frothing and he groaned and beat his breast in agony.
As before Channa explained the phenomena and once more Siddhartha was overcome
with anxiety.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Is this a rare thing, or does it happen to everybody?' he asked.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Everybody is liable to get ill, my lord,' replied Channa, then
added by way of reassurance: 'But if a man is careful about his diet, keeps
clean and takes plenty of exercise he is likely to remain healthy. There is no
need to worry.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'No need to worry!' exclaimed the prince. 'First I see the horror of
decay and old age, and now it seems everyone is liable to find himself in such
a wretched plight as this man!'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*3.   *As before they cut short their excursion and Siddhartha returned
home with a heavy heart.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)A third time
Siddhartha and Channa set out and this time came upon a funeral procession. The
mourners were wailing and beating their breasts, while, in contrast, the corpse
they were carrying lay still and lifeless like a statue. Channa replied to
Siddhartha's predictable questions and then went on: (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Death, my lord, is the end of life. When life ceases, that is
death. Your body dies when it can go on no longer because of old age and decay.
Or else it dies because of disease. Breathing stops and the heart ceases to
beat. But there is nothing strange about it. It is as common as birth, for everyone
who lives must sooner or later die. There is nothing you can do about it, since
it is in the nature of things, so there is no point in worrying about it. Just
hope for a long life.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Siddhartha
pondered this, and also the two earlier pheno­mena, and came to realise that
these unpleasant facts which had been hidden from him for so long, thanks to
the misguided con­cern of his father, represented the true nature of existence.
Life was suffering. And then he began to wonder whether there was not some way out
of this dilemma, some means of escape. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Must everyone I
love, and I myself too, simply endure helplessly this tyranny of old age,
disease and death?' he asked himself as they once more drove back to the
palace.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*4.   *Siddhartha and Channa went out a fourth and last time, and as before
an unaccustomed sight awaited Siddhartha on the roadside. But this time it was
not a scene of despair. It was a man with a shaven head, wearing an
orange-coloured robe that glowed with the mellow light of the morning sun,
standing bare­foot and holding a bowl in his hand. His face bore a calm,
thoughtful expression and his gaze was directed downwards, as if he was a
person at peace, engrossed in pleasant thoughts. Halting his horses, Siddhartha
asked Channa: (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)"Who is this? Is it a man or is it indeed a god who stands there so
calm and aloof, as if the sorrows and joys of this world do not touch him."(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)"That, my lord,' replied the dutiful Channa, 'is an ascetic. It is a
man who has seen how old age, disease and death afflict all beings, and has
renounced the world to seek a solution to the enigma of life. He has no home,
but shelters in caves and woods, begging enough food for one frugal meal a day
and living a life of discipline and simplicity, striving to be pure in deed, word
and thought and seeking deliverance from the world's suffering through
meditation. He travels from place to place and tries to tell people how to live
a good life and find happi­ness."(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)This was, of
course, the fourth symbolic vision foretold by the Brahmins. Greatly impressed,
Siddhartha did not this time turn back but drove on, deep in thought, until he
reached the amusement park that had been the destination of all his excur­sions
with Channa. In the park everything had been prepared for the prince's
entertainment, with musicians, dancers, poets and scholars all waiting to
attend him, and plenty of food and drink. But Siddhartha would not be
distracted from his train of thought and as he walked through the park so
richly provided with possibilities of indulgence and diversion he thought to
himself: (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)"I must become like that ascetic. I too shall renounce the world,
this very day, and seek that deliverance from suffer­ing of which I have been
unaware through all the years I have spent in superficial amusements."(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Eventually,
tired of walking, he sat down in the shade of a tree. While he was thus resting
a messenger galloped up on a foaming steed with an announcement that should have
delighted the young prince--his wife, Princess Yasodhara, had just given birth
to a son. But far from feeling joy, Siddhartha greeted the news with dismay.
"Another bond to tie me!" he exclaimed as he arose to return to the palace. But
his resolve remained un­shaken; nothing, not even the arrival of a son and
heir, would now deflect him from the path he had chosen.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The King sensed the discontent in
Siddhartha and, with the Brahmins' dreaded prophecy now fulfilled, privately
resigned himself to losing his son. Nevertheless, in a last desperate attempt
to hold him he arranged a grand feast and celebration to mark the new birth.
The leading singers and musicians in the land were invited to perform. The best
and most beautiful dancers were summoned. The most sumptuous food was served.
In deference to his father, Siddhartha attended the feast, but, preoccupied
with his own thoughts, he took no inter­est in the lavish entertainment that
had been laid on for his benefit, and as the evening wore on he began to doze
off. In due course, seeing that they were performing for a sleeping prince, the
musicians and dancers decided to have a rest as well, and soon they too were
fast asleep. When Siddhartha woke up he
was surprised to see all the people who had earlier been enter­taining him
lying around deep in slumber. And how changed they looked! Dancers and singers
renowned throughout the land for their grace and beauty now sprawled
inelegantly on the chairs and couches where they had lain down. Some were
snoring loudly, others grinding their teeth like animals. The glamour of a
short while before had turned to squalor. Sidd­hartha's disgust with the
worldly life was complete, and arising quietly so as not to disturb any of the
sleeping bodies he called his attendant Channa. and told him to saddle his
favourite horse, Kanthaka, in readiness for a long journey.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Departure" pagetitle="Departure" tocentry="Departure">
            <paragraph>Before leaving he had one duty to perform.
He had still not set eyes on the son whose arrival had coincided with his
decision to renounce the world, so on his way out he paused at the room where
the child and its mother were sleeping. Yasodhara was holding the baby close to
her, her hand covering its face protec­tively. For a moment Siddhartha wrestled
with an agonising dilemma: if he moved his wife's hand so as to look at the
child's face she might wake up and prevent him from leaving; but un­less he did
he would have to leave without a sight of his son. He quickly made up his mind.
'I must go without seeing my son's face,' he said to himself. 'But when I have
found what I am now going out to seek I shall come back, and then I shall see
him and his mother.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It was midnight as Siddhartha, accompanied
by the faithful Channa, rode quietly out of Kapilavastu. Only when he had gone
beyond the city gates did he pause to look back at the palace, now sleeping in
the moonlight, where he had spent all his life and where he was leaving behind
everyone he knew and loved.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Riding
through the night, they came to the river Anoma, which marked the border
between the Sakyan kingdom and the kingdom of Magadha. Once on the other side
of the river Sidd­hartha dismounted. He then took off his fine silken clothes,
handed them to Channa and told him to return with them and his horse to
Kapilavastu. Such garments were not appropriate to an ascetic. Then he took out
his sword and cut off his long hair. Finally he put on some orange-coloured
robes, provided, according to legend, by a helpful deity, took up a begging
bowl and dismissed Channa. Channa was loathe to go.
'How can I go on living in the palace without you ?' he said. 'Let me follow
you.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'No,' replied
Siddhartha. 'Take my clothes and my jewellery back to my father and tell him
and my mother and my wife that they must not worry. I am going away to seek an
escape from the misery of ageing, sickness and death. As soon as I have found
it I shall return to the palace and teach it to my father, my mother, my wife,
my son and everybody else. Then every­one will be truly happy.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>But it was Siddhartha's horse, Kanthaka,
that figured in the poignant last moments of this parting, according to the
story. When Channa eventually agreed to return Kanthaka refused to move. It was
necessary for Siddhartha to talk to the animal before it could be persuaded to
leave. But it had gone only a short distance when it stopped and looked around
once more at its master. It required further persuasion from Channa to make it
continue, and when it finally departed tears were rolling from its eyes. Later,
it is said, the horse died of a broken heart.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Ascetic Period" pagetitle="Ascetic Period" tocentry="Ascetic Period">
            <paragraph>With all his worldly ties cut, and turning
his back on the river Anoma which now symbolically separated him from his past
life, Siddhartha began the existence of a wandering ascetic. Such people were
then, as ever since, common enough in India, and Siddhartha followed the usual
practice of begging his food and finding shelter wherever he could. People
referred to him as a 'holy man' or 'ascetic', or, when they knew him well
enough, by his family name Gautama. But no one suspected who he really was.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>His identity first became known when he
found himself in the city of Rajagaha, the capital of Magadha, and the site of
the modern town of Rajgir in the Indian state of Bihar. Evi­dently his
distinguished bearing caught the attention of the townspeople, for some of them
remarked about it to the ruler of Magadha, King Bimbisara. 'This young man, the
ascetic Gautama as some people call him, is so charming and polite and
well-groomed,' they said, 'that he does not seem at all like a mendicant.' On
hearing the name 'Gautama' the King realised this was the son of his friend and
neighbour King Suddhodana, for the news of the prince's dramatic act of
renunciation must have travelled fast. Immediately the King went out himself to
look for Siddhartha, and as soon as he found him addressed him in a forthright
manner. 'What are you doing?' he demanded. 'Why are you going about in this
manner? Have you quarrelled with your father?' He then implored Siddhartha to
give up his ascetic life and even offered him half his kingdom if he would
agree to do so and settle down in Magadha. But Siddhartha graciously declined,
explaining his mission and his determination to go on searching for a happiness
that was not dependent on the vicissitudes of life.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Meanwhile, the
news that Siddhartha had set out on the spiri­tual road had reached the Brahmin
Kondanna, the one who had originally predicted such a career for the prince,
and straight­ way he set out to join him. Kondanna lived with four other seekers
after truth, Bhaddiya, Vappa, Mahanama and Assaji, and they went along with
him. All six thereafter, clad in the orange robes of the ascetic, wandered
around as a group.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The usual procedure, then as now, for
anyone seeking spiri­tual enlightenment was to look for a teacher, or guru.
Despite the strict ordering of society according to caste, and the numerous and
detailed obligations which this entailed for every member of that society
according to his status, the actual busi­ness of gaining and imparting
religious knowledge was largely left to individual initiative. There were no
officially recognised institutions of learning nor even a clear hierarchy of
religious authority. For spiritual guidance it was necessary to attach oneself
to a teacher, an ascetic who by virtue of the experience and wisdom attributed
to him had begun to attract and accept pupils. The authority of such teachers
depended solely on their reputation.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There were many such teachers in India at
that time, some of them with large followings. Often a teacher would be known
for his attention to a particular aspect of religious discipline or for a
particular doctrine, so that he and his group of pupils became an identifiable
school, even perhaps a sect. It was up to the novice himself to decide to whom
he would become attached. In accordance with this practice, the first major
step taken by Gautama and his companions was to choose a guru.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)One of the most
celebrated teachers in that part of India at that time was one Alara Kalama, whose system was devoted to
achieving a level of meditation that is described in the texts merely as the
'state of Nothing Whatsoever'. It was under Alara that Gautama and his com­panions
first enrolled. Gautama studied especially hard. In­deed, he made such
progréss that one day Alara announced he could teach him no more. 'You are
equal to me now,' he told Gautama. 'Will you stay here and help me teach my
pupils?'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)But Gautama was
not satisfied. 'Is that all you can teach me?' he replied. 'Can you not teach
me how to escape from death, illness and old age?'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'No,' said
Alara. 'I cannot teach you something that I do not know myself. No one in the
world knows that.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>So Gautama
and his friends left. As they wandered around the country they passed onto
others what they had learnt under Alara, but meanwhile they looked about for a
teacher who could take them further. In due course they came across another
renowned teacher called Uddaka Ramaputta, who headed a school dedicated to
cultivating an advanced form of mental concentration termed 'Neither Perception
nor Non-Perception'. This was something which had reputedly been achieved by
the founder of this school, Rama, but even Uddaka himself, to whom Rama had
relinquished charge of his pupils before he died, was still striving towards
that goal. Under Uddaka's supervision Gau­tama was successful, whereupon Uddaka
with due humility invited him to become the leader of the school. But again Gau­tama
felt unsatisfied, and once more departed to continue his search.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The little party
eventually arrived at a place called Uruvela, and here they decided to settle
for a while. It was a good spot for their purpose--a tranquil wooded area, with
a river at hand to provide water and a village nearby where they could beg for
their food. They set up a hermitage, and resolved to try and find their own
way, unaided by any teacher, to their spiritual goal.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Mortification of
the body has been practised by many people in many places as a spiritual
discipline, and this was the pro­cedure that Gautama, along with his
companions, now decided to follow. He began by eating less. At first he
restricted himself to one meal a day, then gradually it became a meal every two
days, then every three. He no longer begged but fed himself on a rude diet of
fruit, roots and the leaves of certain plants. His once healthy, robust body
became emaciated. His skin became dry and wrinkled, and his eyes sank into
their sockets until, as the text graphically puts it, they resembled stones in
a deep well. He began to suffer terrible pain and hunger.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)But his
self-torture did not end there. He punished his body by holding his breath for
long periods, until his head would seem about to burst. In the hottest season
he would stay out in the burning sun during the day and indoors, where the air
was oppressively stuffy, at night. In winter he would bathe in icy water. To
demonstrate his contempt for his body he took to wearing the filthiest rags
salvaged from rubbish heaps or even from corpses awaiting cremation. He also
put his mental endurance to the test. On the nights of the new moon and full
moon, an awesome time when supernatural beings were abroad, he would go and sit
alone in mortuary grounds. Nor did the more obvious threat from marauding wild
animals in such places scare him away.(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Entering the Middle Way\Between Sensuality and Asceticism"
                     pagetitle="Entering the Middle Way\Between Sensuality and Asceticism"
                     tocentry="Entering the Middle Way\Between Sensuality and Asceticism">
            <paragraph>(eh)And all the
while he practised meditation, though to little avail. For six years Gautama
underwent this regime before he de­cided it was leading him nowhere. Then one
day he collapsed. He was found by a shepherd who gave him milk and took him
into his care. He did not leave the shepherd until he had regained some of his
old health and robustness, and then he went to rejoin his five companions. They
meanwhile were con­tinuing to practise their austerities, and when they saw
that Gautama was no longer doing so they were shocked and upset. In fact, so
disgusted were they at what must have seemed to them a failure of discipline if
not actually a betrayal of the un­dertaking they had jointly agreed that they
would have no more to do with him. They got up and departed, leaving him
behind. But Gautama, now left to himself, went on building up his strength
until, it is said, his body regained its original golden hue and the thirty-two
physical features indicating that he was destined to become a Buddha were once
more clearly visible.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There lived in the neighbourhood at that
time a woman called Sujata, the daughter of a wealthy property owner. Sujata
was expecting a baby and she had vowed that if a son was born to her she would
make a special food offering to the deity of a nearby banyan tree. The banyan tree,
with its characteristic aerial roots that grow into trunks and thus enable the
tree to spread and renew itself, has long been regarded with particular
reverence in India and must have been from quite an early stage the focus of
animist cults. Sujata duly bore a son and set about the elaborate ritual of
preparing a meal fit for a god. First she milked a hundred cows, and fed this
milk to fifty of them. She then fed the milk of these fifty cows to twenty-five
of them and so went on with this process of concentration, known as 'work­ing
in the milk', until she was left with the milk of only eight cows. With this
rich and highly nutritious milk she made a rice preparation, using a special
cooking vessel, and taking care that not a drop was allowed to boil over or go
to waste. Finally she emptied the preparation into a golden bowl, filling it to
the brim. She then sent her maid to the banyan tree to make arrange­ments.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Meanwhile, Gautama had chanced upon this
banyan tree and had sat down under it to meditate. When the maid approached she
was astonished to see this golden-hued figure, radiating a kind of lustre,
sitting motionless at the foot of the tree. She rushed back to her mistress to
announce excitedly that the deity himself had appeared in order to accept the
offering. Sujata duly came hurrying with her bowl of milk rice, appropriately
draped with a fine silken covering, and was likewise struck by the seated
figure glowing golden in the morning sun. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Less credulous
than her maid, perhaps, but overcome with awe, Sujata made her offering to
Gautama, addressing him as follows: 'Venerable Sir, whoever you may be, god or
human, please accept this milk rice, and may you achieve the goal to which you
aspire.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Sujata then
placed the offering in Gautama's hands, saluted him reverently and withdrew,
giving no thought to the precious bowl she had left with him.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The time had
indeed come for Gautama to achieve what he had been seeking for so many years,
and the events of that day, as described in the texts, are imbued not only with
symbolic meaning but with peculiar calm and dignity. Taking the offer­ing, he
went to a nearby river called Neranjara, and putting the bowl on the bank he
entered the water to bathe himself. He then returned to the bank, sat down with
the bowl in his lap and began his last meal as an aspirant to Buddhahood. The
meal over, he washed his hands and the bowl and placed the bowl on the water to
float. Then he said: 'If today I am to attain full enlightenment, may this
golden bowl swim upstream.' The bowl immediately did so. Gautama spent the rest
of the day relaxing in the woodland along the river bank.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)In the evening
Gautama got up and made his way to the Bodhi tree-the 'Ficus Religiosa',
another tree sacred in India and known as the 'Tree of Enlightenment'- which he
had chosen as the place for his great act of meditation. On the way he met a
grass cutter called Sotthiya who gave him some bundles of 'kuss' grass. This
grass was regarded as sacred and was used by Brahmins for sitting on. Gautama spread
this grass at the foot of the Bodhi tree, turned to face the East and sat down
in a meditating posture. Thus began the great trance from which he was to
emerge on the full moon day of the month of Vesak as a Fully Enlightened One, a
Buddha.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The course of
Gautama's meditation is elaborately recounted in the ancient texts. At an early
stage he was confronted with worldly temptations in the form of demons. He then
moved through various stages of spiritual ecstasy, called to mind all his
previous forms of existence, and pondered how things come into being and
disappear. With his mind puri­fied, he then considered the nature of
defilement, how it is caused and how it can be destroyed. In so doing he shed
from his mind the various forms of defilement--the defilement of sen­sual
desire, of the wish for continued existence, of delusion­ and finally achieved
the deliverance that he had sought for so long. 'Now the cycle of rebirth is
ended for me,' he said afterwards, when talking about his experience. 'For me
this world no longer matters.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)According to one
account Gautama spent seven days in this absorption, emerging as the sun was
rising and the full moon of Vesak was setting. Then he spent further periods of
time in the vicinity of the Bodhi tree, gazing at it with gratitude for having
sheltered him and walking up and down in front of it.(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Disciples and Teaching" pagetitle="Disciples and Teaching"
                     tocentry="Disciples and Teaching">
            <paragraph>Many other events, laden with symbolic
significance, are said to have taken place during this period. Soon after
Gautama attained Enlightenment, two merchants called Tapussu and Bhalluka came
by. Seeing Gautama seated under the Bodhi tree, they prepared a meal for him of
flour and honey and offered it to him. After eating the food the Buddha talked
to them about his experience and the two merchants became his first lay
disciples, the first Buddhists. Gautama was now aged thirty-five.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The Buddha was
now ready to begin his mission, and he asked himself to whom he should first
expound the Doctrine, who would most quickly understand. His mind turned to his
former teacher, Alara Kalama, a learned and wise man already far advanced in
his progress towards spiritual perfection. Alas, he had died. Then he thought
of Uddaka, the disciple of Rama. But he, too, was dead. Finally he remembered
the five com­panions with whom he had shared a rigorous asceticism before
breaking away to seek enlightenment alone. They were still at the deer park of
Isipatana near Benares, about a hundred miles away, and he set out to make the
long journey.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>After many days of travelling--on foot, of
course--he arrived one evening at the deer park. Surprised, no doubt, to see him
approaching, the five had not forgotten the scorn and resentment they had felt
on parting from him. So as he walked towards them they remarked sarcastically
to one another: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Look, here
comes that so-called ascetic Gautama, the luxury­loving fellow who could not
keep up a life of austerity and fell back into ease and comfort. Let's ignore
him. Don't show him any respect or offer to take his bowl or his spare robe
from him. Let him come and sit down if he wants to, but he's not worth
bothering about.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As the Buddha came closer, however, they
began to see that he had somehow changed. He had a majestic, authoritative air
about him such as they had not seen before, and without their realising it
their hostility evaporated. Soon they were going for­ward to greet him, and
while one respectfully took his bowl and robe another prepared a place for him
to sit and a third hurried off to fetch water to wash his feet.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)That evening he
delivered his first teaching. It is known as 'The Turning of the Wheel of
Truth' and it is an occasion that holds an important place in Buddhist lore.
The first to grasp the full significance of the Buddha's message was Kondanna
who had originally predicted Siddhartha's enlightenment, and as he did so the
Buddha exclaimed: 'Kondanna has realised it! Kondanna has realised it!' The
full exposition of the Doctrine, however, evidently lasted well beyond that
evening for the Buddha later described how two of the monks would go out
begging while he instructed the other three, and vice versa, until all had
fully absorbed his teaching.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Anyone who becomes a Buddhist monk becomes
a member of the Sangha, the monastic Community or Order that lives and
organises itself according to the Discipline laid down by the Buddha. The
Sangha grew rapidly following the conversion of the five ascetics. No doubt
these, as veteran seekers after the Truth and old companions of Gautama
himself, were already well on the way to conversion when the Buddha preached
his first sermon to them in the deer park. What is striking about many of the
subsequent conversions is that they were of people apparently without any
particular predisposition to the holy life, often people who came in contact
with the Buddha quite by chance while going about their ordinary affairs. There
was nothing novel in those days about the idea of renouncing the pleasures of
the world for a life of meditation, so the rapid spread of his teaching and
growth of his following suggest his message must have had something unusually
dynamic and arresting about it. No doubt much of the explanation lies in his
persuasive and down-to-earth manner, and the numerous parables that appear in
the course of his teaching certainly sup­port this.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This intensity of the Buddha is illustrated
in the very first recorded conversations he made after those of his five
ascetic companions--in other words, the beginning of his mission in the world at
large. One morning, it is related, while the Buddha was sitting in the deer
park near Benares, a young man called Yasa came by. Yasa appears to have been
the epitome of the idle rich, a man bored with his wealth yet unable to see
what else there might be in life. Upon hearing the Buddha explain his teaching,
however, he quickly realised the futility of his career hitherto and asked
there and then to become a monk.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Meanwhile, Yasa's parents had become
alarmed at his dis­appearance and his father set oat to look for him. Towards
even­ing he came across the Buddha. The Buddha told him his son had become a
monk and began to explain to him also his teach­ing, to such effect that the
father resolved to become a lay sup­porter. He also invited the Buddha,
together with his monks, now numbering six, to come to his house for a meal.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It was to become the custom for Buddhist
monks after enjoy­ing someone's hospitality to offer a discourse, known as
'giving thanks', and this is presumably the first occasion on which this
happened; for after the meal the Buddha talked about his teach­ing to those
present, who included Yasa's mother, his wife (who in effect was now his
ex-wife since he had cut his worldly ties) and fifty-four friends. These
fifty-four were so impressed that they all asked to be accepted as monks. The Sangha
had grown to sixty.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Later, it is recounted, when these men had
achieved Enlight­enment, the Buddha addressed </paragraph>
            <paragraph>them with these words: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Go forth,
monks, and teach the truth, which is glorious in the be­ginning, the middle and
the end, for the good of all beings. There are some whose eyes are not obscured
by dust. Teach them, they will understand.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Like other religious teachers of the time,
the Buddha was peri­patetic, wandering from place to place teaching anyone who
would listen. Throughout the forty-five years of his ministry he travelled
widely in northern and eastern India, stopping only during the rainy season,
when he and his monks would go into retreat.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>His first journey took him by stages from
the deer park to Uruvela. During this journey he went to sit down in a wood,
where there also happened to be a group of people enjoying themselves on an
outing. There were thirty men, each accom­panied by his wife except one, who
had brought along with him a prostitute. While no one was paying attention,
this woman picked up the belongings of her companion and made off. Even­tually
the theft was noticed, whereupon everyone got up and started running about to
try and find the woman. While they were busily searching they came upon the
Buddha sitting under a tree and asked him if he had seen a woman, explaining what
had happened. The Buddha replied: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Which do you
think is better: to try and find a woman or to discover yourselves?' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Perhaps this reaction came as a surprise to
them, but it seems they agreed it was more worthwhile to try and discover them­selves,
for they abandoned the search for the woman and sat down to hear the Buddha's
words. In due course they became converted to his teaching and the men joined
the Sangha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At Uruvela were three famed holy men
belonging to a religious sect whose members tied their hair up in a certain way
and were thus known as 'matted hair ascetics'. All three were called Kassapa;
the most prominent, who had a following of 600 ascetics, was known as Kassapa
of Uruvela, the others, who had followings of 300 and 200 respectively, as
Kassapa of the River and Kassapa of Gaya. These men, together with their
followers, heard the Buddha and joined the Sangha, thereby not only greatly
swelling its numbers at a still early stage but bringing to it their own
prestige as holy men. This prestige seems to have been a factor in the
conversion of another influ­ential figure, a king, with all the consequences
this must have had for the spread of the Buddha's teaching, at least in his terri­tory.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This was King Bimbisara of the state of
Magadha, the one who had earlier sought to dissuade Gautama from the religious
life. In the course of his travels, the Buddha arrived with his now large
number of followers at Rajagaha, capital of Magadha, and when King Bimbisara
heard that the Buddha had come to his city he went to visit him, along with a
large retinue. The King was struck by the fact that the renowned religious
teacher Kassapa of Uruvela was now a follower of the Buddha. So were the Brahmins
in the King's retinue, though apparently this was a cause of chagrin to them,
perhaps because it dramatised the growing threat which Buddhism was making to
the established Brahminical form of religion. But the Buddha proceeded in his
usual fashion and addressed them, it is related, along the following lines</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Why are you
unhappy? Because you are filled with want­ing, with desire, to the point that
eventually the desire becomes a thirst that cannot be satisfied even when you
achieve what you desire. So how can you be happy? By ceasing to desire. Just as
a fire dies down when no fuel is added, so your unhappiness will end when the
fuel of desire is removed. You will find real happiness when you conquer
selfish hopes and habits.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>When the Buddbp had finished speaking, King
Bimbisara, together with his loyal retinue, asked to be accepted as lay dis­ciples
of the Buddha. Moreover, the King invited the Buddha and the Sangha to his
palace, where he personally served them food and later dedicated his pleasure
garden, the Bamboo Grove, to the Sangha for their use.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As mentioned earlier, the Buddha's practice
was to spend each rainy season in retreat, or meditative seclusion, at one or other
of a number of places he favoured. The first such retreat was spent with his
five original monks immediately after the first sermon. It was the seventh such
retreat that saw the con­version of two men who were to become known as his
chief disciples.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Near Rajagaha were two villages called
Upatissa and Kolita. The headmen of these village, were also known by these
names respectively, and their two families were very close. One day Upatissa's
wife, Sari, gave birth to a son; so did Kolita's wife, Moggali. Upatissa's son
became known either as Úpatissa or as Sariputta (Sari's son), while the son of
Kolita was called Kolita, Moggaliputta (Moggali's son) or Moggallana. From
their earliest days these two boys were close friends and as they grew up they
developed a common interest in drama. But they increasingly felt there must be
more to life than what they saw on a stage and, one day, while watching a drama
(it was called The Mountain Festival) they decided to leave home in search of
the true meaning of life. They first went to a famous religious teacher called
Sanjaya, who lived near Raja­gaha. But he could not provide the answer they
were seeking. So they made a vow that henceforth they would each ponder and
meditate as hard as they could in quest of truth and that whoever thought he
had found it first would tell the other.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One morning while Upatissa was in the main
street of Raja­gaha he saw what appeared to be an ascetic going from door to
door with a bowl begging for alms of food. But somehow this seemed no ordinary
ascetic. Upatissa felt there was an un­usual modesty and calmness about him,
and as he approached he was even more deeply impressed by the man's manner and
appearance. There was a look about the man's face, he thought, of perfect
peace, as of the smooth undisturbed surface of a lake under a calm clear sky.
'Who can this be?' said Upatissa to him­self. 'Surely he must be one who has
discovered what I am look­ing for, or else he is the pupil of such a person. I
wonder who his teacher is. I shall follow him and find out.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>So when the man had been to all the houses
and was going out of the city gate, Upatissa went up to him and said: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Brother, your
demeanour is so pleasant and your deportment so appeal­ing, your face is so
clear and bright. Please tell me who your teacher is, what is his name?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The man was in fact Assaji, one of the five
original monks, and he replied that his teacher was a great ascetic of the
Sakya clan who had left his home and country behind in order to fol­low the
homeless life and serve others.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Upatissa pressed him to explain the
teaching that he fol­lowed, to which Assaji modestly replied: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'I am only a
newcomer into the monk's life under the Buddha, so I do not know very much yet
about his teachings. I cannot explain it to you in detail, but perhaps I can
give you a summary of it in a few words.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At this, Assaji began to recite a verse
which summed up the Buddha's doctrine of Causation. He had only spoken the
first couple of lines, however, before Upatissa grasped the meaning and in
great excitement he said to Assaji: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'If this is the
doctrine you have learnt from your teacher then indeed you have found the state
that is free from sorrow, free from death, something which has not been known
to men for so many ages.' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Then he thanked Assaji, saluted him
respectfully and went to tell his friend Kolita of his experience. Together
they went to see the Buddha, were received into the Sangha and very soon became
appointed his chief disciples. In Buddhist history they are accorded a special
reverence--Upatissa as a monk of great wis­dom and Kolita as one who developed
miraculous powers.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>During the early years of the Sangha the
Buddha and his monks lived wherever they could find a suitable spot--under
trees, in caves or ravines, or even out in the open. The Buddhist monk, after
all, dedicates himself to a life of homelessness. However, as the episode of
King Bimbisara shows, it soon became common practice for wealthy people to
dedicate gardens or other grounds to the Sangha for its use, and at quite an
early stage the Sangha was given a roof of its own.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The first few rainy seasons (after the
original one near Benares) were spent in the Bamboo Grove given by King Bim­bisara,
and one day during one of these retreats a rich merchant of Rajagaha visited
this park. Seeing the monks sheltering as best they could he offered to provide
proper dwellings for them. They replied that the Buddha had not so far given
any ruling on this question and they went to ask him. He agreed and, the story
goes, the merchant had sixty houses built in the grove in a single day. The
following day he invited the Buddha and his community for a meal at his place,
at which he formally presented the dwellings to the Sangha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This act of generosity led to another, even
more spectacular one. The merchant's sister was married to a man called Anatha­pindaka
who happened to come to Rajagaha on business the day before the meal to which
the monks had been invited. He arrived to find a tremendous bustle, with cooks
making elab­orate dishes and servants scurrying about preparing for what was
obviously going to be a very important occasion. No one had time to pay the
visitor much attention.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'This is
strange,' thought Anathapindaka, somewhat put out by his reception, 'usually
when I come here my brother-in-law drops everything in order to welcome me, but
today he seems solely concerned with ordering his servants about and preparing
for some big event. Can it be a betrothal that is being arranged? Or perhaps he
has even invited King Bimbisara for a banquet?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Eventually the merchant finished
supervising the prepara­tions and went to greet Anathapindaka. He also
explained what all the activity was about and Anathapindaka was immediately
curious. The next morning he went to the Bamboo Grove to meet the Buddha for
himself. The Buddha was out walking and seeing Anathapindaka coming towards him
he said simply: 'Come, Sudatta.' Surprised and delighted to be addressed by his
first name, Anathapindaka prostrated himself at the Buddha's feet to receive instruction
and in due course became a lay disciple.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Anathapindaka lived at a place called
Savatthi, and he invited the Buddha henceforth to stay there during the rainy
season; the Buddha agreed to this. On returning to Savatthi, Anatha­pindaka
started to look around for somewhere to accommodate the Buddha and his followers
and finally found the ideal spot--a pleasure garden belonging to a prince called
Jeta. Jeta, how­ever, demanded a high price--he would agree to sell the garden
only for as many gold coins as would cover it like a carpet. There a1so
followed a dispute as to whether Jeta had legally contracted to get the park on
those terms, but this was resolved and Anath­apindaka had the gold brought to
the park in cart loads. When all the coins had been spread over the park there
was still a small space left uncovered near the gate. Anathapindaka told his
men to get more coins but by this time Prince Jeta realised this was no
ordinary transaction and he offered the remaining space as a gift. Later Jeta
had a gate-house built over the space, while in time Anathapindaka had dwellings
and other amenities constructed for the use of the Sangha. This place became
known as the Jetavana monastery, and it was henceforth one of the main centres
from which the Buddha operated.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Converts to the Buddha's teaching came from
all backg­rounds and circumstances. One of the most prestigious con­versions in
the eyes of people living at the time must have been that of a man called
Upali. At the same time as the Buddha was travelling around northern India
spreading his message, another great religious leader was busy establishing a
faith that, like Buddhism, still flourishes, though on a much smaller scale. He
was Mahavira, the founder of the Jain sect, which is prob­ably best known for
its strict adherence to the principle of avoid­ing harm to any living creature
(orthodox Jains, for instance, wear a small piece of cloth over their mouths to
prevent them inadvertently breathing in insects). Upali was a prominent fol­lower
of Mahavira.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>On one occasion when the Buddha was staying
near Nalanda (later the site of a famous Buddhist university, the ruins of
which can still be seen), Upali was among those who heard the Buddha speak, and
so attracted was he that he said he would like to become a follower forthwith.
The prospect of winning such an adherent, which would be rather like a
government minister crossing the floor to join the opposition, must have been
highly exciting for the more politically minded of the Buddha's entourage. But
the Buddha himself was not impressed by such considerations. Far from welcoming
Upali he cautioned him: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Think it over
properly, Upali. A man of your distinction should not make hasty decisions.' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Upali, who does not seem to have been
unduly modest about his status, was also surprised at this reaction, though it
only served to con­firm his intention. He replied to the Buddha: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'If it had been
any other religious group that I had asked to join they would have taken me through
the streets in procession, boasting that such a celebrated man had renounced
his creed in favour of theirs. But all you do is advise me to think it over!' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>He congratu­lated the Buddha on his
frankness and thereupon joined the ranks of his followers.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Another dramatic conversion was that of
Punna, who later became a rather zealous spreader of the doctrine. Punna was a
merchant from an island called Sunaparanta (the location of this island is not
cer­tain, though some scholars put it on the west coast of India) and once when
the Buddha was staying at the Jetavana monas­tery at Savatthi, he came to the
town with a caravan of goods to sell. While resting after a day's work he
noticed that large numbers of people were going in the direction of the
monastery; when he asked why he was told they were going to hear the Buddha.
Having nothing better to do he went along too. It was an act of curiosity which
was to change his life, for the effect of hearing one discourse by the Buddha
was such that he handed over his money and the goods still to be sold to his
brother­-in-law, who was his business partner, and became ordained as a monk. Later,
after much spiritual practice, Punna felt he should go back to his home to propagate
the Buddha's teaching there, and accordingly he asked the Buddha's permission.
But the Buddha did not immediately agree; instead he tested Punna's resolution
with a rather quaint catechism, which went as follows:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha: 'Sunaparanta is inhabited by
wild, barbarous tribes. They are wicked, fierce, violent and cruel. They are
also given to abusing and annoying other people. If they abused and annoyed
you, what would you feel?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Punna: 'I would feel that the people of
Sunaparanta are good and gentle people, since at least they are not punching me
or throwing dirt at me.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha: 'But supposing they punched you
or threw dirt at you, what would you feel then?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Punna: 'I would feel that they are good and
gentle people, since at least they are not hitting me with clubs or weapons.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha: 'But supposing they hit you
with clubs or weapons?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Punna: 'Then I would feel they are good and
gentle people, since at least they are not taking my life.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha: 'But supposing they killed
you, Punna, what would you feel then?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Punna: 'I would still think they are good
and gentle people, for then they would be releasing me from this rotten carcass
of my body. I should thank them for doing me a service.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At this the Buddha gave in to Punna's wish
and sent him away with these affectionate words: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Punna, you are
endowed with the greatest gentleness and forbearance. Go and live in Sunaparanta,
go and teach them how to be free, as you yourself are free.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Gratefully, Punna took his leave and went
back to his home­land. Before the end of his first rainy season there, we are
told, he had gathered around him 600 disciples.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In contrast to such cases, many who joined
the Sangha came from poor, unprivileged backgrounds. And no background could be
poorer or less privileged than that of an outcaste.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Buddhism and the Caste\System" pagetitle="Buddhism and the Caste\System"
                     tocentry="Buddhism and the Caste\System">
            <paragraph>One of the fundamental differences between
Buddhism and the Brahminical religion in India at the time concerned caste. The
organisation of society into a structure of castes based on occupations began
with the arrival among the indigenous people of India of Aryan invaders from
central Asia. As mentioned in the opening chapter, four broad groups of castes
were established-Brahmins or priests, Kshatriyas or warriors (the group to
which the Gautama family belonged), Vaishyas or merchants and Sudras or menial
workers. Outside the caste structure altogether were the outcastes, the
untouchables, the lowest of the low. They lived outside the community, in
ghettos of their own, their sole function being to dispose of the rubbish and
waste of the community, and to remain inconspicuous. But this system was not
merely a social structure, it was intimately bound up with the Brahminical
religion, which regarded a man's caste as the reward or punishment for his
karma in pre­vious births. Each caste has its own function and obligations
within society, but the untouchables were not recognised as a part of society
at all. Theirs were the most degrading jobs--the disposal of sewage, street
cleaning, the handling of animal carcasses--and they were expected to keep well
out of the way of caste people, particularly Brahmins. Even today in India, there
are orthodox Brahmins who consider themselves polluted if merely the shadow of
an untouchable should fall on them. But Buddhism was from the beginning
universal. The Buddha borrowed from Brahminism concepts such as karma and re­birth,
giving different interpretations to them-but not caste. This, of course, was
not to the liking of the Brahmins of the time, who no doubt saw the Buddha's
ideas as dangerously sub­versive. The following story illustrates this.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>While the Buddha was staying in Savatthi
one of his personal attendants, Ananda (about whom more will be heard in this
chapter), went each day to the town to beg for alms of food. One day, on his
way back to the community he saw a girl fetch­ing water from a well, and asked
her to give him some to drink. The girl belonged to the lowest rung of
untouchables, and aware of her contemptible status in the eyes of society, she
declined, saying that she was unworthy to give him water. Ananda re­plied:
'Sister, I am not asking about your family or your caste. I am not concerned
with caste. But if you have some water, please give me some to drink.'
Whereupon the girl, whose name was Prakriti, gave him water and fell deeply in
love with him.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The story goes on to tell how, with the aid
of a magic love-­potion prepared by her mother, Prakriti tried to get Ananda to
marry her. Ananda, though sorely tempted at one stage, was saved by the
miraculous intervention of the Buddha. But Prak­riti was not cured of her love,
so the Buddha summoned her to him and while ostensibly sympathising with her
wish, in­structed her in his teaching until she abandoned her feelings for
Ananda and decided to join the Sangha as a nun. She became, it is said, a very
devout follower of the Buddha, with a thorough grasp of his teaching.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The news that the Buddha had ordained an
untouchable girl, however, caused great alarm among the Brahmins and other
leading citizens of Savatthi, and they protested to the King Pasenadi, about
it. The King accordingly went to see the Buddha, along with an impressive
entourage of Brahmins, warriors and others and asked him to explain his
actions. The Buddha replied by telling a story about a man called Trishanku, an
untouchable leader--perhaps the chieftain of a tribe regarded as outside the
caste system. Trishanku had a son called Shardu­lakarna, who was highly
learned, and with parental pride and ambition Trishanku decided to try and get
his son married to the daughter of a distinguished Brahmin called Pushkarasari.
The Brahmin, of course, rejected the suggestion with disdain, whereupon
Trishanku began to debate with him the whole validity of the caste system. He
argued that there was no in­herent difference between members of different
castes in the way that there was between different species of animals or plants.
Moreover, he sought to demonstrate that the link between caste and the doctrine
of reincarnation and karma was a fallacious one. Eventually Pushkarasari was so
impressed by Trishanku's arguments that he gave in and consented to the
marriage. No doubt many of those hearing the Buddha tell this story were less
easily convinced, for the same line of reasoning is still being advanced today,
two and a half millennia later, in the face of those who defend apartheid and
other modern forms of casteism. But at least, it seems, the good citizens of
Savatthi did not make any further fuss about the issue.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Another story concerns an untouchable
called Sunita, whose job was to scavenge the streets. For this work he was paid
barely enough money to keep himself alive, and he slept where he worked, by the
roadside, being unable to afford a proper shelter. He also had to beware
constantly of contaminating any high caste person who happened to come by,
since the likely penalty would be a severe beating. So whenever someone of high
caste approached he left the road and stood at a safe distance away.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One day while he was busy sweeping a road
he saw the Buddha approaching, together with a large retinue of monks. Finding
no place where he could hide himself in time, for he assumed these people to be
caste-born holy men, as indeed they mostly were, he did the next best thing,
flattening himself against a wall and folding his hands in a gesture of
respect. No doubt to his dismay, the Buddha came straight up to him. But far
from addressing him harshly, as he had expected, the Buddha spoke in a friendly
manner. Without beating about the bush he asked Sunita if he would like to give
up his job and follow him instead. Astonished and delighted, Sunita replied: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Sir, no one has
ever before spoken to me in a kind way. Usually I am just ordered about,, If
you will accept a dirty, wretched scavenger like me, then of course I shall
come with you and leave this filthy job.' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha ordained him there and then, so
the story goes, and though he started as an ignorant, unedu­cated man, he later
became a celebrated figure in the Sangha, enjoying the respect of great men.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Return Home" pagetitle="Return Home" tocentry="Return Home">
            <paragraph>Some time after the Buddha had begun his
mission and his renown as a teacher had become widespread, his father, King
Suddhodana, came to learn that he was staying at Rajagaha. So one day he
decided to send a messenger to the Buddha with an invitation to visit his home
city of Kapilavastu and give his own people the benefit of his teaching--though
we may suspect that what the King really wanted was simply to see his son
again. The messenger arrived and met the Buddha, but before he could utter his
invitation the Buddha let him hear his own message, with the result that the
messenger quite forgot the purpose of his visit and joined the Sangha. Puzzled
at the dis­appearance of his messenger the King sent another. The same thing
happened, and so it did until altogether nine messengers had been despatched
and lost. Eventually the King sent a child­hood friend of Siddhartha called
Kaludayi, and now the Buddha listened. Accompanied by a large number of monks
he set off for Kapilavastu and took up residence at a place prepared for them
called the Banyan Monastery. It was seven years since he had left the city.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>When the word got around Kapilavastu people
flocked to see this son of the soil who had become so famous. His own relatives
began to speak of him in possessive terms as 'our cousin', or 'our nephew', and
told their children: 'Go up to him and pay your respects.' But the Buddha
realised that there was more local pride behind this welcome than genuine
interest in his teaching; it would require effort and patience before the
citizens would accept him for what he really was. According to one account he
had to resort to the miraculous device of appearing suspended in the air in
order to convince them; at that, it is said, everyone, including the King
himself, prostrated them­selves in reverence. However that may be, when the
Buddha set out next day with his begging bowl and started going from door to
door the King was greatly upset. He went into the street himself and said to
the Buddha: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Why are you
disgracing me in this way? Why can you not have food in my palace? Is it right
for you to beg your food in the very city where you once travelled about in
splendour? How can you put me to shame like this?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha replied that he did not mean to
put the King to shame but that begging food was 'our custom'.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'What do you mean?' said the King. 'Nobody
in our family has ever had to beg. What do you mean "our custom"?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Your Majesty,' said the Buddha, 'It is not
the custom of your royal family. But it is the custom of true sages. Such
people have always lived by receiving their food in this way.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Nevertheless, being a pragmatic man, the
Buddha eventually gave in to the King's repeated appeals to have his food in
the palace, and decided to try and convince his father of his teaching on the
King's home ground. He was successful, for the King eventually became a devoted
follower of the Buddha, his own son.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Despite the initial difficulty in
persuading the people not to regard him merely as a local celebrity, the
Buddha's visit to Kapilavastu greatly enriched the Sangha. Many of his kinsmen,
including some of his closest relatives, became his followers during his stay
there.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Prince Nanda was a step-brother of
Siddhartha and when he reached the age of thirty-five the ageing King
Suddhodana, no doubt until then hoping there might still be some possibility of
his son returning to the kingdom, decided to give him Sidd­hartha's place in
the palace. He also arranged for him to marry a princess, one Janapada Kalyani,
and prepared a separate palace for them to live in. All these plans, the King
decided, would be brought to fruition at a single big celebration, and when he
knew that the Buddha had agreed to return to Kapila­vastu he decided to hold
the festival during his visit so that Nanda and Janapada Kalyani could receive
his blessing.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(the story of Nanda becoming a monk is
omitted here, as we meet it later, in the "purification" teachings)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The other notable convert from among his
family during this visit to Kapilavastu was his own son, Rahula, who was born
at the time that Siddhartha left home in search of enlightenment. Rahula, now
aged seven, had been brought up by his mother, Yasodhara, and his grandfather,
King Suddhodana. No doubt Yasodhara felt as much bereaved by her husband's
departure as the King, and when the Buddha returned to Kapilavastu, she decided
to make an approach to him through Rahula. Her ostensible concern, according to
the accounts, was to secure for Rahula the inheritance which his father had
abandoned, and no doubt this was indeed a preoccupation. But looking at the
incident in a wider context, and particularly in view of Yasod­hara's later
history, one is tempted to see in it an element of forlorn longing for a
husband who had not merely forsaken her but renounced all worldly attachments.
At any rate, on the seventh day of the Buddha's visit, we are told, Yasodhara
dressed Rahula in fine clothes and took him to a place where the Buddha was
having his meal. She pointed him out to Rahula and said: 'Darling, do you know
who that is?' Rahula replied in the matter-of-fact way of children: 'That's the
Buddha, mother.' At this Yasodhara's eyes filled with tears, and she went on:
'Darling, that holy man with the golden complexion, with all his disciples
around him, is your father, and once he had great property. Go up to him and
say: "Father, I am a prince, When I become king I shall be a king of
kings. Let me have my property, for what belongs to the father must belong to
the son." '</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Rahula did as he was told, and approached
the Buddha with the respectful, if somewhat ornate, greeting: 'Father, I love
even your shadow.' The Buddha finished his meal and got up to leave, but Rahula
followed him repeating what his mother had told him to say. The Buddha made no
reply, nor did he attempt to discourage the child. But as he walked he thought: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'He desires his
father's wealth, but that is only a worldly thing, a source of trouble. I shall
give him instead far greater wealth, the sevenfold noble wealth which I
received at the foot of the Bodhi tree. Then he will be the possessor of an
excellent inheri­tance.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>So when they reached the monastery, the
Buddha asked one of his two chief disciples, Upatissa, to ordain Rahula a monk.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The news of this was a further shock to the
long-suffering King Suddhodana, who went to the Buddha and respectfully but firmly
urged him not to ordain children in future without the permission of their
parents. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'When you left
home it made me very very sad,' he said. 'When Nanda left home I was also very
unhappy, and my heart ached. Then I began to concentrate my love on Rahula, but
now you have brought him here and ordained him as well.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha sympathised with this plea and
thereafter no one was allowed to join the Sangha without the approval of his
parents or guardian. Later this requirement of permission was extended to
include the wives of intending members. Rahula nevertheless remained a monk and
he features in one episode in which the Buddha teaches the importance of
truthfulness. At the time Rahula was aged eleven, and the picturesque style of
the Buddha's teaching suggests not just a holy man instruct­ing a pupil but a
kindly father giving guidance to his son. According to the text the Buddha
picked up a scoop used for pouring water and put a little water in it. Then he
said to Rahula: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Rahula, do you
see this drop of water in the scoop?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Rahula replied
with proper respect: 'Yes, Sir.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Well,' said the
Buddha, 'people who tell lies have as much good in them as that.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Then the Buddha went on to say the same
thing in different ways: first he threw out the water to demonstrate how un­truthful
people throw away their virtue, then he turned the scoop upside down to show
how little regard they have for their virtue, and finally he compared them to
the empty, hollow scoop itself.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha followed this with another
metaphor. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Picture a royal
elephant, Rahula, an elephant of high breeding, grown to his full stature, with
tusks as long as the shafts of a chariot, and plenty of experience of war. In
battle he performs well, using his legs and body properly, also his head and
tusks and even his ears and tail. Yet he holds back with his trunk. His rider
thinks: "This elephant uses his limbs and body well, but he keeps his
trunk back. He is not fully devoting himself to the service of the king."
But once he starts to use all his body, in­cluding his trunk, then his rider
says: "Ah, now he is devoting himself fully. He has no more need of
training." </paragraph>
            <paragraph>It is the same
with people who are not wholly truthful, Rahula, until they are it cannot be
said that they are devoting themselves fully. So, Rahula, you must discipline
yourself never to speak untruth, even jokingly.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha concluded his lesson with the
question: </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'What do you
think a mirror is for, Rahula?'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'To look at
yourself in, Sir,' replied Rahula.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Right,' said
the Buddha. 'And in just the same way you should constantly reflect upon the
acts of your body, of your speech and of your mind.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Another of the Buddha's kinsmen to join the
Sangha was the man who was to become perhaps the best-known and best-loved
figure in Buddhist history--his cousin Ananda, who became his personal
attendant. During the first twenty years of his ministry the Buddha had no
regular attendant; various monks waited on him, performing tasks such as
carrying his bowl or his spare robes. But a couple of incidents determined the
Buddha to have one regular per­sonal attendant. One of these incidents is
almost a comic moral tale. One day the Buddha was going on a journey
accompanied by a monk called Nagasamala, and when they arrived at a fork in the
road they disagreed about which way they should pro­ceed. Nagasamala, who was
carrying the Buddha's bowl and robes, put them down on the ground and took the
road of his choice, leaving the Buddha to pick up his belongings and go by the
other one. Unfortunately for Nagasamala, he encountered some robbers who took
his bowl and robes and hit him on the head. He rejoined the Buddha with a sore
head and a heart full of remorse for his disobedience.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>No doubt as a busy teacher whose time was
much in demand, the Buddha felt he needed a reliable and constant attendant and
the above incident merely illustrated that the practice he had followed for
twenty years was not satisfactory. Besides, he was now aged over fifty-five. So
during a stay at the Jetavana monas­tery he announced his intention to appoint
a personal attendant. Both his chief disciples, Upatissa and Kolita, offered
their ser­vices but the Buddha declined, saying the work they were doing was
too valuable to be sacrificed in that way. Other leading monks came forward but
were similarly rejected. Eventually the name of Ananda was suggested, though he
modestly refused to push himself forward and waited for the Buddha himself to
nominate him.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Ananda was the son of Amitodana, who was a
younger brother of the Buddha's father, King Suddhodana. His name means 'joy',
and he was so named, it is said, because his birth was a source of great joy to
his parents. He entered the order, along with other Sakyan princes, when the
Buddha paid a visit to his home territory.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Ananda's devotion to the Buddha was total.
From that time until the Buddha's death he was his constant servant, looking
after his room, washing his bowl and robes, massaging his body and always
keeping close to the Buddha in case he was needed. Later, the Buddha described
Ananda as a learned, mindful, well-behaved and resolute disciple. Ananda is
also famous for the part he played in the admission of women to Buddhist
monasticism, an event dealt with later in this chapter. But partly because of
his role in this controversial matter he came in for a great deal of criticism
from some of his contemporaries and seems to have been treated as a scapegoat
or focus for the grievances of some of his fellow monks.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>So great, however, was Ananda's devotion,
say the texts, that he never had enough time for meditation and so did not
attain Enlightenment during the Buddha's lifetime. Only afterwards did he do
so, in time to take a leading part in the first convoca­tion of 500 perfect
saints who recited and memorised for pos­terity the teachings of the Buddha a
few months after his death.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Inclusion of Women" pagetitle="Inclusion of Women"
                     tocentry="Inclusion of Women">
            <paragraph>It may seem odd in the social climate of
today, at least in the West, that the Buddha did not initially favour the
admission of women to the Sangha. It is more easily understandable in the
context of the society of his time, in which, as is still largely the case in
India, women had clearly defined obligations and responsibilities within the
family and were not expected to want to go off alone in search of the spiritual
life. Besides, to cut loose from their family and lead a homeless life would
immediately expose them to dangers against which they were not considered able
to defend them­selves; so if the attitude of their menfolk was possessive it
was also protective. The breaking down of this mental barrier was another event
involving members of his own family.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Some time after the visit to Kapilavastu
described above the Buddha returned for another stay. In the meantime his
father, King Suddhodana, had died, though not before achieving saint­hood as a
devout follower of his son's teachings. While the Buddha was staying in a place
called Nigrodha's park, Suddho­dana's widowed queen, Mahapajapati Gotami, who
had brought Siddhartha up after the death of his own mother, came to see him
and asked to be ordained into his community. The Buddha refused, and remained
adamant when she asked a second and a third time. Mahapajapati went away
sorrowful, and the Buddha moved to a place called Vesali where his community
had a monastic lodging in a wood.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>But Queen Mahapajapati was not so easily
put off and one day she arrived at Vesali, accompanied by some of her Sakyan
kinswomen, to try again. To demonstrate her sincerity she had had her hair cut
off and was dressed in yellow cloth like the Buddha's disciples. She was standing
at the entrance to the monastery when she was discovered by Ananda. He, not un­naturally
surprised to see her and dismayed by her condition, since she was covered in
dust, her feet were swollen with walk­ing and she was sobbing miserably, asked
her: 'Gotami, what are you doing standing out here?' 'Lord Ananda,' she
replied, 'I am standing out here because the Buddha will not accept women for
ordination.' Ananda, moved by the sight of Mahapa­japati, rushed off to see the
Buddha, and immediately put to him the question of admitting women. The Buddha
was adam­ant as before, so Ananda decided to apply the Buddha's own technique
of logical persuasion in order to bring him around. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>'Supposing,'
said Ananda, 'women were allowed to follow the religious life, would they be
capable of achieving Enlight­enment?' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha could not deny so, so he replied: 'They would, Ananda.' Seizing his advantage, Ananda went on: 'In that case
surely it would be a good thing if women could receive ordina­tion. And
especially Mahapajapati Gotami, who nursed you and brought you up so devotedly
after your own mother died.' At this the Buddha gave in, though he stipulated a
number of con­ditions for women ordinands, under which they must accept strict
discipline and submission to the authority of monks. Mahapajapati thus became
the first Buddhist nun, and in due course she was joined by other female
members of the Sakyan clan, including Siddhartha's wife, Yasodhara.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Tensions in Sangha" pagetitle="Tensions in Sangha"
                     tocentry="Tensions in Sangha">
            <paragraph>In common with all groups and organisations
once they have reached a certain stage of development, the Sangha became prey
to politics and schismatic tendencies. The best-known example of this is the
episode of Devadatta, the Buddha's cousin and childhood companion. Devadatta
had joined the Sangha along with other Sakyans during the Buddha's visit to
Kapilavastu, but it seems the rivalry, if not jealousy, that he had exhibited
at the time of the dispute over the swan was not abated by maturity. Thus, we
read, on one occasion when the Buddha was visiting Kosambi, the territory of
King Bimbisara, Devadatta decided to chal­lenge the Buddha's leadership of the
Sangha, suggesting that the Congregation of Monks should be turned over to his
charge. The Buddha refused and issued a public proclamation denouncing
Devadatta and dissociating the Sangha from his actions. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Devadatta thereupon made an ally of King
Bimbisara's son, Ajatasattu, who was becoming impatient for his father's crown,
and suggested to him that each should assassinate the man who stood in his way.
Ajatasattu duly got rid of his father and Devadatta prepared to do the same
with the Buddha. Alto­gether, we are told, he made three attempts. First he
hired assas­sins to kill him but they fell victim to the Buddha's persuasive­ness
and became converts instead. Then Devadatta climbed to the top of a mountain
called the Vulture Peak and hurled a rock down on the Buddha as he passed
below; but the rock only wounded the Buddha. Finally he despatched an elephant
to attack him, but like Daniel with the lions the Buddha used his moral power
to subdue the animal's wrath.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The story of Devadatta's unsuccessful bid
for leadership of the Sangha, like much else in the life of the Buddha, is
threaded with strands of legend. But there are grounds for thinking there may
also be an element of propaganda in the way he is pictured for, as his next
step shows, he was the author of the first schism in Buddhist history. Having
failed to kill the Buddha, Deva­datta went to him with a list of five demands.
These in essence called for a strict, puritanical application of the Buddhist
prin­ciples of homelessness and poverty, as well as vegetarianism. It may be
this was a cunning attempt to call the Buddha's bluff, or there may indeed have
been some disquiet at the breadth of the Middle Way trodden by some of his
followers. But as one who had spent years seeking the Truth through self-mor­tification
the Buddha was alert to the danger of a cult of disci­pline and firmly rebuked
Devadatta for his ideas. Devadatta then broke with the Order and set up his own
community with five hundred of the Buddha's followers, though these soon returned
to the Sangha under the persuasion of the Buddha's two chief disciples, Kolita
and Upatissa.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The story goes that towards the end of his
life, when he had been suffering illness for some months, Devadatta repented of
his behaviour and decided to make his peace with the Buddha. He had himself
carried on a litter to the Jetavana monastery, where the Buddha was staying,
and, raising himself up, cried out: 'I seek refuge in the Buddha.' Thereupon
the Buddha re­ceived him back into the Sangha, prophesying that he would
eventually achieve Buddhahood.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There was jealousy, too, outside the
community. The first conversions of untouchables had caused an outcry among the
orthodox, and as the fame of the Buddha spread more and more, with people of
both high and low estimate coming to honour him, so did disquiet grow among
other religious leaders. Some of them went and appealed to the crowds: 'Is the
monk Gautama the only Buddha? What about us? We are also Buddhas ! You should
give us alms and show us honour in the same way.' But this achieved little, and
so subtler means were adopted which bore the characteristic stamp of political
under­handedness as it has appeared in many places and at many times in
history.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Two separate plots were hatched by
opponents of the Buddha while he was staying at his Jetavana headquarters. The
first revolved around a young woman of outstanding beauty called Chincha who
had renounced the world for a life as a kind of wandering nun. For reasons
which are not clear, Chincha felt herself under an obligation to a clique of
the Buddha's opponents, and they saw in her a means of discrediting him. As for
Chincha, despite having renounced the world, she was not lacking in worldly
imagination, and once she was persuaded to co-operate in the plot she carried
out her part skilfully.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>While the Buddha was in residence at the
Jetavana monas­tery, it was common for people living in the nearby town of
Savatthi to stroll out in the morning to offer him their greetings and again
later in the day to hear him preach, returning home in the evening. Dressed in
a gaily-coloured cloak, redolent of per­fume and bearing garlands of flowers in
her hands, Chincha also started to make a daily journey from Savatthi in the
direction</paragraph>
            <paragraph>of Jetavana, though in her case she set out
in the evening and after spending the night in a lodging provided by the
plotters returned to the town next morning. So each evening as she went out
towards Jetavana she passed the crowds making their way home while each morning
the procedure was reversed. Naturally, this soon aroused curiosity, and people
started to question her about her conduct. At first she merely replied: 'What
business is that of yours?' But after a few weeks of this, by which time her
travels had become well known, she began to tell questioners: 'I have spent the
night in a perfumed chamber alone with the monk Gautama.' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>As time went on she wrapped cloth around
her waist to make it appear she was preg­nant, and started openly saying the
monk Gautama was respon­sible. Finally, when about nine months had elapsed, she
tucked a piece of wood under her cloak and went to Jetavana while the Buddha
was preaching. Staggering as if exhausted by her effort she broke into his
sermon and called out sarcastically in front of everyone: 'Mighty monk, what a
mighty throng is here listening to you preach the Truth; how sweet is your
voice, how soft your lips. Yet you are the one by whom I have conceived a
child, which is due at any time, and you have done nothing to help me prepare
for it to be born.' She went on some more in this vein and ended: 'You know
well enough how to take your pleasure, but you do not care to take
responsibility for the child you have fathered.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Buddha, who had been interrupted in the
middle of his teaching, merely replied: 'My sister, only you and I know whether
what you say is true or false.' At that moment a gust of wind blew her cloak
open, and the piece of wood fell out, straight onto her feet. It must have been
a hefty block of wood, for according to the story, it cut off her toes.
Scandalised, the crowd rose up crying: 'This hag is reviling the Buddha,' and
promptly drove her away, to the chagrin of the plotters, not to mention the
toeless Chincha herself, and the greater honour of the Buddha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Undaunted by this reversal, however, the
monks hostile to the Buddha later made a similar though more elaborate attempt
to discredit him. This time the principal figure was a woman called Sundari
who, like Chincha, was of outstanding beauty and, like her, was persuaded to
make it appear she was the Buddha's lover. But in her case events quickly took
an unfortu­nate turn, for she had been playing her role for only a few days
when the monks hired some ruffians to murder her and throw her body on a
rubbish heap near where the Buddha was staying. On her disappearance the monks
began to make a hue and cry and went to complain to the King, taking the
opportunity to mention that she had lately been spending her nights at Jeta­vana.
With the King's approval they organised a search and when her body was found on
the rubbish heap they brought it ceremoniously into the town alleging to the
King and the public at large that she had been killed by the Buddha's fol­lowers
in order to cover up his affair with her. There ensued much public concern, but
when this was reported to the Buddha he merely remarked 'Anyone who declares
something has occurred when it has not must accept the sad consequences of his
evil action.' </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Meanwhile the King sent ont his own men to
investigate the incident. Before long they same upon the mur­derers, who were
drinking with the proceeds of their work. They had started quarrelling about
the murder, and were hur­ling accusations at each other when the King's men
found them, so they were immediately taken before the King where they confessed
the whole thing. The King had the monks concerned brought before him and
ordered them to go through the city making a public confession of their crime
before receiving due punishment as murderers.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Nirvana" pagetitle="Nirvana" tocentry="Nirvana">
            <paragraph>(eh)The Buddha
carried out his ministry for forty-five years. The first intimation that he
could not continue for much longer came while he was visiting a village called
Beluva to spend the rainy season. During his stay there he fell ill, and began
to suffer severe pain. He bore the pain uncomplainingly, but he thought to
himself: 'It is not right for me to pass away and finally attain Nirvana until
I have spoken to my attendants and taken leave of the Sangha.' (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)So by force of
will he fought the illness and found the strength to go on. Then the Buddha
summoned Ananda and said to him: (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'Ananda, what does the Sangha need from me? The Law I have taught is
clear, there is no secret version of it distinct from the one I have explained;
I have not kept a closed fist on anything. Now I am old, Ananda, I am past
eighty. So, Ananda, let each of you make a refuge  for himself, an island; and
let that refuge be the Law and nothing else.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Their retreat
ended, the Community once more set out and in due course came to a mango grove
belonging to a man called Chunda. On learning that the Buddha was present,
Chunda went to see him, and after hearing instruction from him invited the
Community to take food with him the next day. The follow­ing morning the Buddha
went with his followers to Chunda's house, where they were served a rich meal
which included mushrooms. It was after, and perhaps because of, this meal that
the Buddha's sickness returned. This time there was to be no recovery.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Despite his
illness, the Buddha went on his way, coming eventually to a place called
Kusinara. Here he settled in a grove of sala trees on the bank of the river
Hirannavati. Ananda pre­pared a couch for him between two sala trees and the
Buddha lay down. Then, addressing Ananda, he again made the point that it was
not he himself, but what he said, that mattered. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'It may be, Ananda,' he said, 'that in some of you the thought will
arise "the word of the Master is ended; we have no teacher any more".
But that is not the way to look at it, Ananda. The Law which I have explained
and laid down for you all, let that, after I am gone, be your teacher.'(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The Buddha then
addressed the monks around him. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)'It is in the nature of all things that take form to dissolve again.
Strive earnestly' (to attain perfection). (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)These were the
last words of the Buddha who then, it is said, moved through various rap­turous
stages of meditation until he passed away. His remains were cremated with the
honours due to a royal person.(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Consolidating the Teachings" pagetitle="Consolidating the Teachings"
                     tocentry="Consolidating the Teachings">
            <paragraph>Notwithstanding all they had learnt about
the transience of life, some of the monks began to mourn bitterly the passing
of their teacher. There was one present, however, who took quite a different
attitude. This was a monk called Subhadda who had entered the Sangha in his old
age, and for him the death of the Buddha was a relief. 'Enough, friends, do not
be sorrowful,' he said. 'Do not lament, we are well rid of the Great Monk. We
have been frustrated by his saying "you may do this, you may not do
that". Now we can do as we like, and not do those things we do not want to
do.'</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This, of course, was a signal for the
Buddha's discipline to be abandoned, and for the Sangha to break up in confusion.
So it was interpreted by one of the senior monks, the great Kas­sapa of
Uruvela, who decided that a full and authentic record of the Buddha's teaching
must be established as quickly as pos­sible. Accordingly, an assembly was
arranged in the city of Raja­gaha, with the blessing of King Ajatasattu, and
500 monks who had attained sainthood were summoned to attend. With Kas­sapa
presiding, this *First Council* rehearsed and committed to memory all that
was known about the Buddha's teaching. Upali and Ananda played leading parts in
formulating respectively, under the interrogation of Kassapa, the Discipline
and the Dis­courses. The Council lasted seven months.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The material produced at this Council was
only committed to writing at the fourth Council held in Ceylon in about 80 BC.
The Buddha's sayings and teachings were divided into three</paragraph>
            <paragraph>sections which became known as the
'Tipitaka' or 'three baskets of the Canon'. These are: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The Vinaya-the disciplinary rules for the
     Sangha.</li>
               <li>The Sutta-the discourses given by the
     Buddha on different occasions. </li>
               <li>The Abhidhamma-the philosophical and
     psychological development of the teaching which was formally closed only
     at the third Council in about 246 BC</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>It is important to appreciate the nature of
the texts that have come down to us, particularly the discourses in the Sutta
sec­tion. Originally, it was intended that each of these discourses ­which
consist of terse sayings of either the Buddha or one of his leading
disciples-should be memorised, probably due to lack of durable writing materials.
For this reason the device of repeating key phrases was instituted in order to
make the task easier. The reader may recall that the tradition of oral transmis­sion
was followed by other Indian contemporaries of the Buddha as well as by teachers
in China and Greece at that time.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="3" title="The Buddha&#xA;and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version"
               pagetitle="The Buddha&#xA;and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version"
               tocentry="The Buddha&#xA;and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version">
         <subsection title="The Buddha\and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version"
                     pagetitle="The Buddha\and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version"
                     tocentry="The Buddha\and the Life of the BuddhA Mahayana Version">
            <image width="434" src="module1_files.image004.png" align=""/>
            <image width="209" src="module1_files.image005.png" align="left"/>
            <paragraph>We will approach this in several steps:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>A very simple introduction to
     Buddha Nature and the Three Kayas, taken from a talk (_The Ways of the
     Bodhisattva and the Arhat_) given to Scottish schoolchildren and
     teachers. </li>
            </list>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The Introduction to the Three
     Kayas from "Maitreya on Buddha Nature". </li>
            </list>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>The full text on the Nirmanakaya
     from "Maitreya on Buddha Nature".</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>_The
Buddha descending into our world                                       _</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="1.   A very simple introduction to Buddha Nature and the\Three Kayas"
                     pagetitle="1.   A very simple introduction to Buddha Nature and the\Three Kayas"
                     tocentry="1.   A very simple introduction to Buddha Nature and the\Three Kayas">
            <paragraph>When we are new to Buddhism, "Buddha" usually evokes
someone: an historical figure who gave us the Buddhist teachings. But as time
goes by, it becomes clear that the historical Buddha Shakyamuni simply achieved
something that we all, one day, in one life or another, will achieve. What he
discovered--and totally perfected--is inside each and every one of us. It is our
true nature; our *buddha-nature*. But this does not mean that each of us
is really, at heart, an Indian prince! It means that locked up in each and
every one of us, there is perfect love, perfect compassion, infinite wisdom,
limitless peace and harmony and a great ability to help and guide others. It is
the inner light. It is our ultimate potential. We just need to discover it and
to remove all the layers of illusion covering it and blocking off its power.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This timeless light, universal peace or cosmic wisdom
manifests in three ways, known as the three _kaya_:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.     This Buddha nature, just as
it is and as _only a Buddha will ever know it_, is called *_dharmakaya_*: _body of dharma_. It is a
limitless, cosmic wisdom: the wisdom of voidness. That voidness has infinite,
unconditional compassion as its very fibre. Dharmakaya is formless because
wisdom and compassion have no shape, colour, sound, smell or form whatsoever.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.     Bodhisattvas who have
completely shed the first, gross, layer of blockage, known as _afflictions_
or _defilements_ and who thereby have gone beyond rebirth, and who are in
the process of shedding the second, subtle, layer of blockage (_dualistic
thought_) *are very close to this Buddha nature but they can only experience
it indirectly*, through the filters of their senses. Though it is formless,
they _see_ it as thousands of different Buddha forms, in various pure
paradises. They _hear_ it as deeply moving teachings expressing the
universal laws of truth. Etc. Etc. The whole experience of their senses is an
uninterrupted mental 'movie' of transcendent perfection. The way Buddha-nature
appears in these bodhisattva's minds is called *_sambhogakaya_*:
the _enjoyment body_, meaning the visions and experiences of purity _enjoyed_
by saintly bodhisattvas. These are sometimes called _pure appearances_ or _pure
lands_. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.     Other beings that, like most
of us, are still in the world of rebirth and suffering, migrating from life to
life, can also have an experience of buddha nature. They will meet enlightened
beings, have wisdom experiences, perhaps see a Buddha or a being of light in a
vision or awaken to one of life's deep truths and so on and so forth. This
happens in moments when the mind is pure and open. It does not last and is not
nearly as pure or vivid and precise as the experience of the bodhisattvas
mentioned above. The bodhisattvas' experience is uninterrupted. Nevertheless,
when worldly beings have experience of the buddha mind, it is usually a
remarkable moment which changes and shapes the whole of their life. This aspect
of buddha-nature or buddha mind is called *_nirmanakaya_*:
the _emanated body_--the truth as it _emanates_ in their personal
world.    (eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="2.   The Introduction to the Three Kayas from &#34;Maitreya on\Buddha Nature&#34;[10]"
                     pagetitle="2.   The Introduction to the Three Kayas from &#34;Maitreya on\Buddha Nature&#34;[10]"
                     tocentry="2.   The Introduction to the Three Kayas from &#34;Maitreya on\Buddha Nature&#34;[10]">
            <a href="#_ftn10">[10]</a>
            <paragraph>This comes from the topic known as _Actualisation_
in the chapter on _Enlightenment_: a major source of information on the
three kayas for Mahayana Buddhists. It is presented first in brief and then in
more detail. The text in red below represents the original root verses<a href="#_ftn11">[11]</a> and the black a commentary
based upon the explanations of contemporary masters, mainly Khenchen Thrangu
Rinpoche.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="in brief " pagetitle="in brief " tocentry="in brief ">
               <paragraph>The
_Actualisation_ section is about enlightenment and illusion--and their
inter-penetration. It could have been translated as _manifestation_ or as _penetration_,
for the following reasons: </paragraph>
               <list kind="ul">
                  <li>From
     the angle of enlightenment, this section shows the various ways in which
     enlightenment's unique nature _manifests _as the three _kaya_: to
     totally-pure beings, to the partially pure and to the impure,
     respectively. </li>
                  <li>From
     the angle of the non-enlightened, it shows how non-enlightened minds can _penetrate_
     enlightenment's mysteries. </li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>This
is a fairly long section of the chapter. First the main subject matter is
introduced in verses 205 through to 208. Then greater detail is given in verses
209 through to 228.  It starts by pointing to the void nature at the very heart
of enlightenment and known as _dharmadhatu_: "the true expanse of
everything". It answers the question, "Who really understands
it?"</paragraph>
               <paragraph>205.                 Beginningless, centreless
and endless, completely indivisible,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       free from the two, free
from the three, stainless and concept-free,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       such is dharmadhatu. Understanding of its nature</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       is the vision of the
yogin who abides in meditation.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_            _</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*_Dharmadhatu_*, is explained through five
characteristics. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It is
not a creation*
and is therefore never had a beginning, has no centre and will never end. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
The
voidness of dharmadhatu *cannot be separated in
any way from its primordial wisdom*<a href="#_ftn12">[12]</a>.
Voidness and wisdom are not like black and white strands of thread, woven into
a rope in which each colour is still visible, despite the mixing of the
threads. This might have been the case, were voidness a mere absence, such as
the absence of horns on a rabbit. But here voidness _is_ the wisdom that
recognises the absurdity of any limiting, defining projection within the
limitless expanse of interdependence. The _absence_ of defining illusion _is_
the _presence_ of wisdom, and not mere blankness.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It is
free from the two intellectual extremes* of overstatement and understatement.
The former would tend to attribute a lasting self, soul or God to the
enlightened nature and the latter would deny it or underestimate it and its
relationship with interdependence.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It is
free from the three obscurations, *i.e. defilements<a href="#_ftn13">[13]</a>,
the cognitive obscuration<a href="#_ftn14">[14]</a>
and obstacles to spontaneous, perfect meditation.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It
cannot be the object of thoughts* or of any dualistic perception. Hence it is _solely_
the 'vision' of the buddha eyes<a href="#_ftn15">[15]</a>
of primordial wisdom: those of the supreme Yogin, the Buddha.       </paragraph>
               <paragraph>206.                 Unfathomable, greater in
number than sand grains in the Ganges,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       inconceivable and
unequalled are the qualities </paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       of the immaculate space
of the tath̄agata,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       purged of every defect
and related conditioning.  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>_            _</paragraph>
               <paragraph>*This
verse presents the five characteristics of dharmakaya:* whereas _dharmadhatu_ represents the voidness
aspect of enlightenment, *_dharmakaya_* represents its primordial
wisdom, which is:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*Unfathomable*, inasmuch as this wisdom
has so many qualities and these are not located in any precise place or within
any particular concrete reality. Normal wisdom is wise about something,
somewhere and is quantifiable. Enlightenment is the innate wisdom about each
and every thing and hence encompasses everything, everywhere, with an
unimaginably vast and deep panoply of qualities.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
These
qualities of wisdom are truly *incalculable*, greater in number than the
grains of sand on the banks and bed of the river Ganges.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*They
are inconceivable*,
since this wisdom is so profound and unique.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It is
unequalled*
by anything, be it in the world and tainted by defilement or be it comprised
within the fruition of the hīnaȳana
path, "merely" pure peace.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
*It is
immaculate*.
The previous four qualities referred directly to the primordial wisdom of _dharmakaya_
and this last point highlights the purity of that wisdom, free from every
obscuration and associated mental conditioning. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Having
seen what it really is, we now consider enlightenment as it is experienced by
beings other than Buddhas. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>207.                 By various facets of the
true dharma,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       Through its radiant
embodiments and diligence</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       In accomplishing the aim
of liberating beings,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       Its deeds are like those
of a king of wishing-gems.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       Although it takes
different 'substantial' forms,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       It is not really of such
a character.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_            _</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The five characteristics\of sambhogakaya:"
                           pagetitle="The five characteristics\of sambhogakaya:"
                           tocentry="The five characteristics\of sambhogakaya:">
               <paragraph>·         
The *various
facets* are the _deep_ teachings of dharma, expressing voidness, and
the _vast_ ones, expressing all the manifold details of the various paths
to enlightenment. Using a body, speeech and mind analogy, _dharmakaya_ is
the mind of enlightenment and _sambhogakaya_ is its uninterrupted speech.
Within _sambhogakaya_, one finds further subdivision into body, speech and
mind qualities. These are those of its *speech *(i.e. speech of the
speech).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
The deep
and vast teachings are experienced by bodhisattvas as being given by *radiant
forms* of Buddhas, in their respective pure lands. These forms exhibit the
thirty-two major<a href="#_ftn16">[16]</a>
and eighty other<a href="#_ftn17">[17]</a>
signs of a fully enlightened being. This is the *body* aspect (i.e. body
of the speech).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
The *mind*
of _sambhogakaya_ is continuously and diligently engaged in its natural
activity of *liberating beings*.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
The _sambhogakaya_
accomplishes its *various tasks* with complete naturalness and
spontaneity, and without prior thought or intention. In this respect, it is
like a wish-fulfilling gem: to be close to it magnetizes results.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·         
Its
deeds take the myriad forms of the *pure lands*, which in turn constitute
the basis from which not only the bodhisattvas of the ten levels, but also
other beings, are benefited. Although these manifestations _appear_ to be real
and substantial, they are not.                  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>208.                 The form aspects are the
cause, establishing worldlings</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       on the path to peace,
bringing them to maturity and predicting.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       Moreover, their presence
always graces these worlds</paragraph>
               <paragraph>                       just as space is the
constant abode of the element of form.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_            _</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The nirmanakaya:" pagetitle="The nirmanakaya:"
                           tocentry="The nirmanakaya:">
               <paragraph>This
is the embodiment of enlightenment perceptible by beings still under the sway
of samsara's delusions, but with relatively little obscuration. One can
recognise three main stages of the development of such beings in which the _nirmanakaya_
plays a special role. The first is that of leading them away from worldliness
and into the Buddhist path. The second is that of helping those already on the
path to gain realisation and purify their defilements. The third is that of
predicting, to those who are already very pure, the time and place of their
future enlightenment.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>The
_nirmanakaya_ is permanent in the sense that it is always active
somewhere. As the activity can take the form of appearing in a world, teaching
and passing away, as did Buddha Shakyamuni, one might think of _nirmanakaya_
as being quite impermanent. Yet, on further reflection, when one considers all
the other _nirmanakaya_ activity in this world and other worlds, it
becomes apparent that there is uninterrupted activity. Just as space is
ever-present in the various animal, human and other dimensions, whatever the
comings and goings of individual beings and geographical features, so is the
radiance of _nirmanakaya_ (_sprul.sku_ in Tibetan, pronounced _tulku_)--mind's
truth and wisdom--constantly active in the worlds of confusion. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>One
can consider the above from a slightly different angle. The permanent presence
of _nirmanakaya_ gives a constant potential for 'spiritual' experience.
Once a being's mind opens to this potential through faith and good karma, he or
she will find the guidance needed at that point, whether the world around the
person is spiritual or not. This is very vividly exemplified in the life
stories of Naropa and Gampopa<a href="#_ftn18">[18]</a>
and it is very encouraging: no matter where you happen to be, unspoiled faith
will open up the doorways to enlightenment in a way which is perfectly tailored
to your own mind<a href="#_ftn19">[19]</a>.             
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>We leave the _in brief_ verses
here.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="2.    The Nirmanakaya from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;"
                     pagetitle="2.    The Nirmanakaya from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;"
                     tocentry="2.    The Nirmanakaya from &#34;Maitreya on Buddha Nature&#34;">
            <paragraph>(from the _in detail_ section of
the "Actualisation" topic in the Enlightenment chapter.)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The _nirmanakaya_ referred to here is a 'supreme _nirmanakaya_'<a href="#_ftn20">[20]</a>, such as the historical
Buddha Shakyamuni or the future Buddha, Maitreya. These emanations manifest,
even to worldly beings, as having the thirty-two major marks and eighty signs
of perfection of an Enlightened Being, teaching dharma in order to set the
world into a cycle of wisdom and goodness. According to the Good Aeon Sutra,
1,002 such Buddhas come during the lifetime of this world, to awaken it over
and over again to the timeless universal truths. Shakyamuni was the fourth of
these. Maitreya, the 'Loving One', will be the fifth, and the being who is
known in these times as the Gyalwa Karmapa, is an emanation of the bodhisattva
who will be the sixth, the 'Lion Buddha'.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The various major events of Shakyamuni's
life, such as his family background, his asceticism, etc., were not simple
accidents but the classical, meaningful and perfect conclusion to a very long
and special story. In Mahayana Buddhism, it is considered that, from the time
he first uttered the bodhisattva vow, the bodhisattva who was to become Shakyamuni
Buddha took many hundreds of lifetimes to reach ultimate perfection.
Altogether, these incarnations of systematic purification and steady
development along the bodhisattva path spanned three cosmic aeons (a cosmic
aeon, in this case, is the time from the inception of a universe, such as our
own, until its final destruction)<a href="#_ftn21">[21]</a>.
After this extraordinary length of time, in which three universes had come and
gone, he had purified absolutely everything in his being that there was to
purify and he had attained every quality that a human being can attain. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)He achieved his final enlightenment in
the 'Highest' deva realm, called _Aknstha_, in Sanskrit, and _og.min<a href="#_ftn22">[22]</a>_ in Tibetan. From
there, he emanated into all the human realms of the thousand million cosmic
systems with which he was associated. His 'lives' in those realms, such as the
one he led in India some 2,500 years ago, were a very meaningful yet
spontaneous drama, enacted to make the dharma teachings he imparted have the
finest and most enduring effect on the world. Such a vision of the
purposefulness of the Buddha's life gives a very different image of him than
that of a simple prince, at first influenced by Brahminism, who gradually
became disillusioned with the royal life and who finally one day set out into
the unknown on a spiritual quest. His wisdom and perfection were there from the
start, as bore witness the special signs on his body and the golden aura which
shone around him as a child. The twelve major activities of his life, and their
significance, are given in the following verses. (eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>220.                 Through greatest
compassion knowing all worlds,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       having seen all worlds,
while never leaving the _dharmak̄aya_,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       through various forms,
apparitional by nature,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       the one excellently born
into the highest birth</paragraph>
            <paragraph>_Manifestation
of the twelve deeds of a supreme _ _nirmanakaya_: The great master Jamgon
Kongtrul underlines the wonder of these deeds. They are amazing, inasmuch as
the enlightened mind, without ever leaving its pure domain of formless _dharmakaya,_
manifests awe-inspiringly beautiful and meaningful forms in many worlds, such
as our own, through the deepest of compassion. These emanations are the best
thing that ever happened in our universe. The presence of the Buddha in each
world, playing out the story of the most meaningful of lives, is even more
wonderful since it takes place like an apparition, i.e. it is vividly apparent
but totally insubstantial, like a rainbow or a mirror image. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the particular case of Shakyamuni, he had already emanated as someone called 'Summit
of Goodness'<a href="#_ftn23">^2^</a> in the _deva_ paradise
called 'Realm of Great Joy' (_Tush́_ _ita_) and taught many gods there the paths
to liberation and maturity. Then he had a five-fold vision, indicating that our
world was ready for the dharma and that the many beings with whom he had established
a dharma link in previous incarnations were now born or being reborn on Earth.
The fivefold vision was:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
The _place_
was right: our world was ready for the dharma and Northern India was an
advanced society in which the dharma could become established and spread
through the civilised world.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
The _time_
was right. Shakyamuni was due to come when the maximum lifespan here was about
one hundred (lunar) years. The significance of this becomes clear in the
Kalachakra teachings which show various epochs during the life of this world,
some with beings of very subtle bodies having extraordinarily long lifespans
and others with degenerate beings, having very brief life-spans (two decades)
in times of great darkness and pollution.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
The _entourage_
of all his former disciples was gathering in India. These would be beings
capable of receiving and perpetuating his teaching.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
There
was a suitable _mother_, Queen Mahamaya, capable of bearing such an
extraordinary child.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Her _caste_
(royal caste) would be the best one for a great teacher to be born into at that
time. The previous Buddha, Kasyapa, for example, had found it more advantageous
to be born into the priestly caste, as it was more prestigious in that age.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Although
the above details form the prelude to the Buddha's life on Earth, they are not
included in the twelve deeds, properly speaking, as they did not take place in
our world. The twelve are:   </paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.         Knowing,
through this vision, that the time had come, he *_left
Tushita and came to our world_*, 'Rose Apple Land" (Jambudvipa)_.
This is the _dharmakaya'_s compassionate response to the hopes and prayers
of good beings in the world. It is the arrival of the great light which
illuminates the path to happiness and liberation, which shows the value of
virtue and which accomplishes its work with a limitless love and totally
fearless resolution.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>221.                 descends from the 'Realm
of Great Joy', </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       enters the royal womb
and is nobly born in Jambudvipa. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       Perfectly skilled in
each science and art,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.         His
teachings of dharma would later point out the limitations of worldly wealth,
status and achievement. It would be very necessary that these worldly goals be
removed from their pedestal and given their proper place by someone who had
known them to the full. The words of a social failure, a "_loser_",
 denouncing gain and fame, may just be dismissed as 'sour grapes'; as personal
rancour. His future father, King Suddhodhana, was a respected and wealthy
monarch. His mother, Mahamaya, was a beautiful queen, capable of bearing him.
Therefore, he *_entered the royal womb_*.
His mother dreamed of a white, six-tusked elephant entering her womb, as though
it were a beautiful palace. There was, it is said, celestial music heard and
many other miraculous signs took place.   </paragraph>
            <paragraph>3.         He was *_born_*
painlessly from her right side in a grove in Lumbini, presently near the
Indo-Nepalese frontier. To those present, he was seen simply to emerge on a
beam of light. When his feet touched the ground, lotus flowers of light sprung
up. He took seven steps in each of the cardinal directions and 'was heard to
declare' (i.e. everyone knew spontaneously) himself to be the Enlightened One,
Lord of the World<a href="#_ftn24">[23]</a>.
The major gods of the planet came and prostrated before him.            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>However,
of equal importance with these miracles was the fact that, to many other
people, he was later thought of as having been born 'ordinarily' as a human
being. This was also helpful for his teaching. Those people would think that an
ordinary human being like themselves, and not a celestial one, had achieved
enlightenment and that they could therefore do likewise.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>4.         As he grew up, he *_exhibited matchless prowess in every field of learning_*.
His beautiful athletic body surpassed all others in sports such as wrestling,
archery and so on. He mastered many different dialects and soon outclassed his
teachers in the various domains of academic study and artistic expression. As
we see so clearly these days, people can value highly--perhaps
overvalue--scientific understanding, artistic skill or physical prowess. Society
adores it geniuses, its great artists and its sports heroes. In order for the
Buddha's teaching to show the transience and limitations of such worldly
prowess, compared with timeless understanding of mind and of existence itself,
it was indeed helpful that he had himself excelled in each of them more than
anyone of his day. It is said that his fame as an athlete and scholar spread
far beyond his own kingdom. He was a living legend long before his
enlightenment: the wisest, most gifted youth that humankind had ever seen.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>222                  Delighting in his royal
consorts' company, then renouncing,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       practising the path of
hardship and difficulty,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       going to the place
called 'Enlightenment's Very Heart',</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       he vanquishes the hosts
of evil,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>5.          
In order to fulfil his duty to his parents and provide an heir to the throne
(he was their only child), he *_married and
enjoyed the company of his royal consorts_*. The quest for a happy
marriage, sexual satisfaction, parenthood and companionship is something which
dominates people and societies everywhere. Given the strength of human beings'
illusions, their hopes and their biological drives, it would not be easy, later
on, for the Buddha to point out the futility of too much time and energy spent
in pursuing these things and  high price. There would be more chance of his
audience heeding someone who, as was his case, had married and satisfied three
of the most beautiful brides in the land and who had enjoyed the company of the
many young consorts in his royal harem, as was custom for royalty of that
culture. Of these, the beautiful Yasodhara, a princess in her own right, was
his main bride and the mother to his only official child, Rahula.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>6.         Having established his excellence in all these
domains in the eyes of the world and fulfilled his duty to his parents by
providing an heir, at the age of twenty-nine he *_renounced
worldliness_*. The details of his fourfold vision of ageing,
sickness, death and a renunciate, and the story of the feast on his last day at
the palace, when Rahula was born, are poignant indeed. The common version of
the renunciation is that he had his servant, whom he had sworn to secrecy,
bring him his horse, Katanka, late that same evening. Cutting off his long,
jewel-adorned, hair--the symbol of his royalty--with his own sword, he rode off
into the jungle to follow the religious life. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
Mahayana version is that the Buddhas of the past, present and future emanated a
crystal stupa, which gave him the vows of monastic ordination, his robes and
hair-cutting, and that he set off on the eternal way of the monk. To teach
others renunciation, he had himself to show the courage and ability to leave
behind all the wonders and joys of his temporal life, in order to seek ageless
wisdom.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>7.         It would be necessary for him to teach
effectively not only the inadequacies of worldly life but also those of
self-mortification. Who could do this better than one who had been the most
rigid of ascetics? For six years, much of it spent in the company of five other
ascetics, *_he practised meditation and
asceticism_*. He trained under the finest meditation teachers of
his day, but soon exhausted what they had to teach him. He then devoted himself
to austerities. He ate less than, endured the burning sun more than and practised
hardships more stringently than anyone had ever done. Much of this occurred in
the area of the river Neranjara. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Often,
he meditated for many days, without eating or moving, beneath the tall trees on
its banks, with a rock for a cushion. At the end, he was such a skeletal bag of
bones that his spine could be seen protruding through the skin of his abdomen.
His brilliant aura and special marks had disappeared. This severe self-denial
would not only serve as a proper basis for dismissing asceticism as the main
way to truth, but would also demonstrate his own mastery of diligence and show
his teaching to be not just an intellectual conclusion but the fruit of
powerful personal experience.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>His
ascetic period ended with him receiving the offering of a special bowl of rice
gruel. Someone who had made a deep commitment to Shakyamuni, in a previous life
when he was a bodhisattva, was reborn as a young milkmaid. She fed ten of her
best cows with the milk of a hundred cows. Then she milked the ten cows and fed
that milk to the best cow of all. Its milk she mixed with honey and the finest
rice. Taking this in a golden bowl, she approached Shakyamuni and offered it to
him. As he drank it, his special marks and halo returned in an instant and he
cast the bowl into the river saying, "If I am to find enlightenment, may this
bowl float upstream." It did.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>8.         He then *_set
out for Vajrasana_*, the place we now call Bodh Gaya. It is said
to be the spiritual 'centre of gravity' of this world and the place where each
of the 1,002 Buddhas will manifest enlightenment. On the way there, he met
another person with a special dharma connection: a young man who offered him a
bundle of _kusha_ grass as a meditation cushion. Arriving beneath the
great tree, a _ficus religiosus_, he arranged the grass and sat in
meditation.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>9.         From an absolute point of view, Shakyamuni was
already completely purified and realised. He had already become the perfection
of _dharmakaya_. But to instil, on a relative level, an understanding of
the need to attain total virtue and wisdom, he needed to show attainment of
this utter purity. Having taken up his seat under the bodhi tree, he entered
into the absorption in _dharmakaya_ known as the 'vajra-like samadhi'.
With his manifestation of enlightenment imminent, the hosts of negative
energies and beings of this world came to distract him. They produced phantasms
of sensuality, hordes of frightening demon armies and other illusions, in a
vain attempt to hinder his achievement. By his remaining unperturbed in the
natural loving compassion and voidness of the vajra-like samadhi, the *_hosts of negative forces (mara) were defeated_*.
The weapons they threw turned into flowers, adorning the Buddha's presence. It
is said, in certain scriptures, that these evil entities were unable to affect
India for many centuries following this: it seemed to them as though it were
protected by a great wall of impenetrable fire. Thus the golden age of
enlightened teachings could establish itself. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
outer 'evil forces' are the external mirror image of the internal ones. One
could also consider the Buddha's total enlightenment as being the final
elimination of every trace of the 'four evils' (four _mara_): those of
death, the defilements, the aggregates and pride.       </paragraph>
            <paragraph>223.                 Then, perfect enlightenment,
the turning of the wheel of dharma</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       and passing into supreme
nirvana. In all these places, so impure,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       the _nirmanakaya_
shows these deeds as long as worlds endure. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>10.       At
dawn the next morning, the day of the full moon in the Vaishakha month, he *_manifested total enlightenment_*. He was
thirty-five. After three cosmic aeons of association with this world, he at
last appeared in it as a fully purified being, a flawless expression of the
absolute truth and the presence of omniscience. Thus he became a peerless guide
for all living beings for thousands of years to come.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>11.       He did not start teaching the buddhadharma
immediately but remained in silence for some weeks, in order to show the
profundity of what he had realised and to give the _deva_ of the planet
the chance to gather virtue by requesting him to teach. They eventually came to
him, prostrated and supplicated him to *_turn
the wheel of universal truth_* for the welfare of beings on Earth.
Something similar to this was happening in all the other planets that fell
within the scope of his activity. In the deer forests near Benares and other
places, he taught the Four Truths and 84,000 dharmas common to all Buddhism. At
the Vulture Peak and other lesser-known places, he taught the special path of Mahayana.
To King Indrabhuti and others, he taught the secret teachings of vajrayana.
Over a forty-five year period, and through the three turnings of the wheel of
dharma, he transmitted all that needed to be known: the profound path to peace
and everlasting happiness.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>12.       Throughout all this time, the Buddha had been an
expression of _dharmakaya_, which is beyond any coming or going. Yet, in
order to instil diligence and a sense of urgency in his disciples, and in order
to dispel the wrong notions of his having eternal, concrete divinity or the
wrong notions of nihilism, he *_passed into
parinirvana_*. If even the physical presence of buddha must seem
to die, how much more so the likes of ordinary beings! His passing also
highlighted the need for all Buddhists to assume personal responsibility for
their own welfare, and not to be over-dependent upon the spiritual radiance of
others.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Buddha
Shakyamuni's life, chosen here to exemplify the meaning of the term 'supreme
nirmanakaya', is not unique. The twelve deeds are typical of the activity of
such supreme nirmanakaya throughout the universe. Whenever worlds are ready to
receive them, those already enlightened in sublime spheres demonstrate these
twelve deeds, which establish the universal truths of dharma in the very best
and most lasting way. It is the supreme dialogue between truth and ignorance,
between the pure and the impure, that will continue for as long as worlds
exist.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>224.                 Knowing the means (through
such terms as </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       'impermanence',
'suffering', 'no-self' and 'peace'), </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       the nirm̄anak̄aya instils
weariness with the world </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       in beings of the three
dimensions, thus causing them </paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       to apply themselves to
the transcendence of suffering. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>_                       _</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*The
function of these manifestations:* This and the following two verses highlight the main
functions of the _nirm̄anak̄aya_:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·         
To lead
beings into, and then along, the path of truth. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·         
To lead
experienced Hinayana Buddhists into the Mahayana path when they are ready.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·         
To
predict the future enlightenment of bodhisattvas.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Buddhas
help beings to enter the path to enlightenment by teaching them the relative
truths, since they would be unable to grasp absolute truth at an early stage.
Using ideas and terminology which make sense to such beings, Buddhas point out
the _impermanence_ of all created things. They show that every situation
tainted by emotional defilement must involve some _suffering_.
Furthermore, they can start to introduce the truth of voidness by explaining
the _absence of self-entity_ within either beings or things, and by
describing how illusions of personality dictate the way beings' lives are led.
As they start to recognise the vivid relevance of these ideas, new Buddhists
awaken to the truth of the human condition. This leads to dissatisfaction with
samsara and a genuine longing for inner peace and for lasting, spiritual
happiness, rather than an impermanent, worldly one. Buddhas then guide them to
skill and maturity in the practice of meditation, of wholesome conduct and of
wisdom.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>225.                 To those excellently
established on the path of peace,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       who believe that they
have already attained nirvana,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       it teaches the thatness
of all phenomena,</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       in the 'White Lotus' and
other (sutra).</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Those
who have liberated themselves forever from worldliness and worldly rebirth, by
following the Hinayana path, attain the state of the arhat<a href="#_ftn25">[24]</a>. Although this is nirvana,
in its strict sense of transcendence of suffering, it is not _the_ Nirvana
of the Buddha. It is, nevertheless, a wonderful achievement. At a certain
point, arhats will have a profound experience of the Buddha's body, speech and
mind. Through hearing such teachings as those of the Lotus Sutra, they are
guided into the way of Mahayana. This will take them to the enlightenment of a
Perfect Buddha.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>226.                 Through this, they turn
away from their former belief</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       and are inspired to
properly adopt wisdom and skilful means.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       It brings them to
maturity within the highest yana</paragraph>
            <paragraph>                       and predicts their
enlightenment supreme.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These
arhats-become-bodhisattvas will need--as do all bodhisattvas--to develop the two
qualities of wisdom and compassion in perfect harmony:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>Deep
     wisdom (_prajna_) will take them beyond the voidness of ego to
     recognition of the voidness of all things, as taught in the _prajnaparamita_.
     This liberates them definitively from even the subtlest aspects of samsara.
     </li>
               <li>Limitless,
     great compassion, referred to here as 'skilful means', relates to the
     first five of the six paramita. It is limitless in its scope and great by
     nature. Such compassion will impress upon them the need to care for all
     beings, not only for the beings' sake but also for the attainment of
     enlightenment. This will free them from attachment both to their own
     welfare and to the limited absorptions of concentration meditation. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>The combining of wisdom and compassion
will lead arhats to the non-abiding Nirvana of the Buddhas.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One
very special task of the form kaya is to predict the future enlightenment of
bodhisattvas. This usually happens to bodhisattvas of the three 'extremely
pure' levels, i.e. the eighth, ninth and tenth. They experience the Buddha
declaring publicly, </paragraph>
            <paragraph>"Later, in such and such an age, you
will become the Buddha known as ...., whose main disciples will be ... Your
teachings will endure for ... length of time and your buddhafield will be known
as ...."</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </chapter>
</book>