<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:book="http://www.leanne.northrop.org/2010/Book">
   <chapter index="3" title="The Second Truth: the Causes of Suffering"
            pagetitle="Module 3"
            tocentry="The Second Truth: the Causes of Suffering">
      <section index="1" title="" pagetitle="" tocentry=""/>
      <section index="2" title="Reflections on Causality in&#xA;General"
               pagetitle="Reflections on Causality in&#xA;General"
               tocentry="Reflections on Causality in&#xA;General">
         <subsection title="Reflections on Causality in\General"
                     pagetitle="Reflections on Causality in\General"
                     tocentry="Reflections on Causality in\General">
            <image width="470"/>
            <paragraph>We
shall explore this in the following seven ways:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>By
     considering causality in general.</li>
               <li>By
     working backwards, from effects to causes, to establish an overview.</li>
               <li>By
     examining karma, and in particular non-virtuous karma, the immediate cause
     of suffering.</li>
               <li>By
     examining the cause of karma: the afflictions.</li>
               <li>By
     examining the cause of the afflictions: primarily notions of ego but also dualistic
     delusions of self and other.</li>
               <li>By
     examining the cause of dualistic delusions: ignorance of the true nature.</li>
               <li>By
     investigating interdependence and in particular _outer_
     interdependent origination in its twelve classical links and _inner_
     interdependence through the six elements.</li>
            </list>
            <image width="452"/>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Causality" pagetitle="Causality" tocentry="Causality">
            <img width="452" src="module3_files/image003.png"/>
            <paragraph>Why
do things happen? Is there some hidden programming, some master-plan, behind
life? Is there some point to it all? In particular, why do we suffer? These
questions have intrigued both everyday humans and philosophers of East and West
for thousands of years. We can witness short-term cause-and-effect on a
material level, such as observing a seedling growing into a flower or CO~2~
emissions changing the Earth's climate. We see them on a psychological level
when a person's behaviour is affected by life experience. Other than obvious
cause-and-effect, is there some even greater logic behind everything: a
longer-term causality? Some common ways of answering have been:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
No, things
just happen, biologically and otherwise, with no particular "greater" cause,
such as God or karma. A thorn is sharp, water is wet. The kidneys produce urine
and a brain produces thoughts and emotions. It's simply like that and any
attempt to attribute meaning to a meaningless universe is merely human vanity
and an attempt to deny mortality and our relative insignificance. Suffering
simply happens.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Or, some
say it is, as above, inherently accidental, with no deep meaning or purpose,
but that as intelligent humans we can give it meaning. Suffering happens and
this gives the opportunity for us to form a noble and useful relationship to
it, in ourselves and in others<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>.
</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Or, some
consider the whole universe, including its sentient beings, is the creation of,
and the play of, immortal beings: gods. The gods have their purpose, beyond our
grasp; a mystery. Their will and power is all-determining. If we suffer, it is
their will and perhaps their displeasure with us. Or their way of testing us. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Or, some
see it as above but with just a single creator god.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Or, without
god or gods, some see "life" as a sort of cosmic 'test'. We will be reborn
again and again into similar situations until we find the correct response.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
And so
on...</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
list could become endless and would lead us into all the details of the great
faiths and philosophies with their fine differences of opinion. Intellectualism
aside, pinpointing the cause of things--and especially of suffering--is a major
issue in all human life. To put it simply, when things get tough, who or what
do we blame? Into what framework falls our reaction?</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
Buddha denied any divine and purposeful creation of the universe and taught
extensively that things happen because of other things, in a continuously
changing process of interdependence. Part of that overall process is for one
conscious existence to give rise to another one, and another, in a series of
reincarnations where what occurs in one life is the result of what happened in
the previous. And what someone does in the present life is determining how the
future one will be. However, the Buddha's teaching--dharma--is not a simple
determinism, even though some people describe it as such<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>. This is because any idea of
a material universe in Buddhism is not purely a mechanistic one but one
tempered by the all-important description of that universe as being _like a
dream or a conjuration_. In other words, "+the+ universe" is a word a
human gives to "my universe"--the narrow slice of everything that his or her
human senses and intelligence enable that person to perceive. Actual reality is
something far more. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
Buddha's teachings on cause-and-effect provide us with a good explanation for
the way things seem to be happening in this relative and highly-subjective
dream of life. They deal with the happenings in the material world around us
and in the mind, following their evolution from day to day and from life to
life. At the same time, the Buddha's other teachings, on absolute truth, show
clearly that nothing ever produced anything. Just as a horse in a dream never
needed to have been sired by a father stallion and borne by a mother mare, so
things in the apparent universe are not all they seem to be! </paragraph>
            <paragraph>We
find a parallel to this in modern physics, where causality is still a practical
and common-sense way of understand the mechanisms of the world in which we
live. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Acid
+ alkali gives salt + water. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>What
goes up must fall down, in a gravity field.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>A
poppy seed gives rise to a poppy flower. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Yet,
causality theory disappears totally on a level of the chaotic behaviour of the
tiniest sub-atomic particles. Nevertheless, the new understanding of quantum
physics doesn't stop the seeds we plant in the garden from growing into
vegetables nor does it stop the kettle from boiling when we plug it in. Likewise,
the semblance of order on our level of perception (gardens, kettles) does not
prevent us from believing in utter chaos on a finer level.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
Buddhists, we have the very practical application of dharma, helping us to sort
out our daily lives and our karma, in terms of predictable cause and effect. We
also have the luxury of a fine philosophical analysis to help us penetrate the
absolute truth of things. This is an extraordinarily helpful blend!</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Before
we do enter into the details of the causes of suffering, here are a few useful
points which often come up, explained by Khenchen Thrangu Rinpoche and the
Goshir Gyaltsabpa:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>*Not
     everything that happens is a result of past karma*. If someone catches a
     cold, or meets an unknown person today, is does not necessarily mean that
     there is a specific cause for that somewhere in a past life. It is not
     always "my karma for this to happen".</li>
               <li>*There
     is no "learning purpose" conspiracy behind everything*. Although almost
     anything can give us the _opportunity_ to learn something or
     other--and it can become our teacher, our guru--there is not some divine
     plot where the guru  or the Buddha is constantly and _intentionally_
     putting each and every thing in our path as a specific test with a
     specific significance at that time.  </li>
               <li>*Not
     everything we do creates karma*. Six factors need to be reunited
     for karma to be established.</li>
               <li>*On
     a relative level, we definitely have choice*, and making the right choices is
     an important point of Buddhist ethics and practice. Thus, we are not
     fatalists.</li>
               <li>At
     a certain--and wonderful--point in the practice, *there may come a time
     when there will be no choice*. This is not fatalism either, as the lack
     of choice results from previous choices: for instance, an astronaut may
     have made hundreds of choices which ended up in him or her being launched
     in the space capsule. Once it is up in orbit: no choice, no turning back!</li>
               <li>*Karma
     actually creates the circumstances* we generally call suffering *but
     not suffering itself*. Whether one actually suffers or not depends upon
     the way the person relates to those circumstances. Wealth can be a torture
     for some and sickness can be deeply liberating.  </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>These
and other points will be explained in this module.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="3" title="The Overview of the Causes of&#xA;Suffering"
               pagetitle="The Overview of the Causes of&#xA;Suffering"
               tocentry="The Overview of the Causes of&#xA;Suffering">
         <subsection title="The Overview of the Causes of\Suffering"
                     pagetitle="The Overview of the Causes of\Suffering"
                     tocentry="The Overview of the Causes of\Suffering">
            <img width="452" src="module3_files/image004.png"/>
            <paragraph>The
following is the master template for this module. Please learn it by heart.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*Ignorance* of the true nature of things _causes_(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*Dualistic thought* projecting an experiencer--"I"--and
something experienced--"other", _causing_(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*Afflictions* of "I"-centred passion,
anger, pride etc. _causing_(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*Action* (karma) to get what is desired or avoid
what is disliked etc. _causing_(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*Rebirth *in "samsara" with its inevitable
suffering.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This
process will be studied in more detail and sophistication through the _twelve
links of interdependence_, which can be applied over a series of lives, over
two lives, within one life or in the very moment.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>At
this point, it is probably helpful to clarify the terms _tainted_ and _untainted_.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Tainted
action* can
be positive or negative, good or bad, virtuous or non-virtuous, helpful or
harmful (whichever terms you prefer). It is _tainted_ because it results
in samsara. The virtuous actions create the pleasant things of samsara--health,
wealth, friendship, harmony--and the non-virtuous ones create the unpleasant
things--illness, poverty, enmity, disharmony etc. The "taint" is the
presence of the illusion of self when the action is performed. It has already
sown the seed of the "someone", in the future, who will experience the
consequence.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*Untainted
action* is
performed without the driving thought of "I". It happens in a state
known as "beyond triplicity", where three things--the notion of
subject, object and interaction--are transcended or absent. Untainted action is
the way out of samsara, to nirvana. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>To
describe the above master template in a few more words, before we enter into
the details:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
mahayana view of the real truth, of everything, of our own being, of mind, is
the _awakened mind_ or _buddha mind_. It is pure, eternal, perfect,
unchanging and filled with wisdom, loving kindness and power to help beings.
This can be interpreted in many ways, but let's leave it like that for now. The
Hinayana view is that it is total peace and purity. Buddha mind or simply
peace: that is the true _identity_. Not to _be _that, and hence not
to know that, is what is meant by _ignorance_. This ignorance is the heart
of the problem. Due to it, the natural feeling of inner identity becomes
mistaken for a personal self and once there is that feeling of a self--a
perceiver, a subject--there will instantaneously be a perception of
"other"--something or someone perceived, an object. For most people,
this happens moment after moment, every moment, before even thoughts can put it
into words. This instant-by-instant fractioning of awareness into two halves is
called _duality_ or _dualistic perception_ and the way our thoughts
rationalise it is called _dualistic thinking_. The latter is the constantly-updated
story that the chatter of the mind is recounting: a tale of oneself and other
people and the world. This has been going on since time immemorial.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Once
the stories about oneself, the people in one's life and the world around one
have become solid realities in the mind, through being rehearsed and repeated
over and over again, all sorts of interactions naturally follow. If the inner
story says _I love Tibetans_ then when one meets Tibetans one feels good
and wants more, planning trips East and so on. When the inner story says _wasps
are horrible and dangerous_, someone will not think twice about destroying
them, even if they have caused no personal harm. The two main polarities of
this stage of the story are attraction and rejection. The attractive and
repulsive forces motivate our lives, since much of our time and effort goes
into trying to get what we want and to avoid what we don't like. When these
motive-forces have the ego-delusion at their heart, they are called _klesha_,
in Sanskrit, meaning _affliction, defilement, canker, poisons _etc.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Because
of the klesha, one will act. Some actions bring happiness to their doer, in the
long term (usually next life) while others bring suffering. The Sanskrit for _action_
is _karma_. Unlike the English understanding of the word _action_,
which finishes once the initial or immediate action has terminated, the word _karma_
includes both immediate and long-term consequences. This is a very interesting
way of looking at actions: it is like a gardener who plants a seedling but who
can already see the future mighty tree in his mind. "Planting a poppy
seed", for Westerners, is an action which finishes once the earth has been
tamped around the seed and it has been watered. In Buddhist thought
"planting a poppy seed" includes everything up to and including the
red flower that appears months later. It is for this reason that the texts
speak of _karma, cause +and+ effect_. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Be
it virtuous or non-virtuous, tainted karma generates samsara. With samsara comes
suffering, as we saw in the previous module.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering"
                     pagetitle="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering"
                     tocentry="A classical presentation of the Truth of the Causes of Suffering">
            <paragraph>In
more technical presentations of the Four Truths, four main aspects are
underlined for each truth<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>.
For this Second Truth, the four are:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*1.  
Cause      2.   Universal origination      3.   Total production      4.  
Condition*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Cause_* is a key term signifying
that suffering does not just happen but that it is caused, by actions (_karma_),
afflictions (_klesha_) and ignorance. The term cause--as opposed to the
term _condition(s)_, which occurs later, refers to a prime cause. This
means something that has the ability to give rise to a certain result. For
instance, a poppy seed has the genetic coding which produces a poppy flower.
Nothing else in the universe possesses that same coding and potential. A human
being's eye colour, blood type etc. are already pre-coded, uniquely, in the
genes of the embryo. With _prime causes_, we are considering the power of
each action to imprint the mind and thereby later cause a certain type of
experience to manifest.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Universal
origination_*
signifies the power to give rise to an entire reality, including the person and
world that the person experiences. Thus we humans are born with a similar lot,
experiencing other humans and a typically-human world. This world is the
production of our group karma: group in the sense of family, society, nation
etc. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Total
production_*
refers to a more personal aspect within this generality of being humans.
Although we are all humans, no two people are the same. The total production of
one human being occurs through that person's actions and mind habits generated
by the past. While we are somehow connected and trigger each other's personal
karma in our shared realities, we are totally unconnected with other realities.
 </paragraph>
            <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*_Condition,_* as opposed to _cause_
(above) refers to general conditions which are necessary for something to
happen. The poppy seed needs light, heat and moisture for its genetic coding to
make a flower. The embryo needs nourishment to grow. This fourth point
highlights the fact that once humans (or other beings) exist in their
particular realities, with their individual karma and habits, there is already
the condition for more karma to be generated, thereby perpetuating the cycle of
suffering.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These
four names came about because the Buddha, when explaining the source of samsara's
painful shortcomings, explained, </paragraph>
            <paragraph>   "It
has four hallmarks:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>Karma
     and affliction create the painful shortcomings of samsara. Therefore, in
     the manner of a seed, it is the cause.</li>
               <li>The
     three realms and the continua of the five realms<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> arise in
     full from it so, in the manner of a harvest arising, it is origination.</li>
               <li>Strong
     karma and affliction produce immediate retribution. Therefore, through
     inter-relationship, it is highest production.</li>
               <li>Because
     the unsatisfactory skandhas in the places of the three realms are actually
     produced from karma and affliction, it assists the production of the
     outcome like water and fertilizer, so it is the condition."<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a>
               </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>We
will not use this classical and rather technical exposition as the basis for
this module but rather concentrate on the way samsara's causes have been
explained many times over the years by our lineage masters at Samye Ling.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="4" title="Karma: The Cause of Samsara"
               pagetitle="Karma: The Cause of Samsara"
               tocentry="Karma: The Cause of Samsara">
         <subsection title="Karma: The Cause of Samsara" pagetitle="Karma: The Cause of Samsara"
                     tocentry="Karma: The Cause of Samsara">
            <img width="452" src="module3_files/image005.png"/>
            <paragraph>We
will now start working back from the Six Realms of suffering, studied last
month, to the immediate causes of those sufferings; previous karma, meaning
previous actions. Although the variety of actions a being can perform is
infinite, they are categorised into three areas--physical, verbal and mental--and
these in turn have their sub-categories, giving us a tenfold guide to non-virtuous
and virtuous action that is very famous in Buddhism. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
order in which we consider these is important. First things first: the priority
for the Buddha wasalways to help us to stop harming others
(and ourselves in the process, through the long-term play of karma). Although
doing positive, wholesome things is important, our priority too should be to reduce
as much and as urgently as is possible actions that cause harm.  In order to do
that, we first need to understand what "harm" means. Thus, our study
of action starts by considering the famous Ten Non-Virtuous Actions. Then we
will consider virtuous karma and thirdly the special karma of meditation, known
as Immobility Karma.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The\Ten Non-Virtuous Actions" pagetitle="The\Ten Non-Virtuous Actions"
                     tocentry="The\Ten Non-Virtuous Actions">
            <table style="background:#CCFFFF;border-collapse:collapse" class="MsoNormalTable">
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <td>Physical Verbal Mental</td>
                     <td>To kill To steal To commit sexual misconduct To lie To create division and enmity To speak woundingly  To speak uselessly Malevolence Avarice Aberrant belief</td>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table>
            <paragraph>Although
each of the above actions will have immediate consequences, on the doer and on
the done-to, here we are considering primarily the aspect that most people
ignore: the long-term effect on the doer. The following is a tremendously
important point, highlighted again and again by our teachers:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Nobody wants to suffer,
everyone wants happiness. The world is striving vigorously for happiness yet
happiness is rare and suffering is widespread. Something is very wrong!
Something is really not working. What is wrong is that we do not understand the
long-term causes of happiness and of suffering and, in such ignorance, efforts
for short-term happiness often become the very causes that trigger needless
suffering in the long-term future.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>An
example to illustrate the above would be that of someone who kills animals for
sport. The thrill of hitting the target and taking a pheasant home to put in
the freezer is an immediate pleasure but could the killer only but perceive the
physical sickness, pain, short life etc. that will result from that action in
the next life, s/he would probably never fire the shot in the first place. Even
then, human nature can be perversely unintelligent and sometimes even opts for
the short-term pleasure despite clear knowledge of the long-term drawbacks.
Smoking is one example. Elected politicians' reluctance to implement obvious
long-term solutions is perhaps another. Dharma is long-term work and part of
the training is a new learning, finding joy in letting go of instant pleasure,
sometimes accepting hardship, in the knowledge that one is working for
long-term sanity<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a>.
 </paragraph>
            <paragraph>We
will consider the long-term consequences of actions in three areas:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>_Full
     maturation_,
     meaning a type of rebirth in the six realms. Whether the
     worst-case-scenario happens or not, or how many times it happens, depends
     upon the frequency and the power of the action (see below).</li>
               <li>_Results
     resembling their causes_, relating to the quality of life within that
     rebirth.</li>
               <li>_Environmental
     effects_
     experienced during the future birth.</li>
            </list>
            <subsubsection title="1.   Killing" pagetitle="1.   Killing" tocentry="1.   Killing">
               <paragraph>(eh)This means intentionally bringing the
life of another sentient being to an end. Harming life, without necessarily
killing a being, is a sub-category of this non-virtue. The motive force behind
killing can be _desire_--for meat or animal products, for the thrill of
hunting, for financial gain or to protect one's goods and loved ones. It could
be through _anger and aversion_--fighting enemies, eliminating competitors,
vengeance and the like. It could be through _ignorance_, such as killing
animals to make sacrificial offerings.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation of
killing
could be rebirth as a hell-being. The result corresponding to the cause is that
even if one is reborn human, one will have a short life and many sicknesses.
The environmental influence is to be reborn in an ill-fated and unattractive
land.(eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="2.   Stealing" pagetitle="2.   Stealing" tocentry="2.   Stealing">
               <paragraph>(eh)The actual wording of this is _taking
what is not given_. The motive force behind stealing is usually desire,
although it could be through malevolence or confusion. There are three main
types of stealing: robbery with violence, burglary and other
"stealth" thefts and, thirdly, fraudulence.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation could be rebirth as
a deprived spirit. The result resembling the cause is that even if one is
reborn human, one will live in poverty or in dissatisfaction. The environmental
consequence is to be reborn in a place of much frost and hail. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="3.   Sexual\Misconduct" pagetitle="3.   Sexual\Misconduct"
                           tocentry="3.   Sexual\Misconduct">
               <paragraph>    
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Comment:* Some people question vigorously some
aspects of what follows, especially traditional teaching concerning oral or
anal sex. Our lamas are often at a loss to answer and would be only too happy
if the Buddha would come back to guide us in these modern times. One must
remember also that most lamas are monastics, coming from a reserved culture.
Many are uncomfortable speaking publicly about these things and often lack
personal or cultural experience of the questions asked.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)Were these karma teachings old social
conventions, from India and Tibet, irrelevant today? Were they, on the contrary,
in whole or in part, based on an understanding of natural energies and the
karma that certain sexual activities generate and, if so, have our societies
something to learn, even if it challenges modern assumptions? (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The very fact of the strength of
people's reaction to this topic is proof in itself of the powerful emotions and
karma at play with sexuality and hence of the importance of getting it right.
All we can do here is to present the traditional advice and leave each person
to draw his or her own conclusions.   (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)"Misconduct" here is defined by two
sorts of factor: natural ones (that apply universally) and ones related to
social convention (and hence varying from culture to culture). The _natural
ones_ arise because of the way the human mind-body mechanisms function,
because of the energies around certain places and holy people, through the
power of certain times in the calendar and so forth. As always, with teachings
on karma, the Buddha is not setting down an arbitrary ethic but simply pointing
out what happens, "If one does this now, later this will occur..." (regardless
of whether one would wish it to be that way or not). (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)    The _social conventions_ are
concerned with mental suffering created by personal conditioning or social
stigma. The impact of having sex with someone who already has a partner will be
very different in a totally-promiscuous society from in a one-partner-for-life
society. The underlying Buddhist guideline, even in our complex modern world of
overlapping values, is not to cause suffering on account of selfish passion. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)    There is no idea of marriage as
something sacred in Buddhism, as it is in the Abrahamic<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a> religions. Nevertheless,
commitment of couples is honoured as a way of reducing selfish passion, of
learning to be satisfied with what one has and as being one way of creating
social harmony. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)There are three areas
of preclusion: (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)1.     Through
genetic proximity: *incest<a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a>*.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)2.     Through *commitment
to another*. This concerns sex with someone already married or committed
exclusively to another person.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)3.     Through *dharma
considerations*. This third covers all situations of sexual relationship--albeit
with a person not in the above two categories-- which are considered
inappropriate by Buddhist convention. It speaks of five areas of inadmissible
intercourse:(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)1.     _Inappropriate
organs_,
meaning oral or anal intercourse. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)2.     An _inappropriate
place_ is in the proximity of a holy being, temple, stupa or a large
gathering. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)3.     _Inappropriate
times_
are those when lay precepts are being observed, during pregnancy, while the
mother is breastfeeding or during daylight hours. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)4.     An _inappropriate
degree_ is five or more times consecutively. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)5.     _Inappropriate
forms_
of intercourse means principally rape but it also includes anal or oral
intercourse with a person of the same sex or a hermaphrodite.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation of sexual misconduct
could be rebirth as a deprived spirit. The result resembling the cause is that
even if one is reborn human, one's partner will become like a hateful enemy. The
environmental influence is to be reborn in a very dusty, desert land. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="4.   Lying" pagetitle="4.   Lying" tocentry="4.   Lying">
               <paragraph>(eh)Given the elusive and sublime nature of
real truth, we cannot define this as "not telling the truth". Its scope falls
within what one believes to be true or untrue and it means knowingly lying for
selfish interest. Three main areas are defined: wrecking lies, big lies and
trivial lies. The first are lies about dharma accomplishment, intended to
mislead followers or potential followers. To pretend or imply that one has
achievements that one does not have is one of the four root downfalls for monks
or nuns, as well as for dharma teachers. It is karmically very heavy. Big lies
are those told with an intention to deceive in order to gain personal benefit
or to benefit kith and kin or to bring harm on others. Trivial lies are a bad
habit of speech.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation of lying could be
to be reborn an animal, although the wrecking lies can cause false gurus to
endure far worse, terrible karmic consequences, depending upon the damage they
cause. The result resembling the cause is that even if one is reborn human one
will be denigrated by others, who will not believe one's words or take them
seriously. The third type of result is not environmental, in this case, but
that of having bad breath.(eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="5.   Divisive\Speech  " pagetitle="5.   Divisive\Speech  "
                           tocentry="5.   Divisive\Speech  ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This mainly involves saying things
which cause friends, or people in harmony, to separate or to have bad feelings
for each other. This can be done in three ways: by directly and vehemently
denigrating people, by underhand insinuation or via third parties (whereas the
first two are in the direct presence of the people concerned).(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation of this could be
rebirth in the hell-realms. The corresponding result is that even if one is
reborn human one will be separated from friends and loved ones. The
environmental result is to have to live in a place where the landscape is
dangerously erratic.  (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="6.   Wounding\Speech   " pagetitle="6.   Wounding\Speech   "
                           tocentry="6.   Wounding\Speech   ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This is of three
types: direct, insinuated or via third parties. The first is to tell someone
openly of their faults and weaknesses. The second means to say hurtful things,
in a half-disguised manner mingled with jest, relevant to someone present. The
third is to gossip about someone's faults or weaknesses to their friends and
third parties.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation
could be rebirth in hell. The corresponding result is that, even if one is
reborn a human, the sounds and words that one hears will be disturbing. The environmental
influence is to be reborn in a hot and arid place where there is much evil. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="7.   Useless\Speech  " pagetitle="7.   Useless\Speech  "
                           tocentry="7.   Useless\Speech  ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This is of three
types: deluded useless speech, useless worldly chatter and true yet useless
speech. The first concerns the formulas and recitations of deluded belief
systems<a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a>.
The second concerns silly talk: jokes and the like. The third concerns attempts
to explain dharma to those lacking respect or an appropriate frame of mind.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation
could be rebirth as an animal. The corresponding result is that, even should
one be reborn human, one's words will carry no weight. The resulting influence
is to be reborn in a place where the seasons are completely erratic. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="8.   Avidity (one could equally say\cupidity or greed)  "
                           pagetitle="8.   Avidity (one could equally say\cupidity or greed)  "
                           tocentry="8.   Avidity (one could equally say\cupidity or greed)  ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This is of three
types: avarice concerning one's own things, other people's things and those
things which belongs to neither. The first is a grasping attachment to one's
own family status, physical appearance, qualities, wealth and possessions
thinking, _There is no one quite like me, Mine is the best_ etc. The
second is to covet the good things others possess, thinking _If only this
were mine_. The third involves attachment to things which belong neither to
oneself or to others, such as the precious substances buried in the earth and
so forth, thinking, _If only I could have that_.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation
could be rebirth as a deprived spirit. The corresponding result is that even if
one is reborn human avarice will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence
is to be born in a place where the quality of food is poor. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="9.   Malevolence   " pagetitle="9.   Malevolence   "
                           tocentry="9.   Malevolence   ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This is of three
types: due to hatred, jealousy or resent. The first is to contemplate killing
another because of hatred, as happens in times of war. The second, due to
competition and the like, is to think about killing or harming another through
fear of being surpassed. The third, due to long- standing resent, is to
contemplate killing or hurting someone who has previously wronged one.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation
could be rebirth in hell. The corresponding result is that even if one is
reborn human, hatred will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence is to be
reborn in a place where the food is bitter and coarse. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="10.   Aberrant\Belief    " pagetitle="10.   Aberrant\Belief    "
                           tocentry="10.   Aberrant\Belief    ">
               <paragraph>(eh)This is of three
types: aberrant beliefs about actions and their consequences, about the
truth(s) and about the precious refuges. The first of these means not believing
that virtuous or harmful actions produce their respective consequences--happiness
and suffering. The second is to consider that liberation will not be achieved
by the proper spiritual practices. This is expressed technically as, "To
believe the truth of cessation<a href="#_ftn10">[10]</a>
will not be obtained by one who practises the truth of the path<a href="#_ftn11">[11]</a>". The third is to deprecate
the three precious refuges<a href="#_ftn12">[12]</a>,
believing them to be untrue.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)The full maturation could be rebirth an
animal. The corresponding result is that even if reborn human, stupidity and
confusion will dominate one's mind. The resulting influence is to be reborn in
a place without harvests. (eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="A Closer Look at Full Maturation"
                     pagetitle="A Closer Look at Full Maturation"
                     tocentry="A Closer Look at Full Maturation">
            <paragraph>Three kinds can be distinguished according to the affliction
present, the frequency of action or the person acted upon:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1.     If the
actions were done through anger or hatred, one is more likely to be reborn in
hell. If they were done through passion or attachment, one is more likely to be
reborn as a deprived spirit. If they were done through stupidity and confusion
one is more likely to be reborn as an animal. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>2.     Innumerable
non-virtuous acts lead to rebirth in hell. A great deal of non-virtuous acts
lead to rebirth as a deprived spirit. A few such harmful actions lead to
rebirth as an animal.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3.     If the
non-virtuous act is committed on a special person (see below) then one may be
reborn in hell. If committed against a medium object then one may be reborn a
deprived spirit and if against a lesser object one may be reborn an animal. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="How Precise Can We Be?" pagetitle="How Precise Can We Be?"
                     tocentry="How Precise Can We Be?">
            <paragraph>The
teachings on karma, cause-and-effect, are not there so that when we see something
happening in the world around us, we can cleverly deduce, "Ah, that is because
in a previous life..."  Unless they have reached the stage of clear cognition, even
erudite lamas cannot use the karma teachings to "calculate" either the precise
consequences of present actions or the reason behind present results. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>   
Why then did the Buddha give these teachings? It was to give us a general idea
of what is happening--the "drift", as is said in English--and especially to
indicate the sort of actions to avoid at all costs. As mentioned above, the
Buddha realised that ignorance of long-term karmic consequences was the main
problem for humans and the cause of our inefficient, harmful, disappointing
struggle for happiness. Thus he gives us these key elements so that we have
some idea of what is going on and a clear guideline for action. But it is said
that what is really taking place with karma only becomes clearer with profound
insight, achieved at advanced stages of the path. "Only those from the seventh
bodhisattva levels onwards truly understand karma," it is said. And another
famous quote says that the Buddha alone knows the reason for each of the hues
in a peacock's tail.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Now
let us return to our analysis of karma.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The Ten Virtuous Actions" pagetitle="The Ten Virtuous Actions"
                     tocentry="The Ten Virtuous Actions">
            <table style="background:#CCFFFF;border-collapse:collapse" class="MsoNormalTable">
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <td>Physical Verbal Mental</td>
                     <td>1.     To protect life 2.     To be generous 3.     To maintain a pure sexual conduct 4.     To speak
  the truth straightforwardly 5.     To dispel
  discord among people and bring them to harmony 6.     To speak
  peacefully, sincerely and in a way that is pleasant for others 7.     To speak
  in a way that is meaningful 8.     To reduce
  desires and be content with what one has 9.     To
  cultivate loving kindness and so forth 10.  To penetrate the highest meaning</td>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table>
            <paragraph>The
full maturation is rebirth in the higher realms, i.e. as a human, demi-god or
sense-dimension god (lower six god realms). The corresponding results are,
respectively:</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>To
     have long life and good health.</li>
               <li>To
     have wealth and to be satisfied with what one has.</li>
               <li>To
     have harmonious, long-lasting relationships where the partner is a joy. Or
     else to be happy with one's own company, if solitary.</li>
               <li>To
     meet non-deceitful people and circumstances and receive dharma. To be
     believed, trusted and respected when one speaks.</li>
               <li>To
     have good, trustworthy friends.</li>
               <li>To
     be loved, hear pleasant sounds and have a pleasant voice.</li>
               <li>To
     have powerful speech.</li>
               <li>To
     feel satisfied and have natural generosity of spirit.</li>
               <li>To
     have a loving mind and be loved.</li>
               <li>To
     have insight and compassion.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>The
environmental consequences are to be born in safe, harmonious places, with good
crops and climate, pleasant landscapes, freedom from war and social tension,
presence of dharma teachers and so forth.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The\Karma of Immobility" pagetitle="The\Karma of Immobility"
                     tocentry="The\Karma of Immobility">
            <paragraph>This
topic can become a little complicated in the classical texts. It defines the successive
steps of a concentration-meditation practice and then takes us through the
natural unfolding of the classical concentration meditation journey of the Four
Absorptions (_dhyā_ _na_) and the Four Limitless
Absorptions. This is a 'natural' journey, where one step of focusing the mind
simply leads to another, as peace and concentration progress. Buddhists use it,
Hindus use it and, in part, it is found in other faiths. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
karma teachings examine rebirth consequences +when there is this concentration
meditation alone, not channelled by Buddhist motivation.+ They show how
reaching a certain degree of accomplishment in such meditation in this life
will produce rebirth into a similar state of absorption after death. Such
rebirth is still within samsara and although it lasts a long time and is
pleasant, it eventually ends and whatever other karma one had created takes
over. Therefore, these states have the suffering of fall, experienced by the
gods (as explained in previous module). Besides the actual meditation practice,
it takes a general basis of virtuous karma (generosity, loving mind) and a
general absence of non-virtuous karma for there to be rebirth in the god
realms.  </paragraph>
            <paragraph>When
factors such as Buddhist motivation and prayers accompany exactly the same
concentration meditations, they can become a vital factor for liberation. We
could compare the power of concentration meditation to the wind in the sail
propelling a boat. Motivation is like the intelligence of the captain, using
the wind to reach the destination he wants, even to sail into the wind, if need
be. Otherwise the boat will go wherever the wind takes it. </paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:"
                           pagetitle="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:"
                           tocentry="The Key Steps of Concentration Meditation are:">
               <list kind="ol">
                  <li>(eh)A "*launching phase*" in
     which one acquires properly the technique and any instructions necessary, overcomes
     the awkwardness of unfamiliarity and  becomes familiar with the practice.(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)An *obstacle-removing stage*,
     in which the technique interacts with habitual being. For instance, for
     beginners, simple concentration needs to overcome the constant pull and
     interruption of distractions. Each meditation tackles specific weaknesses
     or lack of skill in the mind. This stage is characterised by hard work and
     not too much result, with occasional breakthrough. However, due to it, and
     only through it, one reaches(eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)The *stage of absorption *(also
     called 'Stage of Freedom'), when the mind can enjoy the true meditation
     and is comfortably resting in its focus. (eeh)</li>
                  <li>(eh)*Stage of transcendence*, where the practice is
     now a fully-acquired part of one's being: second nature and innate skill.(eeh)</li>
               </list>
               <paragraph>(eh)**(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)**(eeh)</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration"
                           pagetitle="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration"
                           tocentry="The Eight Major Classical Steps of Concentration">
               <paragraph>(eh)*First dhyāna* where absorption is
accompanied by intentional thought, analysis, mental joy and physical bliss. There
is a second stage to this dhyāna, know as its "special aspect", where
the intentional thought is dropped.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Second dhyāna* where intentional thought
and analysis have been abandoned, as being gross and being obstacles to finer
absorption, but mental joy and physical bliss are retained.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Third dhyāna* where mental joy is
abandoned (for equanimity) but physical bliss remains.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*Fourth dhyāna* where physical bliss is
also abandoned and there is but equanimity. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*"Limitless Space"* is mind absorbed in
infinite space<a href="#_ftn13">[13]</a>.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*"Limitless Consciousness"*, where it is realised that
space is an aspect of consciousness and that consciousness is infinite.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*"Nothing Whatsoever"*, where no substance is
found of consciousness and mind rests in the nothingness.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)*"Neither Cognition Nor Absence of
Cognition"*,
where although there is nothing, there is nevertheless some awareness of there
being nothing.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>We
will look more into the use, in the various Buddhist systems, of these
meditations in a later module. Here, we will content ourselves with
understanding the karmic outcome of simply cultivating them as such (not in a
Buddhist context where they are "steered" towards liberation or enlightenment).
This is the same as the table at the end of Module 2. </paragraph>
               <table class="MsoNormalTable">
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Overall Category*</td>
                        <td>*Class*</td>
                        <td>*Realm*</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Formless Devas</td>
                        <td>Samsaric levels resulting from the Four
  Formless meditations</td>
                        <td>Neither Cognition Nor Absence of
  Cognition</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Nothing Whatsoever</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Infinite Consciousness</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Infinite Space</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Form-Dimension Devas</td>
                        <td>(eh)Non-samsaric levels resulting from 4th
  dhyana meditation(eeh)</td>
                        <td>(eh)"Highest"<a href="#_ftn14">[14]</a>(eeh)</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>(eh)"Exceptional Sight"(eeh)</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>(eh)"Magnificent Appearance"(eeh)</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>(eh)"No Distress"(eeh)</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>(eh)"Not Greater"(eeh)</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Samsaric levels resulting from 4th dhyana
  meditation</td>
                        <td>"Greater Result"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Produced by Merit"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Cloudless"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Levels resulting from 3rd dhyana
  meditation</td>
                        <td>"Extended Virtue"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Measureless Virtue"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Lesser Virtue"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Levels resulting from 2nd dhyana meditation</td>
                        <td>"Illuminating"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Measureless Light"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Lesser Light"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>Levels resulting from the 1st dhyana
  meditation</td>
                        <td>"Great Brahmas'"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Leading Brahmas'"</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>"Brahma's"</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <paragraph>Having
taken a glimpse at the principal elements of virtuous, non-virtuous and
meditation karma, we will now consider some very important points about karma
in general.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="What does it take to make karma?"
                     pagetitle="What does it take to make karma?"
                     tocentry="What does it take to make karma?">
            <paragraph>(eh)Not every action performed by body,
speech and mind creates karma. It takes six factors for a karma to be produced:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)There needs to have been the
     definite intention to do it.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)It needs to have been carried out
     as intended.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)It needs to be an action capable
     of producing karmic consequences.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)The action needs to have been
     completed. (eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)The doer is pleased with doing it,
     at the time it is done, and has no regrets.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)No remedial action<a href="#_ftn15">[15]</a> is taken
     before fruition commences.(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>When
all six combine, an action is known as a _karma enacted and established._ "Established"
means that an imprint has been programmed ("established") in the universal
basis consciousness<a href="#_ftn16">[16]</a>
and it will later generate results. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>If
one of the six is absent, there is _karma enacted but not established_. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>If
one or more of the six is weak--e.g. confused motivation, action not quite
carried out as intended etc.--then the resulting karma is weaker. This is
particularly true when remedial actions, which give rise to what is called
"purification", are resorted to. The consequences of even very heavy karmas can
be considerably reduced--and even totally neutralised--if the appropriate remedy
is applied sufficiently.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma"
                           pagetitle="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma"
                           tocentry="Physical and Verbal Karma Are Different From Mental Karma">
               <paragraph>The
actions of body and speech are the ones which involve other people. They are
each quite specific and consequently each produces its karmic results in the
future. There is also a cumulative effect (see below). In-between the initial
action and its result, years and lifetimes can go by with nothing happening
related to that initial action. All the time however, the imprint of the
initial action remains in the doer's consciousness, waiting to be triggered by
the right circumstances to produce its effect. It is very much like a seed that
has been planted in the ground, in the autumn. When the spring warmth and rains
come, it will germinate. To human eyes, it is as though the little green shoot
is something entirely new, popping out of the ground. Thus it is with the
things that happen to us in the world and with the people who are significant
in our lives. The results of the physical and verbal karma of our past lives,
as listed above, can seem to pop out of nowhere in the form of what other
people say and do to us, along with the environmental consequences mentioned
above.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Mental
karma is something very different. It is a constantly-evolving story of
conditioning, involving the person alone. One does not have to wait for
lifetimes for the results of good mind karma to manifest. The impact is
immediate, shifting the mind a little this way or that. This is very good news indeed
for us and it is what enabled Milarepa<a href="#_ftn17">[17]</a>
to become a Buddha in one lifetime. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Were
this not the case, there would be an even greater need for faith than there is
already, as we would just have to trust that our good thoughts, prayers,
meditations and so on will bear their fruit in some future life alone, while we
are condemned to have our habitual mind until we die. That is certainly not the
case: a confused or unsettled mind can become serene and wise in just a matter
of years. In spectacular cases, a person's mind can make a life-changing
breakthrough from one day to the next. However, for the body, if someone lacks,
strength, health and beauty then one has no choice but to put up with it in
this life and to wait for good physical karma created in this existence to
generate a beautiful, healthy, long-living body in the next.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Our
mind is also the "king", determining what its subjects--body and speech--will do.
Where the mind goes, body and speech will follow. Anger in the mind will lead
to violence and abusive speech. The sexual cravings of the mind can lead a
person into all sorts of sordid material realities. Spiritual beauty in the
mind--as faith, inspiration, compassionate love--will lead one into wholesome
physical and verbal habits and will attract the material circumstances where
good things can be found and cultivated.   </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Full Maturation" pagetitle="Full Maturation" tocentry="Full Maturation">
            <paragraph>As
we have seen, the full maturation of acts is to be reborn in one or another of
the six realms. The state into which a person is born in one life is mainly a
consequence of the sum total of the actions done, i.e. the karma enacted and
established, in the previous life. There will also be some "leftover" influence
from lives before that. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>For
example, our own full maturation in this life is to be human and this in itself
exposes us to certain general experiences and risks which are those of human
beings. Thus, one needs to distinguish between generalised consequences (_full
maturation_ karma), due to the type of birth, and specific consequences of
specific past acts that are _results resembling their causes_. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Khenchen
Thrangu Rinpoche explains therefore that *not every single thing that happens
is "my karma"* If someone catches a cold today, because of not being dressed
enough in a chill breeze, it is simply part-and-parcel of having a human body
in this world of the elements<a href="#_ftn18">[18]</a>.
It is a general _full maturation_ result and not a specific _result
resembling its cause,_ where one becomes unwell because of a specific act of
harming life at a precise moment in the past. This distinction also applies to
less obvious things than catching colds. He made the point because some
Buddhists have a tendency to read too much meaning into everything. They would
think, "It's not for nothing that I caught a cold today. It's a sign!" and then
continue to either attribute it to a specific past karma or to start to
associate it with other factors, such as the person they met that day, putting
two and two together to make eleven.  One should always remember that, until
the seventh bodhisattva level, what we understand of karma is just the tip of
the iceberg.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Results resembling their causes"
                     pagetitle="Results resembling their causes"
                     tocentry="Results resembling their causes">
            <paragraph>Although
it is generally not possible to remember past lives<a href="#_ftn19">[19]</a>--either at all or in any significant
detail--it is said that _you can know what you did in the past life by looking
at your life now_. This means that one can start to identify specific
personal karma when patterns emerge and repeat themselves and one starts to
recognise that the seeming problems lies not with the world or other people but
with the karma that one carries, wherever one goes. A few examples:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Someone
works very hard but is always scraping to make a living. The person may try
this job or that, may change profession or even country in an effort to get
some financial comfort but somehow prosperity always eludes. There is a good
likelihood of lack of generosity, or perhaps dishonesty, in a former life.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Attempts
to find a soul-mate fall flat on their face, time after time. Even though the
companion is quite different each time, somehow the same problems, a similar
darkness, a similar reaction, crops up. There is a likelihood of unskilful
sexual karma in the past life. Also maybe the perpetuation of a mind state--mental
karma--seeking the impossible.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
A person
speaks the truth and can express it well but nobody wants to listen. People
have no respect for that person's speech and often look down on them. This can
be a sign of untruthful speech or much useless speech in past lives. An
interesting counterpart is the powerful speech of great masters. They may say
just a few words but those words remain engraved in the heart for years and the
disciple can still hear the teacher saying them, in her or his mind, decades
later. This is the result of lifetimes of teaching the truth, in a way that
suits each person.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
In
Tibetan medicine, some health problems (not the majority by the way), known as
"long-term wind-element disorders", are attributed to specific karma. These are
remarkable proofs, in a way, of karma, because they can generate one clinical
condition after another. When the one has been treated, another appears, as
though the "wind" had left one organ and entered a different one. Treating it
can be like trying to chase a rat out of a room: it runs first into this
corner, then that. These are the result of harmful physical actions in a past
life.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>On
a more positive note, meeting the dharma and meeting pure beings is an
exceptional positive result from our past life or lives. As one connects once
again with the teachings and the practice, a whole world of experience is
trawled up from the psyche: it seems like a new world at first but gradually
becomes recognised as the return of an old and familiar one. Flashes and
moments of past blessing can be remembered but also the old problems--the places
where we got stuck or faltered before--will also emerge as time goes by. Each
practice can awaken an old karma, to be taken forward, and special things, such
as long retreats, have their own, unpredictable karma, for those who had the
chance to do them in past lives.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Other points about\karma" pagetitle="Other points about\karma"
                     tocentry="Other points about\karma">
            <subsubsection title="Karma does not fade with time" pagetitle="Karma does not fade with time"
                           tocentry="Karma does not fade with time">
               <paragraph>Unless
a remedy is applied, a specific karma can remain completely dormant for one or
more lifetimes, sometimes many lifetimes, yet its power does not fade with the
passing of time. When the conditions which trigger its fruition are united, it
will emerge with all its power. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Generally, karma is non-transferable"
                           pagetitle="Generally, karma is non-transferable"
                           tocentry="Generally, karma is non-transferable">
               <paragraph>"The
results of karma always ripen in their doer," it says in the _Compendium
of Knowledge_. There will never be a cosmic mix-up, like a bank account
error where one client's money or debt is shifted to another client's account.
There is good reason for this. Creating a karma programmes the consciousness of
the doer, who then carries that programming throughout the rest of his or her
life and on into the next life. We can understand the mechanism by considering the
trauma of a dog bite. A person bitten may think no more of it for fifty years
but then one day meet a dog exactly like the one that bit him or her in
childhood. The mind carries the memory of the event: where or how is a mystery
but it obviously does. That particular conditioning is not somehow going to be
transferred from the person and turn up in someone who was never bitten.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Each
individual's stream of consciousness is unique and so the karma in one
consciousness (we could say "mind") stays in that consciousness,
through death, into the next life and on and on until triggered to fruition.
Therefore when we say the results ripen in "the doer", it is in some
ways enigmatic, as the person we are in one life is quite different from the
person we may become in the next. Nevertheless, the karmic programming from the
old "person" is there, like it or not. In some ways, it can seem very
"unfair", yet it is simply like that. It is like the pollution thrown
into a river upstream being experienced by the inhabitants downstream. Or, to
take a truer example, like the physical or psychological damage of an
ex-drug-taker persisting long into a future where they have no more interest
whatsoever in drugs and have become "cleaner-than-clean". This
"unfairness" of inheriting karma from the person we were in a past
life is one of the reasons the Buddha, in his compassion, shines light on
action, so that we can become lucid and make the future life how we would like
it to be.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)_Exercise and Topic of Reflection: Some people get very upset
at the idea of karma being the cause of ailments in this life. Taking the
example of someone who is severely disabled, physically or mentally, they see
it as an insult to the person, implying they have something evil about them for
which they are being punished: that they have somehow deserved it. The Buddhist
response it that there is neither punishment nor reason for guilt. It is just
the nature of things and that also the "person" now, although being the ongoing
consciousness stream of the "person" in previous lives, is quite a different
being. Anything could have happened in between the ancient cause and this
present result. Please consider the above paragraphs and try to understand and argue
each side of the case until you come to your own conclusion.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)A second possible step to this exercise
is to consider examples at the other extreme. There are those who are healthy,
long-living and prosperous now yet who seem not to be good people. The
prosperous are not necessarily generous now and the handsome and fit are not
necessarily pillars of moral conduct. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)Karma is not _instant karma<a href="#_ftn20">[20]</a>_. It works itself out
over long time periods and is very complex.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Are
there exceptions to this non-transferability of karma? In some ways, there are.
It is possible, through the coming-together of the power of interdependence and
the power of compassion, for one person to alleviate the sufferings of another
being. It is exceptional but it does happen, as was the case with
Dharmarakshita, a lama who winced and cried out in pain one day in a teaching.
When asked why, he said that some people outside the temple had thrown a big,
sharp rock at a dog and that he had taken the dog's pain. The disciples were a
little incredulous and first went outside where indeed a dog had been stoned. Returning
to the temple, the lama lifted his robe and they saw the wound and a bruise
emerging, in an equivalent place to where the dog had been hit. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Karma is infallible" pagetitle="Karma is infallible"
                           tocentry="Karma is infallible">
               <paragraph> It
will never happen that a "virtuous" karma produces suffering for its
doer in the next life. It will never happen that a non-virtuous action produces
happy consequences for the doer in the next life. The seeds of a poisonous
plant produce a poisonous plant, by their very nature. The data for that is
programmed into the seed from day one. The seeds of a delicious fruit will
similarly produce a delicious fruit. It will never happen that you plant a plum
stone and it produces a deadly nightshade bush the following year.    </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Karma and Morality" pagetitle="Karma and Morality"
                           tocentry="Karma and Morality">
               <paragraph>Ethics
are a fundamental part of each person's life. Everyone has some sense of good_
and _bad_ conduct, of _right_ and _wrong._ These are defined
variously in the different faiths and belief-systems. In the Abrahamic
faiths--the so-called "religions of the book"<a href="#_ftn21">[21]</a>--the guidelines come from
God, via prophets or his son. For Humanists, they arise from reason and a basic
sense of human dignity. For Buddhists, although we have our dharma teachings on
"virtue" and "non-virtue" from the Buddha, we do not adopt
them as a set of ethical values _just_ because he taught them. Rather, we
see them as the natural way things happen and it is simply that the Buddha opens
our eyes to what "is":</paragraph>
               <image width="436"/>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Buddhist Values" pagetitle="Buddhist Values" tocentry="Buddhist Values">
               <paragraph>_Virtuous_ or _good_ or _meritorious _(one
finds all those terms in the texts, and more) actions are +self-defined through
their own effects+--in both the short and long term. Generosity helps other
people in the immediate present, it beautifies the mind of the giver and also
generates happiness, wealth and satisfaction for the doer in future lives. Thus
it is +innately virtuous+, not virtuous because someone, the Buddha,
declared it so.</paragraph>
               <image width="436"/>
               <paragraph>Similarly, _non-virtuous, evil_ or
_damaging_ actions are self-defined by their effects. Killing or violence
hurts other beings in the immediate present, it sullies the mind of the doer in
the present and it brings the painful consequences of illness and early death for
the doer in future lives. It is innately non-virtuous.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Please
contemplate this point, and all its implications for Buddhist morality, at
length. Further, be careful not to become confused about the absolute-truth
teachings of _"no good, no evil", "no samsara, no nirvana",
"samsara and nirvana are the same"_ and so forth. A very
advanced degree of meditation experience is necessary before the meaning of
those phrases is properly known. Beware of taking them at face value and
thereby letting them throw into question the value of strictly applying
conventional Buddhist ethics. None of our great masters ever wanted that and so
many of the greatest (Saraha, Karmapa etc.) warned against it. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Those
absolute-truth teachings are there, on a verbal level, to help us understand that
ultimately any value-judgement, such as _good_ or _evil_, will be
transcended by direct perception of truth. They help us establish a horizon of
going beyond presumptions and fixed ideas, both about the world and about
enlightenment. In the end, these and all concepts are always subjective and
highly-limited.      </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Understanding
the nature of our own projections about relative reality is one thing.
Understanding what is actually happening in relative reality, above and beyond
our subjective labelling, is another. The karma teachings are there to help us
with the latter. This is why Guru Rinpoche said, so famously:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Make your view as broad as space but
your action as fine as flour._</paragraph>
               <paragraph>In
other words, even for those who have mastered _mahamudra_ or _dzogchen_
and other great teachings, and who have an enlightened view as broad as space,
there is no virtuous action that is too small to not be worth doing and
likewise no harmful action that is so trivial it is not worth avoiding. This
attention to detail while remaining ever mindful of voidness is something we
can observe and admire in the best lamas we meet. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="Scale and Proportion in Karma   "
                           pagetitle="Scale and Proportion in Karma   "
                           tocentry="Scale and Proportion in Karma   ">
               <paragraph>The
outcomes of actions are not easily calculable. It is nothing like "an eye for
an eye" and it does not mean that exactly the same thing done in this life will
happen, in return, to the doer in the next life. It is not a simple reversal of
roles, where someone who steals a car will have to have a similar car stolen,
with a similar _modus operandi_, in the next life. That sort of thing can
happen, as some spectacular stories of karma in the sutras illustrate, but it
does not at all have to be like that. The scale can be enormously different: a
small cause can produce a great effect and many causes can produce only a
single result. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>If
the mind informing an action is very strong indeed--powerful hatred or powerful
compassionate love, for instance--then it is said that just one instant of action
can produce hundreds of lifetimes, and in some cases aeons, of result. In those
moments when our minds are uplifted, filled with faith in the absolute and
loving care for all beings, the karmic consequences are great indeed. It is
compared to a single powerful seed, which with time produces a great harvest.
On the other hand, bitter, hateful abuse directed towards a holy being or one's
parents (see below) is compared to poison, which may be small in volume but
which spoils the whole feast of the future and leads to downfall. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>What
determines the scale of the outcome? Several factors: the motivating mind, the
action itself and the "field", meaning the person to whom it is done.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Four Special Fields of Action"
                           pagetitle="The Four Special Fields of Action"
                           tocentry="The Four Special Fields of Action">
               <paragraph>Either
because of their own very nature or because of their strong karmic links with
us, there are four special fields of action which generate much more powerful
results than other, more "indifferent", fields. They are:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>1.     Those particularly
designated by their qualities, i.e. gurus, the Three Most Precious Refuges etc.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>2.     Those particularly
designated by the benefit (they have brought us)--father, mother etc.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>3.     Those particularly
designated by their sufferings--the sick, the unprotected etc.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>4.     Those particularly
designated by the harm (they have done us)--enemies etc.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>   </paragraph>
               <paragraph>For
this reason, although one needs to be mindful and aware of action all the time,
there is a particular need to be mindful in what one says and does when in the
company of the above. Of all instances, karma enacted in the presence of a
buddha is strongest. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="5" title="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma"
               pagetitle="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma"
               tocentry="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma">
         <subsection title="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma"
                     pagetitle="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma"
                     tocentry="The Afflictions (klesha), the Cause of Karma">
            <image width="443"/>
            <paragraph>Why
does someone do the harmful actions described in the previous section? Mind is
the king and body and speech are its slaves. It is a non-virtuous mind that
causes someone to do non-virtuous actions, just as it is a virtuous one that
leads them to virtuous acts. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>Without
anger towards animals (for instance towards aphids for damaging the roses) or
desire for their meat to eat and their skins to wear or the ignorance of animal
sacrifice, why would one kill or harm them? Without self-centred passion, why
would someone engage in non-virtuous sexual conduct? Without self-interest, why
would one lie? In general, actions are performed to get what is wanted--for
oneself or one's kith and kin--or to avoid the unwanted. One simple analysis
often referred to in Tibetan literature is that of the Eight Worldly Concerns,
i.e. seeking: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>To
     *gain* what one needs or wants.</li>
               <li>To
     avoid *losing* what one has.</li>
               <li>To
     seek *pleasure*.</li>
               <li>To
     avoid what is *unpleasant* or *painful*.</li>
               <li>To
     be *praised*.</li>
               <li>To
     avoid *blame*.</li>
               <li>To
     gain *respect*.</li>
               <li>To
     avoid *bad reputation*.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)The Eight Worldly Concerns -
Mnemonic(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)Loss and gain, pleasure and
pain, praise and blame, fame and bad name(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Taken
together, all the motivating emotions and mind-states behind non-virtuous karma
are known as _klesha_, a word meaning _afflictions, defilements,
poisons, cankers..._  If one simply represses the harmful actions themselves,
without working on their causes, there will be bottled-up anger, passion and so
forth. Besides making people uncomfortable, suppressed feelings may well one
day erupt, in moments of weakness, and do untold damage. Therefore it is
important to understand clearly these klesha and to learn how to recognise
them, reduce them and eventually remove them by the very root.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
we are investigating the Truth of the Causes of Suffering, we should only be
considering here the klesha, the thoughts and feelings--known technically as _mental
events,_ the fourth aggregate--which make a person do the non-virtuous acts defined
above in the _karma_ section. However, since in that section we also
considered virtuous and meditative karma then, for completeness, a list of the
virtuous _mental events_ are included in the Annexes, at the <a href="#virtuous">end</a> of this document.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>As
far as non-virtuous mental events are concerned, there are the six basic non-virtuous
mental events and the twenty-one related or _subsidiary_ non-virtuous
mental events. The following is taken from Ju Mipham Rinpoche's _Entering the
Ways of the Wise_, as taught in Samye Ling by the Goshir Gyaltsab Rinpoche.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The\6 basic non-virtuous mental events"
                     pagetitle="The\6 basic non-virtuous mental events"
                     tocentry="The\6 basic non-virtuous mental events">
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*Ignorance* - not to know about
     karma, cause-and-effect, the truth(s) or the Three Precious Refuges<a href="#_ftn22">[22]</a>. This gives
     rise to the afflictions.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Desire and attachment* - to be stickily
     involved with the tainted aggregates of the three dimensions of existence:
     this engenders the sufferings of existence. It is said to be of two types:(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.    
_Involvement
with desires and the objects of the sense fields_: attachment to the sense dimension.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.    
_Involvement
with existence itself_:
attachment to the two higher dimensions.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>(eh)*Anger and hatred* - a state of mind very
     irritated by other beings, sufferings or the circumstances that provoke
     suffering. It is this which prevents one from enjoying happiness and which
     forms a basis for unwholesome action.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Pride *- to be arrogant and high-minded
     due to one of the 'destructible complex' attitudes (see below). There are
     seven main sorts<a href="#_ftn23">[23]</a>. Generally they are a
     basis for not respecting others and for the arising of suffering.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Doubt* - to be "in two minds"
     about the truths and their meaning/significance. This stops one from
     engaging in what is virtuous.(eeh)</li>
               <li>(eh)*Negatively-affected views* - form the basis for all
     the various mistaken views (attitudes).(eeh)</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>The
last of these points can be developed into *The Five Main Misconceptions*</paragraph>
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>_Attitudes
     related to the "destructible complex"_ - these are inner
     attitudes, mental postures, philosophical stances--and sometimes religious
     beliefs and dogmas--that mistakenly attribute the idea of "I",
     "mine", "we" or "ours" to the "five aggregates which attract
     suffering" (the  skandhas).  For example, the first aggregate is
     form: in our case the human body. Some people take the physical body as
     "I", the self, or as "Mine", belonging to the self. Other people attribute
     the self to the third aggregate, perception: "I am what I perceive the
     world to be." Altogether there are twenty such permutations known, not
     very elegantly, as the Views of the Twenty Destructible Complexes,
     so-called since the illusion of a lasting self is attributed to something
     which is impermanent and subject to destruction<a href="#_ftn24">[24]</a>. These
     twenty constitute the basis for the other mistaken attitudes.</li>
               <li>_The
     extremists' attitude_--Eternalist
     or nihilistic beliefs, i.e  respectively thinking the ego or the five
     aggregates are  eternal (permanent) or nothing at all. These create
     obstacles to emancipation through (practice of) the middle way.</li>
               <li>_Perverse
     attitudes_--that
     consider conditions which do exist--such as cause and effect etc.--to be non-­existent.
     These bring about the destruction of the roots of virtue.</li>
               <li>_Conviction
     that one's own attitude is best_--to view the three harmful
     attitudes above and/or their bases (the five aggregates) as being supreme
     and holy. For instance, an _extremist_ may attribute the idea of self
     to consciousness (fifth aggregate) and define it as eternal, making it
     God, and then refuse any thought which puts that into question. This makes
     solid entrenchment in misconception.</li>
               <li>_Conviction
     that one's moral discipline and code of conduct are best_--this follows on from
     the previous points. It is to consider moral disciplines and
     rules of conduct which are innately impure and
     unemancipated--and their bases, the five aggregates--as
     being able to actually liberate one. This renders austerities and
     hardships useless.</li>
            </list>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The 21\Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events"
                     pagetitle="The 21\Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events"
                     tocentry="The 21\Subsidiary Non-Virtuous Mental Events">
            <list kind="ol">
               <li>_Wrath_ - an
     intensification of anger, which makes one ready to inflict real harm by
     beating etc;</li>
               <li>_Resent_ - another aspect
     of anger, whereby one will not let go of thoughts of harm or make
     place for forbearance.</li>
               <li>_Rage_ - arises through wrath
     and resent. It causes one to lose patience and shout abuse.</li>
               <li>_Irritation
     _- also
     part of anger. It causes one to lose compassion and love and to scorn
     others.</li>
               <li>_Jealousy_ - also an aspect of
     anger. A
     deeply distressed mind caused by attachment to one'sown
     reputation, honour etc. and by not being able to bear the good things
     which happen to others.</li>
               <li>_Worldly
     Discontent_
     - a mind not naturally at ease: this forms a basis for the unwholesome.</li>
               <li>_Deceit_ - to conceal one's
     shortcomings through attachment to fame and respect etc. this is adevious state of
     mind that maintains the unwholesome. It is part of desire, aversion and
     stupidity. It creates obstacles to encountering (heeding) the most useful
     advice.</li>
               <li>_Hypocrisy
     or Pretence_
     - through
     attachment to fame, honours and the like,to
     pretendto have qualities that one does not really
     possess. Thereby one attempts to deceive others by such
     untruths. It is an aspect of stupidity and desire. It createsa
     support for the main and subsidiary afflictions as well as
     laying a foundation for a corrupt way of life.</li>
               <li>_Absence
     of Self-Respect_
     - in one's private conduct, one does not try to overcome darker habits.
     This belongs to the three poisons and providesnourishment to the afflictions
     and their subsidiaries.</li>
               <li>_Absence
     of a Sense of Shame_
     - this is similar but in terms of relations with others: one does not shun
     non-virtuous
     activities but blatantly pursues tham. This is part of the three
     poisons and asupport for all the afflictions.</li>
               <li>_Dissimulation_ - part of both
     stupidity and desire,
     whereby one does not respond to useful advice but prefers (instead) to
     cover up shortcomings. It acts as a basis for not following up regret.</li>
               <li>_Avarice_ - through desire and
     attachment, personal possessions become considered to be something
     special. This prevents generosity and simplification of life.</li>
               <li>_Narcissism_ - the sort of state of
     mind that loves and clings to whatever tainted good things are present,
     such as good health,
     youth etc., with complete disinterest and contempt for anyone
     who does not hold you in great esteem. This is a contributory
     factor to the primary and secondary afflictions.</li>
               <li>_Absence
     of Trust/Faith_
     - an aspect of stupidity. It is an absence of interest for all that is
     wholesome and virtuous. It forms a basis for wasting precious life time.</li>
               <li>_Laziness_ - it is involvement
     with unworthy activities,
     such as delighting in sleep, lounging, hanging around etc. It
     makes people take life too easily without either enthusiasm
     for virtue or its application. It is the enemy of diligence.</li>
               <li>_Negligence_ - arises through the
     three poisons and laziness: one does not pay careful attention to the
     principles of action (adopt the good, shun the bad). This is the enemy of care,
     bringing about an increase of non-virtue and a decrease of virtue.</li>
               <li>_Lack
     of mindfulness_
     - one forgets or becomes vague about virtuous intentions. It is the basis
     for distraction and a giving way to the afflictions connected with
     the contrary of mindfulness as well as to the wrong sort of
     mindfulness that accompanies them .</li>
               <li>_Unawareness_ - intelligence that is
     distracted and accompanied
     by the afflictions. When acting through the 'three
     doors' of body, speech and mind, there is little or no awareness. Things
     are done just any old way: this creates opportunity for
     mistakes to happen.</li>
               <li>_Torpor_ - is part of stupidity
     - a physical and mental heaviness where the mind is unworkable and unable
     to be directed to its object. Instead it is drawn into an inner obscurity.
     This lays the foundation for the negative afflictions.</li>
               <li>_Agitation_ - part of
     desire/attachment: to chase after attractive characteristics. The mind
     vacillates towards its object and is no longer workable. It
     loses its peace. This constitutes an obstacle to samatta (tran­quility).</li>
               <li>_Total
     Distractedness_
     - part of the three poisons: the mind is pulled to its object and wanders.
     This prevents it being concentrated on a worthwhile goal. There are
     various types (of distraction) - outwards, inwards, to be carried
     away by detail etc.</li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>These
21 afflictions
are called "the subsidiary afflictions" because they are
part of, and close to, the primary ones.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>end of extract from Mipham
Rinpoche text</paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="6" title="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of&#xA;Self and Other"
               pagetitle="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of&#xA;Self and Other"
               tocentry="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of&#xA;Self and Other">
         <subsection title="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of\Self and Other"
                     pagetitle="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of\Self and Other"
                     tocentry="The Cause of the Afflictions: Delusions of\Self and Other">
            <image width="461"/>
            <paragraph>Once
it is well understood that the afflictions described above are the reason why
people act--to get what they want and to avoid what they don't want--the next
question is of course, "Well then, why are
these desires, jealousies, pride, fears and anger in the mind?" The main reason
is because the mind has a fixed and deluded notion of self, of "I" (of ego, of
persona, however you prefer to express it). The Theravada and Hinayana
teachings focus almost uniquely on this *ego-illusion* as being the *prime
cause of the afflictions*. In Mahayana Buddhism, this delusion of self is
taken as part of a twofold process of projecting dualistic delusions concerning:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Oneself and </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Other people and the world.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Ego-illusion" pagetitle="Ego-illusion" tocentry="Ego-illusion">
            <paragraph>Many
people misunderstand non-ego. The Buddha's teaching is not that a person does
not exist _at all_, that there is nothing there whatsoever. By one day understanding
non-ego, we do not suddenly disappear in a puff of smoke! The Buddha teaches
very clearly that we each exist relatively as an exceedingly complex,
ever-changing stream of the five aggregates. What does not exist lastingly and
substantially is +the imagined self+ that is projected--very grossly--onto
that real stream of the aggregates. It is only an idea, with all the frailty
and changeability that ideas have. It is called a delusion or an illusion. One
could equally say _projection of self_, _assumption, preconceived idea_
etc.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>   
The illusory idea of "I", "me", "us", "mine" etc. is the root of our passions
and hates, pride and jealousy. By understanding the nature of the five
aggregates (what we truly are) and by dismantling these fixed delusions of
self, freedom from samsara can be attained, definitively.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Overcoming
the enormous power of delusions of self is equally a fundamental part of
Mahayana Buddhism. It is the only way to freedom. However, by tackling _all_
dualistic delusions--of both self +and+ other--not only freedom but also
enlightenment can be attained. There are two main aspects to dualistic delusion:
the "dualistic split" and dualistic thought.</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="The Dualistic Split" pagetitle="The Dualistic Split"
                     tocentry="The Dualistic Split">
            <paragraph>In year
three, when we study the transformation of the eight consciousnesses into the
five wisdoms, we will investigate the seventh consciousness, known as the _warping
consciousness_. It performs two functions: </paragraph>
            <list kind="ul">
               <li>It
     splits the awareness of the present moment arbitrarily into two.</li>
               <li>It
     simultaneously triggers the following moment of consciousness. </li>
            </list>
            <paragraph>This
happens instant after instant, every instant, and is part of the fundamental
mechanism of mind, until one reaches the 8^th^ bodhisattva level. In
actual fact, the information in the mind at any instant has no compartments, no
two sides, no inner and outer. Yet the seventh consciousness provokes an
arbitrary split, giving the impression that some things within any instant of
awareness are the inner subject while other things are the outer object. It
creates a strange, invisible borderline, wherein the inner observing awareness
feels like "I" and the outer thing observed seems much more distant and feels like
something else or someone else. The line is arbitrary as it changes from moment
to moment.</paragraph>
            <image width="472"/>
            <paragraph>*Exercise:*  In a quiet moment, perhaps
during meditation, look out of a window at an object in the far distance.
Become aware of your awareness and feel how one part of the experience feels
like "you", looking. Then become aware of the distant "thing" that you are
looking at, and how it feels "other". After a while, become aware of both sides--you
and the thing--at the same time and of the combined feeling of subject-object,
perceiver-perceived. Then, quietly, let your gaze shift from the distant object
to the window itself: look at the window. Then look again at the object. As you
do this, shifting focus from the window to the distant object, be aware of how
this invisible boundary between subject and object shifts. You can continue the
exercise by shifting your awareness next from the window to your own body.
Recognise how your body, which felt like part of "me", the subject, when you
were looking at the distant object, has now shifted from being on the inside to
being on the "outside" and it has become "the object".</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Dualistic Thought" pagetitle="Dualistic Thought"
                     tocentry="Dualistic Thought">
            <paragraph>The
above split of consciousness happens--whether one likes it or not--every single
instant, for all beings of the six realms. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>On
the basis of this split, the conceptual mind of a being capable of constructive
thought, such as a human, builds up stories. These stories are very important as
they determine the nature and quality of life. In fact, for the most part, they
_are_ the nature and quality of life. For example, if someone lives in a
land of much rain and has an inner dialogue repeating the story that "I adore
the rain", then he feels blessed to live there. Perhaps the person living next
door detests rain and feels cursed to live in such a place. The climate is the
same: the inner hermeneutic is different.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One
facet of the inner dialogue is the story told about "me". It has built up over
time, with some parts deeply, sometimes secretly, entrenched and other parts
more superficial. The other facet of the inner dialogue is that of the many
stories told about "other": other people--mother, father, brother, sister,
friend, enemy, colleagues and so forth-- and other things--the world, politics,
places, situations and the like.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Although
all of those inner reference cards of other people are never any more than ephemeral
thoughts, they can become seemingly very "solid" over time. They turn into
fixed ideas and rigid preconceptions, so much so that when one pulls up an
image of the person in the mind, it can bring floods of emotion--tenderness,
anger, nostalgia, passion... The same happens with more abstract concepts:
ideas about politics, religion, nationality, culture and the like. People would
die or kill on account of the thoughts and images in their "head".</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
"I" side of the story complicates itself into four departments: "I" and "mine"
and the extended self of "we" and "ours". In other words, ego extends to
encompass family, or friends, or nation, or religious group. It also extends to
material and intellectual possessions.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The
ideas of "I" and "other", as described above lead to the afflictions. This is
because once "I" has been defined in a certain way and "other" has been defined
in a certain way, then it will follow that "I" will _crave_ for certain
"others" and _detest_ other "others". The imaginary "I" will be _proud_
of itself compared to some others and _jealous_ of other "others". There
are very vivid examples of this in the way people fall in and out of love, or
in the religious or racial conflicts that beleaguer our world, or in the pride
of a football supporter. It is happening everywhere, all the time.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>On
a positive note, there is an extraordinary potential in this process. Although
one has no power at all to alter the dualistic split itself, one *can* change
the inner dualistic storytelling--about each side of the split--to great
advantage. In Mahayana and Vajrayana Buddhism, it is done in a systematic way
using skilful method. However, it can happen even in ordinary life in quite a
spectacular way. By changing the story, a person who was formerly deeply loved
can become a detested enemy overnight. Something once scorned can become
cherished. A person can become proud of his or her origins, whereas previously
there was shame. Meat, previously relished, can become repulsive for someone
who turns vegetarian.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <img width="472" src="module3_files/image011.png"/>_Exercise:  Study the previous two
paragraphs and bring them to life by thinking through examples that make sense
to you, either from situations in your own life or in the lives of people
around you or from situations you find in the media. Try to grasp clearly the
role of the inner storytelling. Notice also, in the process, that the thoughts
involved come and go like ghosts, with no substance or solidity whatsoever, yet
with so much power to shape a person's character and life.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*In Mahayana Buddhism delusions of ego
are gradually and harmoniously replaced by the bodhisattva ideal. *(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)*In Vajrayana Buddhism, the delusions
are replaced by identifying with the "deity"<a href="#_ftn25">[25]</a>.*(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>We
will return to these later in the course. The point in this section is to
recognise the power of dualistic thought to give rise to, and then nourish, the
afflictions.  </paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="7" title="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"
               pagetitle="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"
               tocentry="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality">
         <subsection title="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"
                     pagetitle="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality"
                     tocentry="Ignorance, the Cause of Ego and Duality">
            <image width="461"/>
            <paragraph>(eh)Why is there the instant-by-instant
dualistic split of awareness? It occurs because of the ignorance veiling mind's
true nature. When will it end? The veil is torn apart when ignorance becomes
primordial wisdom.(eeh)</paragraph>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance"
                     pagetitle="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance"
                     tocentry="Simultaneous Ignorance &amp; Conceptual Ignorance">
            <paragraph>(eh)These are the two main aspects of
ignorance:(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)·     
*Concomitant
ignorance* or
*simultaneous ignorance<a href="#_ftn26">[26]</a>*
dates back to time without beginning and accompanies each moment of awareness.
It is karmically neutral. What is ignored is absolute truth: the true nature.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)·     
*Conceptual
Ignorance* is one of the mind poisons. By solidifying the chronic ignorance
into fixed ideas of self and other, it gives rise to karma that perpetuates
samsara. It is therefore one of the afflictions. Further, it causes specific
ignorance and confusion about the relative truth and in particular the nature
of cause-and-effect.(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Ignorance
is the way we translate the Sanskrit term _avidyā_
or the Tibetan term _ma rig pa_. In both cases, it is a negative, meaning _not-knowing,
unaware_. The opposites are important terms in dharma: _vidyā_ and _rig pa_ (pronounced _rikpa_)
meaning intelligent awareness. The term has the feel of bright, awakened clarity.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the case of *chronic ignorance, what is not known is defined as:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Non-ego,
in the Hinayana and Theravada systems, and </paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
Non-dual<a href="#_ftn27">[27]</a>, pure, enlightened nature of
mind (voidness or buddha nature) in the Mahayana. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>It
is (fortunately) karmically neutral, as otherwise, since it occurs in each
instant and it has been happening since time immemorial, the harmful karma
generated would be devastating and unbearable, with no hope of ever being free
of it. </paragraph>
            <paragraph>This
ignorance is brought to an end by wisdom but not by wisdom as thoughts. The wisdom which ends ignorance is a vivid, direct
awareness of the nature of things. In the Hinayana and Theravadin
systems, this means becoming directly aware of the meaning of the Four Truths
of the Realised. This happens in sixteen "moments" of awakening: four for each
truth. Profound realisation of non-ego is accomplished during those sixteen.  </paragraph>
            <paragraph>In
the Mahayana, one realises the non-dual purity of everyone and of every thing.
There are many names for this and the various traditions each have their
favourites. It is called buddha nature, the true nature of mind, _sunyata_,
voidness, _mahamudra_, the great perfection, the great middle way, _prajnaparamita_,
the one-and-only, _dharmata_, the unique bindu, buddha mind, primordial
wisdom, pristine awareness and so on. </paragraph>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section index="8" title="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent&#xA;Origination"
               pagetitle="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent&#xA;Origination"
               tocentry="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent&#xA;Origination">
         <subsection title="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent\Origination"
                     pagetitle="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent\Origination"
                     tocentry="Interdependence &amp; Interdependent\Origination">
            <paragraph>Nothing
simply _is_. Nothing exists all by itself. Everything and everyone _depend_
upon other things in order to be what they are. There are two aspects to
interdependence: momentary interdependence and historical interdependence:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*Momentary
interdependence*
is the way one thing depends upon other things for its seeming existence+ in
the instant+. For instance, a "yellow wall" seems to be yellow in its own
right--a yellow thing--yet the yellow we see when we look at "the wall"
is in fact the _yellow of sunlight _reflected off the wall, not the yellow
of the wall at all. The wall absorbs some of the spectrum but "bounces" off the
yellow part. Without light shining on the wall, there is no yellow.
Furthermore, without an eye to see it, there is no "yellow" either, as yellow
is an experience that happens in a human brain. No actual yellow colour travels
through space but whatever (if anything) does travel through space triggers the
eye which triggers the brain which produces the yellow experience. It is the
coming-together of many things--a human eye, the substance of the wall, the sun's
rays etc.--that produces the momentary experience of yellow. 
    This is simply an example that is easy to understand, using "modern" scientific
intelligence. It demonstrates to anyone that in each instant, each seeming
"thing" is in fact the coming-together of many circumstances and not something
fixed forever in its own nature. It is not what it at first seems.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>·     
*Historical
interdependence*
follows the cause-and-effect process +through time+. The eye that sees
yellow was created by the person's parents, along with the rest of the child.
It was sustained, protected and developed through food and other conditions
until this moment. The wall was built from bricks, because of someone's idea to
build it there. The bricks themselves came out of mud due to silt deposited
over centuries by a river and so forth. The light shining on the wall comes from
nuclear reaction in the Sun. Each circumstance during a moment of
interdependence has its own history and causality.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>One
could simplify the above and talk of _interdependence in space and in time_.
In this section, we are investigating interdependence in relation to suffering.
The main process has already been outlined, step by step:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>*ignorance   **a **ego illusion   **a **  affliction** a**    karma** a**   suffering*</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The classical way of
looking into the historical interdependence of this is through a topic known as
_Interdependent Origination_ or _The Twelve Links of Interdependent
Origination_. These
twelve are presented clearly as a chain-reaction. Interdependent origination
shows us that once a certain number of factors are gathered together, the
consequences will surely be triggered, like putting a match to dry gunpowder.
They also show, in the opposite sense, that if any single link in the chain is
destroyed, then none of the subsequent links will happen. +With the "Twelve
Links of Interdependence", we have the genetic code of samsara+. It is
a sort of universal master-plan that can be applied over a series of lifetimes,
over two lifetimes or to a single instant of time. </paragraph>
            <image width="481"/>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Outer Interdependence: the\Twelve Links"
                     pagetitle="Outer Interdependence: the\Twelve Links"
                     tocentry="Outer Interdependence: the\Twelve Links">
            <paragraph>(eh)*Ignorance**   **a **creations**   **a **consciousness**   **a **name
and form**   **a **perceptual gateways**   **a **contact**   **a **feeling**   **a **craving**   **a **grasping**   **a **becoming**   **a **birth**   **a **ageing
and death *(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>**</paragraph>
            <paragraph>We shall now study Gampopa's presentation of
the Twelve Links, supported by images from the outer ring of the Wheel of Life
thangka<a href="#_ftn28">[28]</a>:
In the
explanation below, links in *blue* are
afflictions (_klesha_), links in *red*
are action (_karma_) and the *others* are suffering itself. </paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The\Twelve Links of Interdependence"
                           pagetitle="The\Twelve Links of Interdependence"
                           tocentry="The\Twelve Links of Interdependence">
               <image width="136"/>
               <paragraph>1.     <img width="11" src="module3_files/image015.png"/>The first (link)
established, represented by a lost, blind person, is the condition of "*confused ignorance*", a non-recognition of that
unique nature<a href="#_ftn29">[29]</a>
which ought to be known, due to which</paragraph>
               <image width="142"/>
               <paragraph>2.     There is the actual
doing of *tainted action*, be it virtuous
or non-virtuous, represented by a potter (fabricating a reality by his own
actions). This is known as "*creation* due to the condition of ignorance".</paragraph>
               <paragraph>3.     <img width="11" src="module3_files/image017.png"/>
                  <img width="115" align="left" src="module3_files/image018.png"/>The mind polluted by
the seed-like potentials imprinted in it by such actions is known as "*consciousness*
due to the condition of creations", represented by monkeys gathering fruits.
Through the power of action, mind is</paragraph>
               <paragraph>4.     <img width="144" align="left" src="module3_files/image019.png"/>
                  <img width="136" align="left" src="module3_files/image020.png"/>Transformed into
something quite aberrant and joins up with the procreative elements in the
mother's womb to become the various stages of embryo and then foetus. This is
known as "*name and form* due to the condition of consciousness". Name and
form (see below) are represented by two people in the same boat. Through the
development of this</paragraph>
               <paragraph>5.     The various sense and
mind faculties--of sight, smell etc.--become complete. They are known as the "*six
perceptual gateways* due to the condition of name and form", represented by
a house with six sections.</paragraph>
               <image width="146"/>
               <paragraph>6.     <img width="135" align="left" src="module3_files/image022.png"/>When these various
faculties, such as sight and so on, meet up with their corresponding objective
fields through the corresponding consciousness, this tripartite meeting causes
an actual experience of the object. This is known as "*contact*
conditioned by the six perceptual gateways", represented by a couple in
passionate embrace. According to the nature of this contact there arises</paragraph>
               <paragraph>7.     *Feeling*, or sensation, in the
sense of a pleasant, unpleasant or indifferent experience, represented by a
person with an arrow in the eye. This is known as "feeling due to the condition
of contact".</paragraph>
               <paragraph>8.     <img width="139" align="left" src="module3_files/image023.png"/>Attachment to that
feeling--craving and powerful craving for it--is known as "*craving* due to the condition of feeling",
represented by a picnic. Through such craving there is a</paragraph>
               <image width="85"/>
               <paragraph>9.     Mental striving in
order either not to lose the experience or to bring it back. This is known as "*grasping* due to the condition of craving",
represented here by picking fruit from a tree. Due to this striving one</paragraph>
               <image width="84"/>
               <paragraph>10.  Performs
actions--physically, verbally or mentally--which generate rebirth. This is known
as "*becoming*, due to the condition of
grasping" and is represented by a pregnant woman.</paragraph>
               <image width="133"/>
               <paragraph>11.  <img width="114" align="left" src="module3_files/image027.png"/>Whatever existence
composed of the five aggregates is generated by those actions is known as "*birth*
due to the condition of becoming", represented by childbirth. Through having
been born,</paragraph>
               <paragraph>12.  The development and
maturity of the actual existence is ageing and its destruction is death,
depicted by a man carrying a shrouded corpse to the cremation ground. These are
"*ageing and death* due to the condition of birth".  </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The section accompanied by a green line can represent the inheritance
from past lives, in which case we are considering timeless ignorance and all
the things done in the past that have made the unique consciousness coming into
this life.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img width="11" src="module3_files/image028.png"/>The section accompanied by a purple line represents the generating and
the generated in respect of the future life<a href="#_ftn30">[30]</a>.
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Let us consider four of the less-obvious links
above:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Link 3: Consciousness_ is the consciousness
moving from one life to the next. Having left the body of the last life, it is
in the _bardo_ or in-between state. It carries with it all of its past,
including all the karmic programming generated by actions in the previous life.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Link 4: _Name and Form_ is another way of saying
the five aggregates or, to put it simply, the new life, once the _bardo_
is over. _Form_ covers the tangible aspects and means the new body whereas
_Name_ means the intangible things--mind--in the sense of feelings,
cognition, mental events and consciousness. In this link the _bardo_
consciousness has joined the sperm and ovum of the parents to make a new
sentient being. Although technically the new life has started, there are not
yet eyes, ears, nose and so forth and so many aspects of consciousness and
cognition are only there nominally. That is one of the reasons it is called _Name_.
</paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Link 5: Six Perceptual Gateways_ develop as the body
of the foetus  grows, enabling its world to be perceived. As the ear and brain
develop, a "gateway" opens to the world of sound and likewise for the other
four fields of the senses: sights, odours, flavours, tactile sensations. The
sixth perceptual gateway is that of the mind. This has two aspects, the first of
which is simply to receive and process inputs from the five senses. It is a
little like a switchboard, with attention shifting continuously from one sense
to another, first to sound, then to physical sensations, then to odour and so
on and so forth. The second aspect of the mental perceptual gateway is for
mind, as a subject, to be aware of mind as an object. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>To illustrate this, if just now you think of a
childhood memory, then your mind, the thinker, is contemplating its object,
another aspect of your mind, its memory. Just as your power to see opens out to
the world through the gateway of vision to the world of visible objects, so
does your mental power to be aware open out through the mental perceptual
gateway to the world of things you can be aware of<a href="#_ftn31">[31]</a>.  If we apply this to the
newly-conceived child, then while still in the womb, there is already a sense
of identity within the child and there are mental reactions to the environment
of the womb. With birth comes a whole new set of subject-object situations at
play in the baby's mind. With the acquisition of language, names can be given
to the various components of the already-established mental landscape. With
time, this becomes the inner dialogue about self and other.<a href="#_ftn32">[32]</a>   </paragraph>
               <paragraph>_Link 10: Becoming_ maybe does not sound
as important as it is. It covers _all_ the actions of the present
lifetime, in other terms all the karma created in the present lifetime. These
actions contribute, one by one and inescapably, to creating the future person.
By performing actions, we are becoming what we will be in the future. Some
people sensitive enough to be aware of the process, will feel that
all-important shift from being inclined to do something (link 9, intense mental
involvement and grasping) to actually giving way to the impulse and performing
the action. This critical step is what link 10, becoming, is all about. By
creating karma (action), we not only give reality to what we have thus far only
imagined but we also have made a future: we are _becoming_ what we will
be.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Having clarified these three links, let us
return to the overall process of the twelve steps of interdependence. In one
discourse, the _Rice Shoot Sutra_, the Buddha uses the example of a rice
plant to illustrate interdependence:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Bhikkhus! Whoever understands this rice shoot
understands interdependent origination. Whoever understands interdependent
origination understands the nature of phenomena. Whoever understands phenomena
understands buddhahood.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Monks! Through the existence of this, this will arise.
Through this having arisen, (then) this arises. That is how it is. Through the
condition of ignorance, there will be creations<a href="#_ftn33">[33]</a> ... etc. (up to) ... there
will be birth and through that condition there will be ageing and death,
sufferings and lamentations, pain, mental stress and upsets. That is how this
great cluster of nothing but misery is produced.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>In the above quotation, one needs to imagine
the Buddha holding a rice seed in one hand and a rice shoot in the other. Note,
in passing, that the Buddha does not say, "This seed makes a shoot" but more
accurately points out that _once there is this_ (the seed) _then there
will be this _(the shoot).</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The\Twelve Links of Liberation"
                           pagetitle="The\Twelve Links of Liberation"
                           tocentry="The\Twelve Links of Liberation">
               <paragraph>By understanding the billiard-ball effect of
one thing triggering another in the twelve links described above, one has the
key to sabotaging the whole process of suffering. The removal of any one link
means that none of the following links can happen. This means:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
Removing
link 11 prevents link 12</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
Removing
link 10 prevents link 11 &amp; 12 etc. up to</paragraph>
               <paragraph>·     
Removing
link 1 removes links 2 - 12</paragraph>
               <paragraph>In particular:</paragraph>
               <table class="MsoNormalTable">
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Action*</td>
                        <td>*Prevents
  this link*</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Wise action* (link 10, becoming
  ) in this life will avoid the ten non-virtues and therefore links 11 and
  12--unfortunate rebirth and suffering, due to non-virtuous actions--cannot
  occur. Until someone has completely transcended all samsaric action, there
  will still be rebirth, link 11, but in fortunate circumstances due to
  virtuous karma. </td>
                        <td>11 &amp; 12</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Self-control* in the sense of not
  giving way to thoughts and impulses (link 9) will prevent non-virtuous karma</td>
                        <td>10</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Mindfulness and meditation* help one be aware
  of how craving (link 8) for certain experiences of the mind or of the senses
  leads into intense mental activity (link 9) around those things craved for or
  detested. One learns to not let the mind wander into and dwell within those
  danger zones.</td>
                        <td>9</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*"Snipping it in the bud"* meditation
  practices create the skill of immediately recognising when feelings (link 7)
  give rise to craving and of cutting off, in the instant, the processes described
  above.</td>
                        <td>8</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Bardo *instruction<a href="#_ftn34">[34]</a> helps someone use
  consciousness skillfully to find a better rebirth. These are special
  vajrayana instructions, not part of the general twelve-links teachings. They
  help the transitions from links 2 to 3 and from links 10 to 11 to happen in a
  more helpful way.</td>
                        <td>3 or 11</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Purification practices* help one to modify
  the content of conditioning carried in the universal basis consciousness
  (link 3) and this will change the type of existence one will be reborn into.</td>
                        <td>4</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>*Voidness wisdom<a href="#_ftn35">[35]</a>* tackles the very
  root of samsara--ignorance (link 1). It is the best--the most radical--way to
  tackle suffering. In the Hinayana, this means understanding the voidness of
  ego. In the Mahayana, it means understanding the voidness of everything. One
  cannot overestimate the importance of centreing efforts on achieving direct
  realisation of voidness, as this solves all the problem of samsara in one
  fell swoop. When samsara, in all its complexity, is compared to a mighty,
  long-standing tree, then this is the equivalent of severing its trunk.</td>
                        <td>2</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <paragraph>The _Treatise on Interdependence_ says:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Also, to exemplify this: ignorance is like the
one who sows a seed, karma is like the field, consciousness like the seed
itself, grasping is like moisture, name and form like a shoot and the remaining
links are like the branches and leaves (of the plant).</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Were ignorance not to occur, creation and so
forth could not occur ... (etc. up to) ... and were birth not to happen then
ageing and death could not occur. </paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="No\one's &#34;fault&#34;" pagetitle="No\one's &#34;fault&#34;"
                           tocentry="No\one's &#34;fault&#34;">
               <paragraph>The Buddha, in his great compassion, simply
pointed out that this is the way things happen. In the Rice Shoot Sutra, he put
his finger on it, "Once there is _this_, then there will be _this_."
Suffering and happiness are not the punishments and gifts of God, or of the
gods. In many ways, the sufferings are not even the creation of the person one
was in the previous life: who would intentionally create future sufferings for
themselves? Simply, one thing inevitably leads to another, in a world confused
by ignorance. Fortunately, just now, we have the intelligence to be able to
understand the process and to do something about it. In this context, Gampopa says:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>In these processes, ignorance does not plot,
thinking, _I will make creations truly manifest_, nor do the creations
have a mind which thinks, _We were made to manifest by, and created by,
ignorance_ ... etc. Likewise birth does not plot, thinking, _I will make
ageing and death truly happen_ nor do ageing and death consider themselves
actually brought into being by birth. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>Nevertheless, it is through the existence of
ignorance that creations and so forth do become manifest realities and will
occur and, likewise, through the existence of birth that ageing and death are
made manifest and will happen. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>The twelve links described above, are
sometimes known as _outer interdependence_, since they deal with the world
that we see, hear and touch. _Inner interdependence_ adds another
dimension--one which resembles very much our modern physics.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
         <subsection title="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements"
                     pagetitle="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements"
                     tocentry="Inner interdependence: the Six Elements">
            <paragraph>Inner interdependent origination concerns general
conditions, on an atomic level, rather than the prime causes in the tangible
world, discussed above<a href="#_ftn36">[36]</a>.
</paragraph>
            <paragraph>It may seem surprising to use the word
"atomic" here but that was precisely what was being discussed in Buddhist and
other circles in India two thousand years ago. People speculated, with great
intelligence, about what unchangeable components could be present in the
tiniest of particles. In Buddhism, these components are known as:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)The Six Elements(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)1.     Matter(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)2.     Bonding(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)3.     Energy(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)4.     Movement(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)5.     Space(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>(eh)6.     Consciousness(eeh)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>These were given respectively the symbolic
names _earth element, water element, fire element, wind element, space
element and consciousness element_.</paragraph>
            <subsubsection title="The Indian System\of the Elements"
                           pagetitle="The Indian System\of the Elements"
                           tocentry="The Indian System\of the Elements">
               <paragraph>The
Buddha's teachings, 2,500 years ago, contributed to an already vigorous debate
concerning the nature of matter, on its molecular level. The five elements, as
they appear in Buddhism, are five universal components of all things animate or
inanimate. They are each present in all material realities and one must be
careful not to be misled by their simple names. The element 'fire' (see below)
is really the energy present in a reality. This can be latent, stored-up energy
or energy actually in the process of being released. Thus the 'fire' element is
present in ice, in cold rock and so forth--anything that has reserves of energy--without
any need for flames or heat. Actual fire is, of course, one vivid example of
energy being released. Likewise, 'earth', 'water' and 'wind', as we experience
them in everyday life, are metaphors of what those elements represent on a more
subtle level.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)<img id="_x0000_i1026" width="13" src="module3_files/image029.png"/>   EARTH element.
  MATTER    This is the material body of a situation.
It is the ground state, the basis. Its qualities are stability, firmness,
resistance, heaviness and slowness. On a non-universal level, and more
specifically in the body, the earth element is most apparent as the flesh and
bones of the bodily frame and its organs, which constitute the basis for life.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)<img id="_x0000_i1027" width="18" src="module3_files/image030.png"/>   WATER element.
     BONDS/RELATIONS/FLUIDITY       Matter
would just collapse were not all of its components held in relation with each
other by all sorts of forces. The water element connects things, severally,
and, by the very nature of the connections, enables flow and change and the
'elasticity' of coming closer and drawing apart. In the body, the water element
is most obviously manifest as the bodily fluids ensuring its maintenance and
correct functioning. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)<img id="_x0000_i1028" width="18" src="module3_files/image031.png"/>   FIRE
element.        ENERGY, latent or
manifest         Each situation
has its potential. There are also times when this potential is being released:
times of change when the old state is consumed and a new one created. In the
human body, the fire element is most manifest in the process of nourishment, in
which foodstuffs are transformed into the energy needed by the body and, in
turn, this energy is used to enable body and mind to function properly.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)<img id="_x0000_i1029" width="18" src="module3_files/image032.png"/>    WIND
element.          MOVEMENT       All
matter is in movement and movement provokes change. Life is a constant flux and
each situation has its own dynamics and forces. In the human body, the wind
element is most manifest as the respiratory system and as the various
intentional and unintentional movements of the body. On another level, it is
the flows of the blood, the nervous system, the endocrine system etc. (eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)<img id="_x0000_i1030" width="18" src="module3_files/image033.png"/>    SPACE
element.       Unlike the other elements,
which are in constant interaction, increasing and decreasing, space is simply the
constant, unchanging backdrop or _dimension_ that enables all the others
to exist and to operate. In the human body, it is the particularly linked to
the inner cavities and bodily orifices.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>(eh)CONSCIOUSNESS
element. The five elements as described above were part of scientific
speculation in India thousands of years ago. Buddhism added a sixth element,
that of consciousness. It is comprised of the five sense consciousnesses and the
tainted mental consciousness. These will be described in a later module.(eeh)</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Although
not having our present-day means of investigation to confirm their theories,
the sages of ancient India had our main tool: intelligence. They believed the
universe to be--on an atomic level--a vast interdependence of matter, energy,
movement and bonding. This ever-changing atomic maelstrom appears--on a gross
level--as all the trees, rocks, ocean and living beings we perceive. A human
body is a highly-complex manifestation of the five elements, just as the
universe in which that body moves is an immensely complex manifestation of the
five elements. On the atomic level, they share a similar character and depend
upon similar things. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>In Tibetan Medicine and Science, one finds two major Asian
systems of the elements:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1031" width="10" src="module3_files/image034.png"/>   The
<a href="../../../../Web/khenpoeu/tara/elements.html#indian">Indian</a> system, as described above,
in which they appear primarily as the five fundamental components of all
relative phenomena, corresponding to what, on one level, we would currently
call matter, bonding, thermodynamics, kinesis and space. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1032" width="10" src="module3_files/image035.png"/>   In
the
<a href="../../../../Web/khenpoeu/tara/elements.html#chinese">Chinese</a> system, they appear not as
a description of the _status quo_ but to show the dynamics of things. They
correspond to the four general phases of most life cycles and to an underlying
ground state. The four phases are: initial growth, maturation, decomposition
and resorption into the whole. This applies on all sorts of levels and over all
sorts of timescales, from the molecular right up to the duration of a human
life.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Although
not strictly part of our Buddhist studies, below is a resumé of the Chinese
system of the elements, as integrated into Tibetan sciences.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
            <subsubsection title="The Chinese System of the Elements"
                           pagetitle="The Chinese System of the Elements"
                           tocentry="The Chinese System of the Elements">
               <paragraph>The
names are similar to those of the system above, except that metal replaces
space and wood is the name for wind.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1033" width="18" src="module3_files/image036.png"/>     WOOD
element.       INITIAL APPEARANCE AND
GROWTH      Wood is used here in the sense of the
tender green shoots of spring, denoting the appearance of the new. That which
at first starts as a few signs of a new reality gradually takes shape and
strength, like branches growing or buds appearing out of the earth. This is
closely related to the WIND element above, wind being the vector of change. On
a constant level within the human metabolism, the circulation (represented by
the wind element) of oxygen, blood and other bodily fluids brings a constant
renewal of the system. It is particularly connected with the working of the
liver and the gall-bladder. Major changes - such as conception, puberty,
menopause etc. - are heralded by changes in this element. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1034" width="18" src="module3_files/image037.png"/>     FIRE
element.       ACHIEVING
FULLNESS          This is
very similar to the fire element as explained above. As the Chinese system
deals more with the dynamic aspect of this element, here it is more concerned
with the release of potential and the coming to fullness of a situation. To use
the analogy of summer and harvests ripening, the crops reach maturity and, by
the same token, create the seeds of future realities. In the human body the
fire element is highly related to the metabolic process, to the heart and the small
intestine.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1035" width="13" src="module3_files/image038.png"/>   METAL
element (represented by a sword).     DISAGGREGATION
&amp; DECAY    This is the destructive (one can also see it
as pre-regenerative) phase of the cycle. Having reached fullness, a situation
deteriorates, its constituent elements gradually fall apart and take other
directions, become parts of other things. This phase is, of course, typified by
autumn. In the body, it is associated with the lungs and the large intestine.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1036" width="18" src="module3_files/image039.png"/>   WATER
element.     CLEANSING, DESTRUCTION &amp; POOL OF
POTENTIAL     Typified by winter, this is the latent
stage of the cycle, in which things decompose and then lie dormant as the
various constituents of what will manifest in the spring. In the body, this
element is related to the kidneys and the bladder.</paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <img id="_x0000_i1037" width="13" src="module3_files/image040.png"/>   EARTH
element.    THE BASIS, THE BACKDROP     In
the parade of the seasons, the earth element occurs four times, i.e. in between
the other seasons. We can interpret this as indicating a basic state of
affairs, which can be glimpsed when the more dramatic phases of the cycle are
not dominant. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>There
is a natural order in these elements and there are natural affinities and
conflicts between them. It is obvious that a great release of energy will
perturb the dormant state of a latent potential. Thus fire is the 'enemy' of
water. That latent state of potential is the very source of what will happen as
new realities take shape. Thus water is the 'mother' of wood. Four main types
of relationship are described: *mother, child, enemy and friend*,
represented in the table below:</paragraph>
               <table width="498" class="MsoNormalTable">
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td/>
                        <td>MOTHER </td>
                        <td>CHILD</td>
                        <td>ENEMY</td>
                        <td>FRIEND</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>WOOD</td>
                        <td>water</td>
                        <td>fire</td>
                        <td>metal</td>
                        <td>earth</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>FIRE</td>
                        <td>wood</td>
                        <td>earth</td>
                        <td>water</td>
                        <td>metal</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>EARTH</td>
                        <td>fire</td>
                        <td>metal</td>
                        <td>wood</td>
                        <td>water</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>METAL</td>
                        <td>earth</td>
                        <td>water</td>
                        <td>fire</td>
                        <td>wood</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>WATER</td>
                        <td>metal</td>
                        <td>wood</td>
                        <td>earth</td>
                        <td>fire</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
               <paragraph>Recalling the Indian, Buddhist, system of the
elements, let us return now to Gampopa:</paragraph>
               <paragraph>Without the above condition of the six elements,
a body cannot come into being. Furthermore, the presence of all six inner
elements is universal and hence comprises everything. It is due to them that
the body will have its actual manifest existence. </paragraph>
               <paragraph>In these (processes), the six elements do not
think, _I will establish the body's firmness_ etc. and neither does the
body think, _I am generated by these specific conditions_. Nevertheless,
it is through these specific conditions that the body--life--occurs in all the
ways it does.</paragraph>
            </subsubsection>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </chapter>
</book>